<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sadique Ali</title>
    <link>http://sdqali.in/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sadique Ali</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2015 15:57:30 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://sdqali.in/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Integration testing Spring command line applications</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/12/11/integration-testing-spring-command-line-applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2015 15:57:30 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/12/11/integration-testing-spring-command-line-applications/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&#34;http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/12/10/integration-testing-challenges-for-non-web-spring-applications/&#34;&gt;last blog post&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote about the challenges of writing an integration test for a Spring command line application. One of the solutions for this issue discussed in the blog post was to use the &lt;code&gt;@IntegrationTest&lt;/code&gt; annotations to inject Java system properties and use that to run the application instead of the normal command line arguments. This blog post describes how to perform this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is to rewrite our test to use the &lt;code&gt;@IntegrationTest&lt;/code&gt; annotations. This will result in a test that looks as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;@RunWith(SpringJUnit4ClassRunner.class)
@SpringApplicationConfiguration(classes = {Application.class})
@IntegrationTest(value = &amp;quot;input:expectedOutput&amp;quot;)
public class ApplicationIntegrationTest {
    @Autowired
    private Application application;

    @Rule
    public OutputCapture outputCapture = new OutputCapture();

    @Test
    public void shouldGenerateResultFiles() throws Exception {
        application.run();
        assertTrue(outputCapture.toString().contains(&amp;quot;expectedOutput&amp;quot;));
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, it is worth taking a look at what the &lt;code&gt;@IntegrationTest&lt;/code&gt; annotation causes Spring to do. This is a meta-annotation &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7dbd0b0b8fa67b28f9dffc46ddaee5e0:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7dbd0b0b8fa67b28f9dffc46ddaee5e0:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that specifies a number of test listeners including &lt;code&gt;IntegrationTestPropertiesListener&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;@Documented
@Inherited
@Retention(RetentionPolicy.RUNTIME)
@Target(ElementType.TYPE)
@TestExecutionListeners(listeners = { IntegrationTestPropertiesListener.class,
        DirtiesContextBeforeModesTestExecutionListener.class,
        DependencyInjectionTestExecutionListener.class,
        DirtiesContextTestExecutionListener.class,
        TransactionalTestExecutionListener.class, SqlScriptsTestExecutionListener.class })
public @interface IntegrationTest {
    String[] value() default {};
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;IntegrationTestPropertiesListener&lt;/code&gt; is an implementation of &lt;code&gt;TestExecutionListener&lt;/code&gt; which is a mechanism used by Spring to react to test execution events like &lt;code&gt;beforeTestClass&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;prepareTestInstance&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;beforeTestMethod&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;beforeTestMethod&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;afterTestClass&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of what we are trying to achieve, the listener we are really interested in is the &lt;code&gt;beforeTestClass&lt;/code&gt; of &lt;code&gt;IntegrationTestPropertiesListener&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;    @Override
    public void prepareTestInstance(TestContext testContext) throws Exception {
        Class&amp;lt;?&amp;gt; testClass = testContext.getTestClass();
        AnnotationAttributes annotationAttributes = AnnotatedElementUtils
                .getMergedAnnotationAttributes(testClass,
                        IntegrationTest.class.getName());
        if (annotationAttributes != null) {
            addPropertySourceProperties(testContext,
                    annotationAttributes.getStringArray(&amp;quot;value&amp;quot;));
        }
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see, the value of the &lt;code&gt;value&lt;/code&gt; element &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7dbd0b0b8fa67b28f9dffc46ddaee5e0:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7dbd0b0b8fa67b28f9dffc46ddaee5e0:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of our &lt;code&gt;@IntegrationTest&lt;/code&gt; gets injected to the configuration of the test context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have understood and used the &lt;code&gt;@IntegrationTest&lt;/code&gt; annotation to push in configuration, it is time to make our application consume this configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;@Configuration
@EnableAutoConfiguration
@ComponentScan
public class Application implements CommandLineRunner {
    @Autowired
    DataService dataService;

    @Value(&amp;quot;${input}&amp;quot;)
    String input;

    public static void main(String[] args) {
        SpringApplication.run(Application.class, args);
    }

    @Override
    public void run(String... args) {
        dataService.perform(input);
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An added benefit of this approach is that this forces us to use named parameter arguments when running the application as opposed to the position based command line arguments. This of course does not solve the problem of testing if you absolutely have to use position based arguments for your application. It would be nice Spring provided a mechanism to inject the command line arguments in a test before &lt;code&gt;SpringApplicationContextLoader&lt;/code&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7dbd0b0b8fa67b28f9dffc46ddaee5e0:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7dbd0b0b8fa67b28f9dffc46ddaee5e0:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; took over. But I suspect that this is not a common enough use case of Spring that users have asked the Spring team to implement it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7dbd0b0b8fa67b28f9dffc46ddaee5e0:1&#34;&gt;Meta annotations are Spring annotations that can modify and act up on other annotations. For an example of customizing behavior using meta annotations, see &lt;a href=&#34;http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/12/06/implementing-custom-annotations-for-spring-mvc/&#34;&gt;this blog post&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7dbd0b0b8fa67b28f9dffc46ddaee5e0:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7dbd0b0b8fa67b28f9dffc46ddaee5e0:2&#34;&gt;The tendency of programmers to name the default element of an annotation &lt;code&gt;value&lt;/code&gt; is one of my least favorite aspects of Java annotations. In most cases, there is another name that conveys the intent of the element better. I plan to write my thoughts about this in a blog post soon.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7dbd0b0b8fa67b28f9dffc46ddaee5e0:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7dbd0b0b8fa67b28f9dffc46ddaee5e0:3&#34;&gt;See the previous blog post to see how &lt;code&gt;SpringApplicationContextLoader&lt;/code&gt; executes the application without arguments.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7dbd0b0b8fa67b28f9dffc46ddaee5e0:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integration testing challenges for non-web Spring applications</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/12/10/integration-testing-challenges-for-non-web-spring-applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2015 21:45:59 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/12/10/integration-testing-challenges-for-non-web-spring-applications/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are building a command line data loader application at work that uses Spring. One of the things that I took us more time that it should have to figure out was how to write an integration test that invokes the command line application with the right command line arguments. This blog post describes this scenario and a potential solution to this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s consider a simple command line application implemented using Spring Boot&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;CommandLineRunner&lt;/code&gt;. The main application class is fairly simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;
@Configuration
@EnableAutoConfiguration
@ComponentScan
public class Application implements CommandLineRunner {
    @Autowired
    DataService dataService;

    public static void main(String[] args) {
        SpringApplication.run(Application.class, args);
    }

    @Override
    public void run(String... args) {
        dataService.perform(args[0]);
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to this, there is a configuration class &lt;code&gt;AppConfiguration&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;@Configuration
public class AppConfiguration {
    @Bean
    public DataService dataService() {
        return new DataService();
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;DataService&lt;/code&gt; simply prints the argument it receives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;public class DataService {
    public void perform(String arg) {
        System.out.println(arg);
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we were to attempt writing an integration test for this application, it would look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;@RunWith(SpringJUnit4ClassRunner.class)
@SpringApplicationConfiguration(classes = {Application.class})
public class ApplicationIntegrationTest {
    @Autowired
    private Application application;


    @Rule
    public OutputCapture outputCapture = new OutputCapture();

    @Test
    public void shouldGenerateResultFiles() throws Exception {
        application.run(&amp;quot;sampleOutPut&amp;quot;);
        assertTrue(outputCapture.toString().contains(&amp;quot;sampleOutput&amp;quot;));
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That test is straightforward—it loads the Spring context with all the beans, runs the application with parameters and expects the parameter to be printed to the console.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except, it does not work. If we were to execute the above test, we will get the following error:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;...
Caused by: java.lang.ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException: 0
at in.sdqali.springapps.Application.run(Application.java:24) ~[main/:na]
...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened? It looks like the &lt;code&gt;run&lt;/code&gt; method was called with out any arguments while the test configuration was loaded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let‘s try and understand wh
y this happens. Remember how we annotated the test with &lt;code&gt;@SpringApplicationConfiguration&lt;/code&gt;? This annotation is a meta-annotation &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1944f35ca6adb86a80e399600f75145d:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1944f35ca6adb86a80e399600f75145d:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; specified as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;@ContextConfiguration(loader = SpringApplicationContextLoader.class)
@Documented
@Inherited
@Retention(RetentionPolicy.RUNTIME)
@Target(ElementType.TYPE)
public @interface SpringApplicationConfiguration {
...
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ContextConfiguration&lt;/code&gt; is an annotation that allows tests to specify the information used to load and configure the application context. From the Java doc for this annotation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; * {@code @ContextConfiguration} defines class-level metadata that is used to determine
 * how to load and configure an {@link org.springframework.context.ApplicationContext
 * ApplicationContext} for integration tests.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us to &lt;code&gt;SpringApplicationContextLoader&lt;/code&gt;‘s &lt;code&gt;loadContext&lt;/code&gt; method and buried deep inside are these line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;application.setInitializers(initializers);
ConfigurableApplicationContext applicationContext = application.run();
return applicationContext;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, regardless of how many arguments our command line application was supposed to take, this loader always call the application without any arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two solutions I have been able to think of for this problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Override the&lt;code&gt;SpringApplicationContextLoader&lt;/code&gt; and pass the necessary arguments in &lt;code&gt;application.run()&lt;/code&gt;. This is definitely not an elegant or easy solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use an environment variable instead of the command line argument as the input to the service. This will allow us to inject this variable using the &lt;code&gt;@IntegrationTest&lt;/code&gt; annotation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My next blog post will discuss the second approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1944f35ca6adb86a80e399600f75145d:1&#34;&gt;Meta annotations. &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.spring.io/spring/docs/current/spring-framework-reference/html/beans.html#beans-meta-annotations&#34;&gt;Spring documentation&lt;/a&gt;. To see how to use meta-annotations to write custom annoations, see &lt;a href=&#34;http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/12/06/implementing-custom-annotations-for-spring-mvc/&#34;&gt;this blog post&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1944f35ca6adb86a80e399600f75145d:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How thinking of Documentation as Legislation helped me become a better programmer</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/12/07/how-thinking-of-documentation-as-legislation-helped-me-become-a-better-programmer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2015 20:43:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/12/07/how-thinking-of-documentation-as-legislation-helped-me-become-a-better-programmer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I first started programming, it was predominantly creating applications that utilized the C++ graphics library. I was 14 and my friends and I tried to make the most of the time we got to spend at the computer lab of the boarding school we attended. We created applications that drew pretty, often animated pictures on the screen and not much else. This taught us basics, but our learning lacked any kind of structure. We read and figured out just enough to do what we wanted to do. There was no guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I went to college and ended up pursuing a degree in Electronics and Instrumentation, most of the programming I did was against a few micro-controller architectures and the odd C programming class. I learned a lot, but I did not delve in to the inner details of things. By the time I started working, I was a good programmer, but deep inside I always had the fear that I was faking it and that I was not good enough. When I had to solve things in new languages and technologies I often tried to find solutions that I could learn from and adapt as opposed to diving deep in to the details and inner workings of things. I was afraid that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to handle it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At around the time I went to college, I had become really drawn to the legislative process and how legislation evolved. Interests in certain topics like the constant legal tussle that the Republic of India engaged with it&amp;rsquo;s States on the topic of the National Language &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:a5afb5dc33b2fc67590eea4a9e3c0e13:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:a5afb5dc33b2fc67590eea4a9e3c0e13:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; compelled me to read the related legislation and court rulings. I slowly discovered that even though I was neither a student of Political Science nor a lawyer, I could understand legislation and court orders well enough because they were so specific—specific to the point of being boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This prompted me to look at documentation in another light. From being unnecessarily complex in my view, they became specific and often the place to see answers for contentious topics that brought conflicting interpretations from different people. Around this time, I had started reading the R.F.C.s &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:a5afb5dc33b2fc67590eea4a9e3c0e13:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:a5afb5dc33b2fc67590eea4a9e3c0e13:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of the I.E.T.F. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:a5afb5dc33b2fc67590eea4a9e3c0e13:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:a5afb5dc33b2fc67590eea4a9e3c0e13:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and it convinced me that well written documentation has the same qualities as well written legislation—specificity, context and lending themselves to being represented as change-sets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has had tremendously positive effect on my programming—instead of being afraid of diving deep and understanding for myself how a particular programming language feature or library or protocol specification, I see it something that I can understand really well if I spend enough time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have since come across projects that look at this similarity from the other side. There are multiple projects that tries to represent and record constitutions and legislation as version controlled repositories. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.abevoelker.com/gitlaw-github-for-laws-and-legal-documents-a-tourniquet-for-american-liberty/&#34;&gt;GitLaw&lt;/a&gt; idea has taken off with multiple version-controlled repositories of legislation—examples include &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/xlfe/gitlaw-au&#34;&gt;Australia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Br3nda/legislation&#34;&gt;New Zealand&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bundestag/gesetze&#34;&gt;Germany&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:a5afb5dc33b2fc67590eea4a9e3c0e13:1&#34;&gt;The topic of the National Language was a hot–button issue in the political landscape of the nascent independent Republic of India. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Official_Languages_Act,_1963&#34;&gt;Official Languages Act of 1963&lt;/a&gt; is an example of legislation associated with this struggle.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:a5afb5dc33b2fc67590eea4a9e3c0e13:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:a5afb5dc33b2fc67590eea4a9e3c0e13:2&#34;&gt;Request for Comments are publications of the I.E.T.F. Read more on &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Request_for_Comments&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:a5afb5dc33b2fc67590eea4a9e3c0e13:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:a5afb5dc33b2fc67590eea4a9e3c0e13:3&#34;&gt;Internet Engineering Task Force develops and promotes Internet standards. Read more on &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Engineering_Task_Force&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:a5afb5dc33b2fc67590eea4a9e3c0e13:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing custom annotations for Spring MVC</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/12/06/implementing-custom-annotations-for-spring-mvc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2015 13:28:26 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/12/06/implementing-custom-annotations-for-spring-mvc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I often have to work with Spring MVC based code bases that have been living for a while. One of the common trait of these code bases I have observed is the repeated use of the same Spring annotations to achieve the same effect again and again. A really good example of this is annotating a controller method with a combination of &lt;code&gt;@RequestMapping&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;@ResponseStatus&lt;/code&gt; to set the expected request and response &lt;code&gt;Content-Type&lt;/code&gt;, the request Method, response status etc. This blog post describes how to compose Spring annotations that produce the same effect as multiple Spring annotations acting together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the new things introduced in Spring 4 was the idea of meta-annotations. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:b72714563591dcee83238042a831f26c:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:b72714563591dcee83238042a831f26c:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Meta annotations are annotations that can act up on other annotations by modifying and overriding attributes of the target annotations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows us to build composed annotations &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:b72714563591dcee83238042a831f26c:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:b72714563591dcee83238042a831f26c:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that combine the behavior of multiple annotations. The &lt;code&gt;@AliasFor&lt;/code&gt; annotation allows us to override attribute names, thereby adding great flexibility while composing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a common pattern in code bases that use Spring MVC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;    @RequestMapping(path = &amp;quot;/register&amp;quot;,
            method = RequestMethod.POST,
            consumes = MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE,
            produces = MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE
    )
    @ResponseStatus(HttpStatus.CREATED)
    public Map register(@RequestBody @Valid EmailRequest emailRequest) {
        return registrationService.register(emailRequest);
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two annotations as applied on this method represent the fact that this is an end point that a client can &lt;code&gt;POST&lt;/code&gt; JSON to and produces JSON and a &lt;code&gt;201 Created&lt;/code&gt; HTTP status when it succeeds. If we had 20 end points that did the similar operations, it would be really useful to have a &lt;code&gt;@PostJson&lt;/code&gt; annotation that did the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is one way of writing such an annotation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;@Target(METHOD)
@Retention(RUNTIME)
@Documented
@RequestMapping(method = RequestMethod.POST,
        consumes = MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE,
        produces = MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE
)
@ResponseStatus(HttpStatus.CREATED)
public @interface PostJson {
    @AliasFor(annotation = RequestMapping.class, attribute = &amp;quot;path&amp;quot;)
    String[] path() default {};
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This annotation takes a single parameter &lt;code&gt;path&lt;/code&gt; that represents that URL path to which it will respond to. This can now be applied on the register end point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;    @PostJson(path = &amp;quot;/register&amp;quot;)
    public Map register(@RequestBody @Valid EmailRequest emailRequest) {
        return registrationService.register(emailRequest);
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we wanted to allow the consumers of &lt;code&gt;@PostJson&lt;/code&gt; to override other parameters of &lt;code&gt;@RequestMapping&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;@ResponseStatus&lt;/code&gt;, it can be achieved by adding more aliases. For example, the following will allow users to specify a reason phrase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;    @AliasFor(annotation = ResponseStatus.class, attribute = &amp;quot;reason&amp;quot;)
    String[] reason() default {};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pattern can easily be extended to introduce annotations like &lt;code&gt;@GetJson&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;@PutJson&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;@PostXml&lt;/code&gt; and so on and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:b72714563591dcee83238042a831f26c:1&#34;&gt;Meta annotations. &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.spring.io/spring/docs/current/spring-framework-reference/html/beans.html#beans-meta-annotations&#34;&gt;Spring documentation&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:b72714563591dcee83238042a831f26c:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:b72714563591dcee83238042a831f26c:2&#34;&gt;Composed annotations. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/spring-projects/spring-framework/wiki/Spring-Annotation-Programming-Model#composed-annotations&#34;&gt;Spring documentation&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:b72714563591dcee83238042a831f26c:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Validating RequestParams and PathVariables in Spring MVC</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/12/04/validating-requestparams-and-pathvariables-in-spring-mvc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2015 22:50:24 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/12/04/validating-requestparams-and-pathvariables-in-spring-mvc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Spring MVC provides a convenient way to validate inputs to API end points through the use of &lt;code&gt;JSR-303&lt;/code&gt; annotations. While this mechanism works great for end points that consume a &lt;code&gt;RequestBody&lt;/code&gt; (as is the case with most &lt;code&gt;POST&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;PUT&lt;/code&gt; requests), it is not easy to achieve the same effect for end points that consume primitives in the form of path variables or request parameters (as is the case with most &lt;code&gt;GET&lt;/code&gt; requests).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at how to validate RequestBody inputs using JSR-303.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;    @RequestMapping(method = RequestMethod.POST,
            consumes = MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE,
            produces = MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE
    )
    @ResponseStatus(HttpStatus.OK)
    public Map register(@RequestBody @Valid EmailRequest emailRequest) {
        return registrationService.register(emailRequest);
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value object &lt;code&gt;EmailRequest&lt;/code&gt; is annotated with the appropriate constraint annotations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;public class EmailRequest {
    @Email
    public String email;

    private EmailRequest() {
    }

    public String getEmail() {
        return email;
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we were to attempt a similar approach for a &lt;code&gt;GET&lt;/code&gt; end point that accepts a &lt;code&gt;RequestParam&lt;/code&gt;, the validation would simply not happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;    @RequestMapping(method = RequestMethod.GET,
            consumes = MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE,
            produces = MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE
    )
    @ResponseStatus(HttpStatus.OK)
    public Map search(@Email
                   @Valid
                   @RequestParam(&amp;quot;email&amp;quot;)
                   String email) {
        return emailMessage(email);
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where Spring&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;@Validated&lt;/code&gt; annotation is useful. With &lt;code&gt;@Validated&lt;/code&gt;, we can validate request parameters and path variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;@RestController
@Validated
public class RegistrationController {
    @RequestMapping(method = RequestMethod.GET,
            consumes = MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE,
            produces = MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE
    )
    @ResponseStatus(HttpStatus.OK)
    public Map search(@Email
                   @RequestParam(&amp;quot;email&amp;quot;)
                   String email) {
        return emailMessage(email);
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important thing to note here is that using &lt;code&gt;@Valid&lt;/code&gt; annotation results in &lt;code&gt;MethodArgumentNotValidException&lt;/code&gt; being thrown when validation fails, but &lt;code&gt;@Validated&lt;/code&gt; results in &lt;code&gt;ConstraintViolationException&lt;/code&gt; being thrown. Since these exceptions have different ways of abstracting the error messages associated with validation, it is important to have different error handlers for both of these. An example pattern using &lt;code&gt;ExceptionHandler&lt;/code&gt; will be as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;@ControllerAdvice
@Component
public class GlobalExceptionHandler {
    @ExceptionHandler
    @ResponseBody
    @ResponseStatus(HttpStatus.BAD_REQUEST)
    public Map handle(MethodArgumentNotValidException exception) {
        return error(exception.getBindingResult().getFieldErrors()
                .stream()
                .map(FieldError::getDefaultMessage)
                .collect(Collectors.toList()));
    }


    @ExceptionHandler
    @ResponseBody
    @ResponseStatus(HttpStatus.BAD_REQUEST)
    public Map handle(ConstraintViolationException exception) {
        return error(exception.getConstraintViolations()
                .stream()
                .map(ConstraintViolation::getMessage)
                .collect(Collectors.toList()));
    }

    private Map error(Object message) {
        return Collections.singletonMap(&amp;quot;error&amp;quot;, message);
    }
}

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing async responses using MockMvc</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/11/24/testing-async-responses-using-mockmvc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2015 05:45:06 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/11/24/testing-async-responses-using-mockmvc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are times when a Spring MVC end point performs asynchronous operations. Testing these end points using MockMvc can be tricky because of the asynchronous nature in which the result of the operation is eventually returned. This blog post describes how to write tests in such scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at the following example. In this example, we have a simple end point that responds with a JSON object when invoked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;@RestController
@RequestMapping(&amp;quot;/test&amp;quot;)
class ExampleController {
    @RequestMapping(value = &amp;quot;/hello&amp;quot;,
            method = GET,
            consumes = APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE,
            produces = APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE)
    @ResponseStatus(OK)
    public Map&amp;lt;String, Object&amp;gt; hello(){
        return helloMessage();
    }

    private Map&amp;lt;String, Object&amp;gt; helloMessage() {
        return Collections.singletonMap(&amp;quot;message&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;hello&amp;quot;);
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing a MockMvc test for this controller is fairly simple. The following test invokes the end point and asserts that the end point returns:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The right HTTP response code &lt;code&gt;200&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The right Content-Type &lt;code&gt;application/json&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The right JSON message&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;@RunWith(MockitoJUnitRunner.class)
public class ExampleControllerTest {

    public static final String CONTENT_TYPE = &amp;quot;Content-Type&amp;quot;;
    private ExampleController controller;
    private MockMvc mockMvc;

    @Before
    public void setUp() {
        controller = new ExampleController();
        mockMvc = MockMvcBuilders
                .standaloneSetup(controller)
                .build();
    }

    @Test
    public void shouldHaveAMessageInResponse() throws Exception {
        mockMvc
                .perform(get(&amp;quot;/test/hello&amp;quot;)
                        .contentType(APPLICATION_JSON))
                .andDo(print())
                .andExpect(status().isOk())
                .andExpect(header().string(CONTENT_TYPE, APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE))
                .andExpect(jsonPath(&amp;quot;message&amp;quot;).value(&amp;quot;hello&amp;quot;));
    }
}

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, lets try and write a similar test for an end point uses &lt;code&gt;DeferredResult&lt;/code&gt; to do asynchronous request processing. The end point in this example just wraps the JSON structure in &lt;code&gt;DeferredResult&lt;/code&gt; and returns, whereas there will be a long running asynchronous process in a more useful case. But the idea remains the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;    @RequestMapping(value = &amp;quot;/deferred&amp;quot;,
            method = GET,
            consumes = APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE,
            produces = APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE
    )
    @ResponseStatus(OK)
    public DeferredResult&amp;lt;Map&amp;gt; deferred() {
        DeferredResult&amp;lt;Map&amp;gt; deferredResult = new DeferredResult&amp;lt;&amp;gt;();
        deferredResult.setResult(helloMessage());
        return deferredResult;
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If our test for this end point were to use the same mechanism as the previous test, we will start observing an interesting error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;    @Test
    public void shouldHaveAMessageInDeferredResponse() throws Exception {
        mockMvc
                .perform(get(&amp;quot;/test/deferred&amp;quot;)
                        .contentType(APPLICATION_JSON))
                .andExpect(status().isOk())
                .andExpect(header().string(CONTENT_TYPE, APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE))
                .andExpect(jsonPath(&amp;quot;message&amp;quot;).value(&amp;quot;hello&amp;quot;));
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;Response header Content-Type expected:&amp;lt;application/json&amp;gt; but was:&amp;lt;null&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This happened because MockMvc did not wait for the asynchronous process to finish. The solution to this involves using MockMvc&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;asyncDispatch&lt;/code&gt;. AsyncDispatch creates a new request that continues from the result of a previous MockMvc request that started the asynchronous process.
The test re-written using &lt;code&gt;asyncDispatch&lt;/code&gt; would be as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;    @Test
    public void shouldHaveAMessageInDeferredResponseWithAsyncDispatch() throws Exception {
        MvcResult result = mockMvc
                .perform(get(&amp;quot;/test/deferred&amp;quot;)
                        .contentType(APPLICATION_JSON))
                .andReturn();

        mockMvc
                .perform(asyncDispatch(result))
                .andExpect(status().isOk())
                .andExpect(header().string(CONTENT_TYPE, APPLICATION_JSON_VALUE))
                .andExpect(jsonPath(&amp;quot;message&amp;quot;).value(&amp;quot;hello&amp;quot;));
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same approach can be employed to test when controllers use Java 8&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;CompletableFuture&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running multiple applications in the same Tomcat installation</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/06/09/running-multiple-applications-in-the-same-tomcat-installation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2015 01:11:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/06/09/running-multiple-applications-in-the-same-tomcat-installation/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This blog post describes how to set up Tomcat to run multiple applications running as separate JVM processes, using the same Tomcat installation. This method utilizes the &lt;code&gt;CATALINA_HOME&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;CATALINA_BASE&lt;/code&gt; environment variables used by Tomcat. I have verified this method against Tomcat versions &lt;code&gt;8.0.x&lt;/code&gt;; other versions should work the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-typical-tomcat-installation:a2ed05b8bb95da785f1e814e64b0e342&#34;&gt;A typical Tomcat installation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we explode the Tomcat 8.0.23 &lt;a href=&#34;http://mirrors.sonic.net/apache/tomcat/tomcat-8/v8.0.23/bin/apache-tomcat-8.0.23.tar.gz&#34;&gt;tarball&lt;/a&gt;, we get the following directory structure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ tar apache-tomcat-8.0.23.tar.gz

$ ls apache-tomcat-8.0.23/
LICENSE		RELEASE-NOTES	bin		lib		temp		work
NOTICE		RUNNING.txt	conf		logs		webapps
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This distribution, by default runs applications in a single JVM. How does it do this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomcat control scripts - &lt;code&gt;startup.sh&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;shutdown.sh&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;catalina.sh&lt;/code&gt; uses the environment variables &lt;code&gt;CATALINA_HOME&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;CATALINA_BASE&lt;/code&gt; to locate binaries and configuration files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the documentaion inside &lt;code&gt;catalina.sh&lt;/code&gt; under &lt;code&gt;apache-tomcat-8.0.23/bin/&lt;/code&gt; we can see that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;#   CATALINA_HOME   May point at your Catalina &amp;quot;build&amp;quot; directory.
#
#   CATALINA_BASE   (Optional) Base directory for resolving dynamic portions
#                   of a Catalina installation.  If not present, resolves to
#                   the same directory that CATALINA_HOME points to.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows us to separate the &lt;code&gt;CATALINA_HOME&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;CATALINA_BASE&lt;/code&gt; directories. The Tomcat binaries and scripts need to be inside &lt;code&gt;CATALINA_HOME&lt;/code&gt; and our first application can deploy itself to &lt;code&gt;CATALINA_BASE&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;separating-catalina-home-and-catalina-base:a2ed05b8bb95da785f1e814e64b0e342&#34;&gt;Separating CATALINA_HOME and CATALINA_BASE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;app1&lt;/code&gt; directory will have the following directories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ ls -a app1/
.	..	bin	conf	logs	temp	webapps	work
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;bin&lt;/code&gt; directory will have the &lt;code&gt;setenv.sh&lt;/code&gt; script used to set additional environment variables for the application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;tomcat&lt;/code&gt; directory will have the following directories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;
$ ls tomcat/
LICENSE		NOTICE		RELEASE-NOTES	RUNNING.txt	bin		lib
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;bin&lt;/code&gt; directory will have the Tomcat management scripts like &lt;code&gt;startup.sh&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;shutdown.sh&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;catalina.sh&lt;/code&gt; etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we can start &lt;code&gt;app1&lt;/code&gt; by pointing &lt;code&gt;CATALINA_BASE&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;app1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;CATALINA_HOME&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;tomcat&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;
$ export CATALINA_HOME=/Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/tomcat

$ export CATALINA_BASE=/Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/app1

$ $CATALINA_HOME/bin/startup.sh

$ $CATALINA_HOME/bin/startup.sh
Using CATALINA_BASE:   /Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/app1
Using CATALINA_HOME:   /Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/tomcat
Using CATALINA_TMPDIR: /Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/app1/temp
Using JRE_HOME:        /Library/Java/JavaVirtualMachines/jdk1.8.0_45.jdk/Contents/Home
Using CLASSPATH:       /Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/tomcat/bin/bootstrap.jar:/Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/tomcat/bin/tomcat-juli.jar
Tomcat started.

$ curl -s -D - -o /dev/null http://127.0.0.1:8080
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Server: Apache-Coyote/1.1
Content-Type: text/html;charset=UTF-8
Transfer-Encoding: chunked
Date: Tue, 09 Jun 2015 07:37:43 GMT
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s try and deploy a second application &lt;code&gt;app2&lt;/code&gt; running on port &lt;code&gt;9090&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;
$ export CATALINA_HOME=/Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/tomcat

$ export CATALINA_BASE=/Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/app2

$ $CATALINA_HOME/bin/startup.sh
Using CATALINA_BASE:   /Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/app2
Using CATALINA_HOME:   /Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/tomcat
Using CATALINA_TMPDIR: /Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/app2/temp
Using JRE_HOME:        /Library/Java/JavaVirtualMachines/jdk1.8.0_45.jdk/Contents/Home
Using CLASSPATH:       /Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/tomcat/bin/bootstrap.jar:/Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/tomcat/bin/tomcat-juli.jar
Tomcat started.

$ curl -s -D - -o /dev/null http://127.0.0.1:9090
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Server: Apache-Coyote/1.1
Content-Type: text/html;charset=UTF-8
Transfer-Encoding: chunked
Date: Tue, 09 Jun 2015 07:41:02 GMT
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tying-it-all-together:a2ed05b8bb95da785f1e814e64b0e342&#34;&gt;Tying it all together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, it is useful to create management scripts that abstract away the environment variables and allows for starting up and shutting down applications individually. The &lt;code&gt;start.sh&lt;/code&gt; script will be as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;#!/usr/bin/env sh

# start.sh
# Script to start a Tomcat application

show_usage() {
    echo &amp;quot;Usage: ./start.sh &amp;lt;app-name&amp;gt;&amp;quot;;
    exit 1;
}

declare app_name=$1;
[[ -z $app_name ]] &amp;amp;&amp;amp; show_usage;


declare INSTALL_BASE=/Users/sdqali/src/sandbox

export CATALINA_HOME=$INSTALL_BASE/tomcat
export CATALINA_BASE=$INSTALL_BASE/$app_name

$CATALINA_HOME/bin/startup.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the &lt;code&gt;stop.sh&lt;/code&gt; script will be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;#!/usr/bin/env sh

# stop.sh
# Script to stop a Tomcat application

show_usage() {
    echo &amp;quot;Usage: ./stop.sh &amp;lt;app-name&amp;gt;&amp;quot;;
    exit 1;
}

declare app_name=$1;
[[ -z $app_name ]] &amp;amp;&amp;amp; show_usage;


declare INSTALL_BASE=/Users/sdqali/src/sandbox

export CATALINA_HOME=$INSTALL_BASE/tomcat
export CATALINA_BASE=$INSTALL_BASE/$app_name

$CATALINA_HOME/bin/shutdown.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can manage individual applications using these scripts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ ./management/start.sh app2
Using CATALINA_BASE:   /Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/app2
Using CATALINA_HOME:   /Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/tomcat
Using CATALINA_TMPDIR: /Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/app2/temp
Using JRE_HOME:        /Library/Java/JavaVirtualMachines/jdk1.8.0_45.jdk/Contents/Home
Using CLASSPATH:       /Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/tomcat/bin/bootstrap.jar:/Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/tomcat/bin/tomcat-juli.jar
Tomcat started.

$ nc -z  127.0.0.1 9090
Connection to 127.0.0.1 port 9090 [tcp/websm] succeeded!

$ curl -s -D - -o /dev/null http://127.0.0.1:9090
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Server: Apache-Coyote/1.1
Content-Type: text/html;charset=UTF-8
Transfer-Encoding: chunked
Date: Tue, 09 Jun 2015 08:16:05 GMT


$ ./management/stop.sh app2
Using CATALINA_BASE:   /Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/app2
Using CATALINA_HOME:   /Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/tomcat
Using CATALINA_TMPDIR: /Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/app2/temp
Using JRE_HOME:        /Library/Java/JavaVirtualMachines/jdk1.8.0_45.jdk/Contents/Home
Using CLASSPATH:       /Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/tomcat/bin/bootstrap.jar:/Users/sdqali/src/sandbox/tomcat/bin/tomcat-juli.jar

$ nc -z  127.0.0.1 9090

$ curl -v http://127.0.0.1:9090
* Rebuilt URL to: http://127.0.0.1:9090/
* Hostname was NOT found in DNS cache
*   Trying 127.0.0.1...
* connect to 127.0.0.1 port 9090 failed: Connection refused
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making sense of Cloud Foundry security group declarations</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/05/21/making-sense-of-cloud-foundry-security-group-declarations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2015 22:58:41 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/05/21/making-sense-of-cloud-foundry-security-group-declarations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cloud Foundry allows fine grained declaration of security groups, down to IP address ranges and Ports. While this provides great flexibility, making sense of why each rule in a security group exists and what each does is really difficult because of the limitations of the security group declaration mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cloud Foundry command line tool allows the creation of security groups from JSON declarations. The &lt;code&gt;create-security-group&lt;/code&gt; command works like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;&amp;gt; cf create-security-group SECURITY_GROUP PATH_TO_JSON_RULES_FILE
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The JSON file needs to declare an array of rules where each rule has the following structure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34;&gt;{
   &amp;quot;protocol&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;tcp&amp;quot;,
   &amp;quot;destination&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;10.244.1.18&amp;quot;,
   &amp;quot;ports&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;3306&amp;quot;,
   &amp;quot;log&amp;quot;: true
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my Cloud Foundry environment, I have a security group assigned to a &lt;code&gt;Space&lt;/code&gt; with the following declaration:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34;&gt;[
  {&amp;quot;protocol&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;tcp&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;destination&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;lt;ip-foo&amp;gt;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;ports&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;3306&amp;quot;},
  {&amp;quot;protocol&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;tcp&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;destination&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;lt;some-ip&amp;gt;-&amp;lt;another-ip&amp;gt;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;ports&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;55882&amp;quot;},
  {&amp;quot;protocol&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;tcp&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;destination&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;lt;ip-bar&amp;gt;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;ports&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;443&amp;quot;}
]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With only 3 rules in place, it is already confusing what service each rule is for and why they are there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe this can be easily improved by allowing an extra field &lt;code&gt;comment&lt;/code&gt; that provides context about each rule. With this in place, the rules will look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34;&gt;[
  {&amp;quot;protocol&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;tcp&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;destination&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;lt;ip-foo&amp;gt;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;ports&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;3306&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;comment&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Allow database connection to PostgreSQL at hosted-postgres-service.com&amp;quot;},
  {&amp;quot;protocol&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;tcp&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;destination&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;lt;some-ip&amp;gt;-&amp;lt;another-ip&amp;gt;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;ports&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;55882&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;comment&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Allow logging to hosted-logging-service.com&amp;quot;},
  {&amp;quot;protocol&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;tcp&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;destination&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;lt;ip-bar&amp;gt;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;ports&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;443&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;comment&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Allow monitoring service at hosted-monitoring-service.com&amp;quot;}
]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As things stand, Cloud Foundry Cloud Controller does not allow any extra fields to exist in a rule. For example, the above declaration will cause an error while trying to create a security group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;&amp;gt; cf create-security-group sample-space-security-group spec.json

Server error, status code: 400, error code: 300001, message: The security group is invalid: rules rule number 1 contains the invalid field &#39;comment&#39;, rules rule number 2 contains the invalid field &#39;comment&#39;, rules rule number 3 contains the invalid field &#39;comment&#39;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If JSON allowed comments, commenting would result in a slightly more readable declaration file, although it won&amp;rsquo;t be stored in the Cloud Controller database and hence won&amp;rsquo;t be available upon querying with &lt;code&gt;cf security-group &amp;lt;security-group-name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. This is a moot point anyway, as JSON &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/+DouglasCrockfordEsq/posts/RK8qyGVaGSr&#34;&gt;explicitly&lt;/a&gt; doesn&amp;rsquo;t allow comments. There are workarounds that involve minifying the JSON input before parsing the configurations, but I don&amp;rsquo;t think that is the right direction to head to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have filed a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cloudfoundry/cloud_controller_ng/issues/382&#34;&gt;ticket&lt;/a&gt; against Cloud Controller to address this issue. It &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cloudfoundry/cloud_controller_ng/blob/cacb5563264208e920f4b7fecc7060f89b929fbb/lib/cloud_controller/rule_validator.rb#L6&#34;&gt;doesn&amp;rsquo;t look like a difficult&lt;/a&gt; feature to implement. Hopefully this is available in Cloud Controller soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Configuring Cloud Foundry Java Memory Parameters</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/05/20/configuring-cloud-foundry-java-memory-parameters/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2015 19:42:56 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2015/05/20/configuring-cloud-foundry-java-memory-parameters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week I have been trying out Cloud Foundry. Today while trying to set up monitoring through AppDynamics, the sample application that I was using started crashing because of a Java memory error. This blog post discusses how to prevent this from happening by configuring Java memory parameters used by the application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what was in the Cloud Foundry logs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;May 20 18:14:51 CloudFoundry 6767b9fd-1874-43cb-a4f8-7470a17c90ae/[App/2]:  /bin/bash: line 31:    32 Killed                  ( SERVER_PORT=$PORT $PWD/.java-buildpack/open_jdk_jre/bin/java -cp $PWD/.:$PWD/.java-buildpack/spring_auto_reconfiguration/spring_auto_reconfiguration-1.4.0_RELEASE.jar -Djava.io.tmpdir=$TMPDIR -XX:OnOutOfMemoryError=$PWD/.java-buildpack/open_jdk_jre/bin/killjava.sh -Xmx499200K -Xms499200K -XX:MaxPermSize=65M -XX:PermSize=65M -Xss1M -javaagent:$PWD/.java-buildpack/app_dynamics_agent/javaagent.jar -Dappdynamics.agent.applicationName=&#39;******&#39; -Dappdynamics.agent.tierName=&#39;******&#39; -Dappdynamics.agent.nodeName=$(expr &amp;quot;$VCAP_APPLICATION&amp;quot; : &#39;.*instance_id[&amp;quot;: ]*&amp;quot;\([a-z0-9]\+\)&amp;quot;.*&#39;) -Dappdynamics.agent.accountAccessKey=****** -Dappdynamics.agent.accountName=******* -Dappdynamics.controller.hostName=******.saas.appdynamics.com -Dappdynamics.controller.port=443 -Dappdynamics.controller.ssl.enabled=true org.springframework.boot.loader.JarLauncher )
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be seen that the &lt;code&gt;MaxPermSize&lt;/code&gt; is set to &lt;code&gt;65M&lt;/code&gt;. Now, this is not something I configured for this app. This value was assigned by the Java build pack generated by Cloud Foundry when the app was deployed. This can be in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cloudfoundry/java-buildpack&#34;&gt;Java build pack&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s OpenJDK JRE configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-yml&#34;&gt;# config/open_jdk_jre.yml
---
jre:
  version: 1.8.0_+
  repository_root: &amp;quot;{default.repository.root}/openjdk/{platform}/{architecture}&amp;quot;
memory_calculator:
  version: 1.+
  repository_root: &amp;quot;{default.repository.root}/memory-calculator/{platform}/{architecture}&amp;quot;
  memory_sizes:
    metaspace: 64m..
    permgen: 64m..
  memory_heuristics:
    heap: 75
    metaspace: 10
    permgen: 10
    stack: 5
    native: 10
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to change this value is to change the configurations of the Java build pack. There are two ways to do this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fork the build pack, modify the default memory parameters and use this build pack to deploy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Override the memory parameters used by the build pack at deploy time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Option 1 seems to be an overkill and Cloud Foundry provides a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cloudfoundry/java-buildpack/blob/master/README.md#configuration-and-extension&#34;&gt;relatively easy method&lt;/a&gt; to override build pack parameters. Option 2 is the approach I decided to take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cloudfoundry/java-buildpack/blob/master/docs/jre-open_jdk_jre.md&#34;&gt;two sets of mappings&lt;/a&gt; that control the various Java memory configurations - &lt;code&gt;memory_sizes&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;memory_heuristics&lt;/code&gt;. Together, these two parameters provide a lot of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cloudfoundry/java-buildpack/blob/master/docs/jre-open_jdk_jre.md#memory-calculation&#34;&gt;flexibility&lt;/a&gt; to control memory allocation. For the particular issue my application faced, all I need to do is to force an appropriate value for &lt;code&gt;MaxPermSize&lt;/code&gt; and this can be done by setting the &lt;code&gt;JBP_CONFIG_OPEN_JDK_MEMORY_CALCULATOR&lt;/code&gt; environment variable as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;cf set-env app-name JBP_CONFIG_OPEN_JDK_MEMORY_CALCULATOR [memory_sizes: {metaspace: 128m}]&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this configurations works for applications running under Java &lt;code&gt;1.8&lt;/code&gt;, the right parameter to use for applications running under Java &lt;code&gt;1.7&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;code&gt;permgen&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;cf set-env app-name JBP_CONFIG_OPEN_JDK_JRE &#39;[memory_sizes: {metaspace: 128m}]&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After re-staging the application and making sure the application works as expected, I added this environment variable to the application&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;manifest.yml&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-yaml&#34;&gt;---
applications:
- name: test-app
  ...
  env:
    JBP_CONFIG_OPEN_JDK_MEMORY_CALCULATOR: &amp;quot;[memory_sizes: {metaspace: 128m}]&amp;quot;
  ...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see how to adjust the memory parameters by modifying the Java build pack, see Haydon Ryan&amp;rsquo;s blog post &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.haydonryan.com/java-8-increasing-metaspace-size-in-cloud-foundry/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disputed territories and merging shapes and features</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2014/08/08/disputed-territories-and-merging-shapes-and-features/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2014/08/08/disputed-territories-and-merging-shapes-and-features/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Making a map that shows a disputed territory can be a tricky business. Nation states vigorously contest maps that appear to portray a boundary that challenges what a border looks like. From the Falkland Islands to Kuril Islands; from Western Sahara to Arunachal Pradesh, disputed territories result in omissions, additions and inaccuracies in maps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up looking at maps in books printed by the Oxford Press, that came with a disclaimer in blue rubber stamped across them that stated how the map was wrong. This was due to the fact that the maps showed only the parts of Kashmir being administered by India, thereby omitting areas under Chinese and Pakistani control. The Criminal Law Amendment Act, 1961 in India makes it punishable with imprisonment up to 6 months to publish a map that excludes all or parts of Kashmir&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:331feb6386b5b7cd03d2133ef33a86dd:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:331feb6386b5b7cd03d2133ef33a86dd:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This creates a lot of trouble for people who make maps for fun or to visualize data. Survey of India does not make it easy to get hold of shape files that represent India&amp;rsquo;s boundaries, and all the shape files that are available from international sources exclude parts of Kashmir. So, how do we solve this problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The North American Cartographic Information Society&amp;rsquo;s Natural Earth &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:331feb6386b5b7cd03d2133ef33a86dd:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:331feb6386b5b7cd03d2133ef33a86dd:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; maps has all the disputed territories available for download as shape files. One way to solve the issue on our hands will be to take the shapes relevant to Kashmir from this file and merge it with the rest of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will explore how to perform and an operation like this through QGIS &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:331feb6386b5b7cd03d2133ef33a86dd:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:331feb6386b5b7cd03d2133ef33a86dd:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the disputed areas shape file in QGIS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select all the regions in Kashmir that are seen by India as it&amp;rsquo;s territories.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In order to make merging these shapes easier, we will introduce a new attribute on them. Go to &lt;code&gt;Layer → Open Attribute Table&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switch to editing mode in the Attribute Table by clicking the &lt;code&gt;Toggle editing mode&lt;/code&gt; button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &lt;code&gt;New column&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose a name for the column. In this example we are using &lt;code&gt;target&lt;/code&gt;. Select &lt;code&gt;Text (string)&lt;/code&gt; as the Type and choose a number like &lt;code&gt;10&lt;/code&gt; for width.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For all the selected shapes, set the value of &lt;code&gt;target&lt;/code&gt; to Kashmir.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the &lt;code&gt;Dissolve&lt;/code&gt; tool, found at &lt;code&gt;Vector → Geoprocessing tools → Dissolve&lt;/code&gt; to dissolve the shapes in to a single shape file. Choose &lt;code&gt;target&lt;/code&gt; as the value for &lt;code&gt;dissolve&lt;/code&gt; field. Save the output to a new shape file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the QGIS plugin &lt;code&gt;MergeShapes&lt;/code&gt;. Plugins can be installed from &lt;code&gt;Plugins → Manage and Install Plugins&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copy the &lt;a href=&#34;http://biogeo.ucdavis.edu/data/diva/adm/IND_adm.zip&#34;&gt;India shape file&lt;/a&gt; from DIVA-GIS and the newly generated Kashmir shape file to a directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merge these into a single shape using &lt;code&gt;Vector → MergeShapes → MergeShapes&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that we have a shape File for India that closely resembles India&amp;rsquo;s official version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we have the shape File for Kashmir from step &lt;code&gt;8&lt;/code&gt;, we could do the merging by converting both shape Files to their corresponding GeoJSON formats and doing simple JavaScript operations on the objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start by converting both shape Files to their GeoJSON representation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;&amp;gt; ogr2ogr -f GeoJSON india.geo.json india.shp
&amp;gt; ogr2ogr -f GeoJSON kashmir.geo.json kashmir.shp
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Load the two feature collections in to a JavaScript console. I tend to use Chromium&amp;rsquo;s Developer Tools, but in this example I am using  Node.js&amp;rsquo; REPL.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;kashmir = JSON.parse(fs.readFileSync(&amp;quot;./kashmir.geo.json&amp;quot;).toString());
india = JSON.parse(fs.readFileSync(&amp;quot;./india.geo.json&amp;quot;).toString());
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify the Kashmir feature in the India feature collection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;kin = india.features.filter(function(f) {return f.properties.NAME_1.match(&amp;quot;Kashmir&amp;quot;);})[0];
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace it&amp;rsquo;s coordinates with the unified Kashmir we generated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;kin.geometry.coordinates = kashmir.features[0].geometry.coordinates;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save it back to a GeoJSON file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;fs.writeFileSync(&amp;quot;full_india.geo.json&amp;quot;, JSON.stringify(india));
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the GeoJSON file can be transformed back in to a shape file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;ogr2ogr -f &#39;ESRI Shapefile&#39; full_india.shp full_india.geo.json
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to Kashmir and laws. Will this map save one from trouble? I am not sure, but this is an improvement on the omission of territories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:331feb6386b5b7cd03d2133ef33a86dd:1&#34;&gt;The Criminal Law Amendment Act, 1961 - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vakilno1.com/bareacts/laws/the-criminal-law-amendment-act-1961.html#2_Questioning_the_territorial_integrity_or_frontiers_of_India_in_a_manner_prejudicial_to_the_interests_of_safety_and_security_of_India&#34;&gt;Questioning the territorial integrity or frontiers of India in a manner prejudicial to the interests of safety and security of India.&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:331feb6386b5b7cd03d2133ef33a86dd:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:331feb6386b5b7cd03d2133ef33a86dd:2&#34;&gt;Natural Earth is a public domain map dataset available at 1:10m, 1:50m, and 1:110 million scales. The data set is available for download &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.naturalearthdata.com/downloads/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:331feb6386b5b7cd03d2133ef33a86dd:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:331feb6386b5b7cd03d2133ef33a86dd:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://qgis.org/en/site/&#34;&gt;QGIS&lt;/a&gt; is a cross-platform free and open source desktop geographic information systems application that provides data viewing, editing, and analysis capabilities.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:331feb6386b5b7cd03d2133ef33a86dd:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A list of GIS tools</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2014/08/03/a-list-of-gis-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2014/08/03/a-list-of-gis-tools/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I have been playing around with maps a lot these days and have ended up using various tools in the process. This blog post is a way to make a note of these tools for later use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;geojson-io:7591cb75a8855983e3f9edf802cbce55&#34;&gt;geojson.io&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mapbox&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://geojson.io/&#34;&gt;geojson.io&lt;/a&gt; is a simple tool for creating, editing and sharing maps. It lets you import map data in various formats and has an editor to modify maps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;geojson-topojson:7591cb75a8855983e3f9edf802cbce55&#34;&gt;GeoJSON-TopoJSON&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/JeffPaine&#34;&gt;Jeff Paine&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/JeffPaine/geojson-topojson&#34;&gt;GeoJSON-TopoJSON&lt;/a&gt; is a simple tool to convert between the more common GeoJSON format and the TopoJSON format used by libraries like D3.js. It is a simple tool, but it does exactly what it says on the tin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-distillery:7591cb75a8855983e3f9edf802cbce55&#34;&gt;The Distillery&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New York Times&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;http://shancarter.com/&#34;&gt;Shan Carter&lt;/a&gt; built &lt;a href=&#34;http://shancarter.github.io/distillery/&#34;&gt;The Distillery&lt;/a&gt;, a GUI around TopoJSON. Apart from converting GeoJSON to TopoJSON, it allows you to alter the map&amp;rsquo;s projection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;ogr2ogr:7591cb75a8855983e3f9edf802cbce55&#34;&gt;ogr2ogr&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gdal.org/ogr2ogr.html&#34;&gt;ogr2ogr&lt;/a&gt; is a command line utility to convert features data between different file formats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;ogre-ogr2ogr-web-client:7591cb75a8855983e3f9edf802cbce55&#34;&gt;Ogre - ogr2ogr web client&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ogre.adc4gis.com/&#34;&gt;Ogre&lt;/a&gt; is a web UI around ogr2ogr. It lets you do transformations on your map files when you are lazy and don&amp;rsquo;t want to use the command line to run ogr2ogr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;merge-geojson-features:7591cb75a8855983e3f9edf802cbce55&#34;&gt;merge-geojson-features&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.npmjs.org/package/&#34;&gt;merge-geojson-features&lt;/a&gt; is a Node.js module to combine Features defined in different files in to a single FeatureCollection. I use it when I am not in the mood to alter GeoJSON objects from a JavaScript console by hand.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Importing the Yelp dataset into MongoDB</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2014/08/02/importing-the-yelp-dataset-into-mongodb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2014/08/02/importing-the-yelp-dataset-into-mongodb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today Yelp announced their dataset challenge &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:c6878b2b502d5257f269a3d2e809c771:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:c6878b2b502d5257f269a3d2e809c771:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The dataset they released includes data from 5 cities (Phoenix, Las Vegas, Madison, Waterloo and Edinburgh) and consists of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;42,153 businesses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;320,002 business attributes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;31,617 check-in sets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;252,898 users&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;955,999 edge social graph&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;403,210 tips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1,125,458 reviews&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data is available for public consumption, although Yelp owns any derivative dataset you create from the original &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:c6878b2b502d5257f269a3d2e809c771:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:c6878b2b502d5257f269a3d2e809c771:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data is available as files with each line representing a JSON object. Since I am using MongoDB these days to analyze geospatial data, I wanted to convert this into an easy format that I could import into Mongo. Mongo puts a strict constraint on how a location needs to be specified - It expects a location field in a document to be an array in the format &lt;code&gt;[longitude, latitude]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, the first step is to convert and transform the objects into objects that Mongo can make sense of. The following Ruby script does the job:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ruby&#34;&gt;#!/usr/bin/env ruby

require &amp;quot;json&amp;quot;

businesses = IO.readlines(&amp;quot;yelp.business.json&amp;quot;).map do |line|
  b = JSON.parse(line)
  b[&amp;quot;location&amp;quot;] = {
    &amp;quot;type&amp;quot; =&amp;gt; &amp;quot;Point&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;coordinates&amp;quot; =&amp;gt; [b[&amp;quot;longitude&amp;quot;], b[&amp;quot;latitude&amp;quot;]]
  }
  b
end
IO.write &amp;quot;businesses.mongo.json&amp;quot;, businesses.to_json
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is to import this data into Mongo using the &lt;code&gt;mongoimport&lt;/code&gt; tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;mongoimport --collection businesses --file businesses.mongo.json --jsonArray
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need the &lt;code&gt;--jsonArray&lt;/code&gt; parameter because our data is an array.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since there are 42153 businesses, it will take some time. On my Macbook Pro, it took around 2 minutes, 10 seconds. Once the import is done, make sure that we have a Geospatial index on the &lt;code&gt;location&lt;/code&gt; field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;db.businesses.ensureIndex({location: &amp;quot;2dsphere&amp;quot;})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the indexing is done, we can use Mongo&amp;rsquo;s Geospatial queries to find interesting things. As an example, here we look up all the restaurants within 1 kilometer distance from downtown Phoenix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;db.businesses.find({
  location: {
    $near: {
      $geometry: {
	type: &amp;quot;Point&amp;quot;,
	coordinates: [-112.0667, 33.4500]
      },
      $maxDistance: 1000
    }
  }
})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy hacking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:c6878b2b502d5257f269a3d2e809c771:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.yelp.com/dataset_challenge&#34;&gt;Yelp Dataset Challenge, 2014&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:c6878b2b502d5257f269a3d2e809c771:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:c6878b2b502d5257f269a3d2e809c771:2&#34;&gt;DATASET CHALLENGE ACADEMIC DATASET TERMS OF USE &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.yelp.com/html/pdf/Dataset_Challenge_Academic_Dataset_Agreement.pdf&#34;&gt;Section 5, Ownership&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:c6878b2b502d5257f269a3d2e809c771:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clojure Dojo - Levenshtein edit distance</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2014/03/20/clojure-dojo---levenshtein-edit-distance/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2014/03/20/clojure-dojo---levenshtein-edit-distance/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I have been playing around with Clojure and after familiarising myself with the core, I decided to start writing little programs that forces me to choose the right idioms. I am starting off with Levenshtein edit distance of two strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;levenshtein-edit-distance:d5d4c3a7257ad508bc68cd569fb16682&#34;&gt;Levenshtein edit distance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Levenshtein edit distance between two string is a way of quantifying how similar or dissimilar they are, lower distance implying higher similarity. The algorithm to calculate Levenshtein distance is fairly simple - the algorithm cares about three operations that can be performed at a particular position in a string to move it towards the other - insertion, deletion and substitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be recursively solved for two strings &lt;code&gt;A0:AS&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;B0:BS&lt;/code&gt; by comparing &lt;code&gt;AS&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;B0:BS&lt;/code&gt;; &lt;code&gt;A0:AS&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;BS&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;AS&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;BS&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;code:d5d4c3a7257ad508bc68cd569fb16682&#34;&gt;Code&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34;&gt;(ns clojure_dojo.core)

(defn edit-distance
  &amp;quot;Return the Levenshtein edit distance between two strings&amp;quot;
  [first second]
  (cond
   (empty? first) (count second)
   (empty? second) (count first)
   :else (min (+ 1 (edit-distance (drop 1 first) second))
              (+ 1 (edit-distance first (drop 1 second)))
              (+ (cond
                  (= (take 1 first) (take 1 second)) 0
                  :else 1)
                 (edit-distance (drop 1 first) (drop 1 second))))))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;test:d5d4c3a7257ad508bc68cd569fb16682&#34;&gt;Test&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-clojure&#34;&gt;(ns clojure_dojo.t-core
  (:use midje.sweet)
  (:use [clojure_dojo.core]))

(facts &amp;quot;about `edit-distance`&amp;quot;
       (fact &amp;quot;it returns length of other string if one string is empty&amp;quot;
             (edit-distance &amp;quot;foo&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&amp;quot;) =&amp;gt; 3
             (edit-distance &amp;quot;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;foo&amp;quot;) =&amp;gt; 3)
       (fact &amp;quot;detects deletions&amp;quot;
             (edit-distance &amp;quot;foo&amp;quot; &amp;quot;oo&amp;quot;) =&amp;gt; 1)
       (fact &amp;quot;detects substitutions&amp;quot;
             (edit-distance &amp;quot;ab&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;cd&amp;quot;) =&amp;gt; 2)
       (fact &amp;quot;detects additions needed&amp;quot;
             (edit-distance &amp;quot;oo&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;foo&amp;quot;) =&amp;gt; 1
             (edit-distance &amp;quot;kit&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;sitting&amp;quot;) =&amp;gt; 5
             (edit-distance &amp;quot;intention&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;execution&amp;quot;) =&amp;gt; 5
             (edit-distance &amp;quot;sittin&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;sitting&amp;quot;) =&amp;gt; 1))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-problem-with-this-approach:d5d4c3a7257ad508bc68cd569fb16682&#34;&gt;The problem with this approach&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This solution looks fine - it passes the tests. However, if we carefully observe the recursion tree, we notice that there are sub-problems that are solved multiple times and this makes this algorithm&amp;rsquo;s order of complexity Θ(3^min(m, n)). This can be observed from the call tree of this recursion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;improvement:d5d4c3a7257ad508bc68cd569fb16682&#34;&gt;Improvement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recursive algorithms of this nature can be improved in two ways - memoization during recursion or applying &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_programming&#34;&gt;Dynamic Programming&lt;/a&gt; in a bottom up manner. The next blog post in this series will deal with how these two approaches can be done in Clojure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code for the above solution is on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sdqali/clojure-dojo&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A simple JMeter test with login</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2014/02/17/a-simple-jmeter-test-with-login/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2014/02/17/a-simple-jmeter-test-with-login/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I had to set up a JMeter test last week - the test included logging in to a site, and then hitting a bunch of URLs, all of them being GET requests. I found it hard to find a simple documentation that described how to do this - the ones I found were either incomplete or were trying to teach me a large number of things at the same time. So when I figured it out, I decided to write this down, for anyone else finding themselves in the same place as me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this example, the application under test is a simple Rails application, with the login form at &lt;code&gt;/login&lt;/code&gt; and a &lt;code&gt;POST&lt;/code&gt; request to &lt;code&gt;/login&lt;/code&gt; does the authentication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;add-a-thread-group:432050f6a9a1f05bac0d71354129b823&#34;&gt;Add a Thread Group&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Thread Group defines a pool of users that will execute a particular test case against the server. JMeter makes the number of users, and the ramp-rate configurable. For the purpose of this example, Number of Threads is 2 and the ramp up time period is 1 second. This thread group is also configured to run forever.
&lt;img src=&#34;http://sdqali.in/images/jmeter/thread_group.png&#34; alt=&#34;Thread Group&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;http-request-defaults:432050f6a9a1f05bac0d71354129b823&#34;&gt;HTTP Request Defaults&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The net step is to add an HTTP Request Defaults configuration element to the Thread Group. This configuration element sets up the domain or I.P. address of the server, the port and the protocol (HTTP / HTTPS). In this example, Server Name is &lt;code&gt;127.0.0.1&lt;/code&gt; and Port is &lt;code&gt;3000&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;img src=&#34;http://sdqali.in/images/jmeter/request_defaults.png&#34; alt=&#34;HTTP Request Defaults&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;http-cookie-manager:432050f6a9a1f05bac0d71354129b823&#34;&gt;HTTP Cookie Manager&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cookie manager stores and sends cookies, as a web browser would do if an actual user was hitting the server. For the purposes of this example, the default configurations are enough.
&lt;img src=&#34;http://sdqali.in/images/jmeter/cookie_manager.png&#34; alt=&#34;Cookie Manager&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;implement-normal-page-actions:432050f6a9a1f05bac0d71354129b823&#34;&gt;Implement normal page actions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this point, all that remains is to implement HTTP Requests to the end points that are relevant to this test. In this example, we navigate to the Login page at &lt;code&gt;/login&lt;/code&gt;, fire a &lt;code&gt;POST&lt;/code&gt; request to &lt;code&gt;/login&lt;/code&gt; with the appropriate form input values and proceed to the Admin page.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The SNDP - NSS political experiment of 1980s</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2014/02/09/the-sndp---nss-political-experiment-of-1980s/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2014/02/09/the-sndp---nss-political-experiment-of-1980s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, at the annual congregation of the Sree Narayana Dharma Paripalana (S.N.D.P.) Yogam, it&amp;rsquo;s leaders - Vellaapalli Nadesan and his son Thushaar announced that the Yogam is about to form their own political party that will unite Hindus of Kerala under one umbrella. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; S.N.D.P. and it&amp;rsquo;s leaders are no strangers to threatening to announce their intent to form a political party. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; They did the same in 2012, generating much talk in Kerala&amp;rsquo;s political landscape. The latest announcement is likely to suffer the same fate as these earlier announcements. To understand why the Yogam is highly unlikely to form a party of their own, one needs to look at the time when they indeed had their own political party - to the late 1970s; and the 1980 election to the Kerala legislature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Socialist Republican Party (S.R.P.) formed in 1976 with the blessings of the Yogam and the almost farcical level of communal politics that resulted in it&amp;rsquo;s aftermath - helped in large by the Nair Service Society (N.S.S.) formation of the National Democratic Party (N.D.P.) offers a great lesson in the often communal nature of class politics in Kerala and how the constant on the other side of the aisle - the Left - reacts to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1970s was a torrid time period in the political landscape in Kerala. Achutha Menon&amp;rsquo;s C.P.I.-led government ruled for 8 years from 1969 - the longest term any government has ruled Kerala. Menon&amp;rsquo;s C.P.I. ruled with the help of the Indian National Congress, the Kerala Congress and the Indian Union Muslim League (I.U.M.L.). In the slug fest between the C.P.I. and the C.P.I.(M) after the Communist party&amp;rsquo;s split down the middle, the Church stood with the C.P.I., reluctantly siding with the same people against whom they lead an annual procession from the St. George Forane Church, the burial place of the martyrs of the police shooting of 1957. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I.N.C. had started distancing from communal politics and this meant that the S.N.D.P. and the N.S.S. found themselves without political parties willing to carry their flags. And they decided to change this situation. N.S.S.&amp;rsquo;s National Democratic Party (N.D.P.) came to being in 1974, immediately followed by S.N.D.P.&amp;rsquo;s Socialist Republican Party (S.R.P.) in 1976.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noticing that these announcements came in the aftermath of the agitation led by the Ezhava, Nair and Christian communities against the State&amp;rsquo;s Education Bill aimed at ending corruption and bringing parity to the appointment of teachers in colleges. The appointment of teachers to colleges that receive State aid remains a contentions issue in Kerala politics to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1979, after Achutha Menon had stepped down and infighting in Congress led to two governments that lasted only 11 months, another temporary alliance took over governance under I.U.M.L.&amp;rsquo;s Muhammed Koya and his cabinet comprised of a member of the N.D.P. This marriage of convenience made The Hindu remark in an editorial&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The front-men have so far been drawn from forces who were communal and sectarian in their own local right and specialize in making an appeal to primordial sentiments. The new gang up, which is likely to prove shortlived is an abomination thrust up on the people of Kerala.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As predicted by The Hindu, the government lasted only 2 months and the State went to an early election in January of 1980. But by this time, something monumental had happened - the C.P.I. and the C.P.I.(M) had decided to consolidate under a grand Left Democratic Front and this meant that the Congress found themselves in the United Democratic Front with such parties as the Kerala Congress, the N.D.P. and the S.R.P. In the election, the electorate firmly voted for the Left&amp;rsquo;s coalition and both S.R.P. and the N.D.P. failed miserably. The L.D.F. won 93 of the 140 seats and 50.04 per cent of the votes, while the U.D.F. won 46 seats and 40.10 per cent of the votes. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The communal appeal of the U.D.F. was glaringly obvious and it was too much for the electorate to digest. The Ezhava voters that S.R.P. thought would form it&amp;rsquo;s base voted for the Left. It is also worth noting that a large per cent of (nearly 60%) of laborers belonging to the upper caste Nair community and the lower caste Ezhava community were members of the Left parties. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The S.R.P. and N.D.P. experiments lost their momentum and went through splits before being politically irrelevant by the end of 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:1&#34;&gt;SNDP makes political plans clear. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thehindu.com/news/national/kerala/sndp-makes-political-plans-clear/article5639766.ece&#34;&gt;The Hindu, February 1, 2014&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:2&#34;&gt;SNDP Yogam to launch Hindu party. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thehindu.com/todays-paper/tp-national/tp-kerala/sndp-yogam-to-launch-hindu-party/article3608451.ece&#34;&gt;The Hindu, July 6, 2012&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:3&#34;&gt;During the liberation struggle against the first Communist government of Kerala, a police shooting resulted in the death of seven followers of the Roman Catholic Church in Angamaly. The seven martyrs of the Church were buried in a common tomb at the cemetery of St. George Forane Church at Angamaly. The Church&amp;rsquo;s famous slogan &lt;em&gt;Angamali kallarayil, njangade sawdharaanakkil, aa kallarayanu kattayyam, pakaram njangal choodikkum&lt;/em&gt; (If it is indeed our Brothers who sleep in the tomb at Angamaly, that tomb be witness, we will have our revenge.) originated after this incident.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:4&#34;&gt;The Official Webportal of the Government of Kerala - &lt;a href=&#34;http://kerala.gov.in/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=3776:history-of-kerala-legislature&#34;&gt;History of the Kerala Legislature&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:5&#34;&gt;George Mathew - &lt;em&gt;Communal Road to a Secular Kerala&lt;/em&gt;. Concept Publishing Company, Jan 1, 1989.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:89739ec58dfe85f6340b4ae3a94dd0f3:5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>