<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Talk Code D3.Js Visualisation on Sadique Ali</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/talk-code-d3/index.js-visualisation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Talk Code D3.Js Visualisation on Sadique Ali</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/talk-code-d3.js-visualisation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>D3.js Workshop</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/2012/08/01/d3.js-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/2012/08/01/d3.js-workshop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I did a &lt;a href=&#34;http://d3js.org&#34;&gt;d3.js&lt;/a&gt; workshop at ThoughtWorks Bangalore yesterday (31st
July, 2012). I split the workshop in to two parts. The first was a basic
introduction to d3.js - SVG, Scaling, Axes etc. The second part
was an exercise to hack together a Scatterplot with some Cricket
dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 30 people attended the workshop. I spent too much time on the first part and hence we did not have enough
time to complete the second part. This was the first ever workshop I have done
and my time plan was way off. I should fix it the next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great learning experience for me. In the process of preparing
for it and conducting it, I realised that giving talks and conducting
workshops are way different. For a talk, you have the freedom to pick
examples that are easy to explain. For a workshop, the examples have to
be easy to understand and easy to put together during the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really looking forward to watching the video of the workshop and
learning from my mistakes. Unfortunately, the video camera had some
issues and ended up recording only the first 10 minutes of the 1 hour
workshop. That was not fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the 10 minutes the camera managed to capture was still
helpful. I realized that I no longer have the annoying habit of saying
&amp;ldquo;Right&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; when speaking in front of a crowd. I appear a lot more calm
and collected. I am really happy to see that slowly but surely, I am
getting better at this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the slides in &lt;a href=&#34;http://lab.hakim.se/reveal-js/&#34;&gt;reveal.js&lt;/a&gt; and the
slides are &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/visualizations/d3-workshop/index.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The examples I used are &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sdqali/d3-dojo&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>