<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Football on Sadique Ali</title>
    <link>http://sdqali.in/categories/football/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Football on Sadique Ali</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://sdqali.in/categories/football/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Missing the game</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2010/02/05/missing-the-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2010/02/05/missing-the-game/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have continued to watch and follow the beautiful game, save for my first few months in Bangalore. This is supposed to be a metro. Well, apparently a metro where people don&amp;rsquo;t give a damn about football. After taking a cable connection, I soon realized that I will have to beg with the cable guy to put on ESPNStar so that I could watch EPL. Pretty soon, Hathway had some issues with ESPNStar, which meant there was no way I could watch ESPNStar. On the weekends, I tried to pursue the cable operator to put on NEO Sports, at least I could watch Bundes Liga and Serie A. He would not budge, and I had to endure the interesting argument that &amp;ldquo;NEO Cricket and NEO Sports are the same&amp;rdquo;. It was tough to accept - in the small village of Vadakkethala, where I hail from, I could watch as much football as I wanted. In Malappuram, if you are a cable TV operator and don&amp;rsquo;t put on channels with football on, God save you. So Bangalore&amp;rsquo;s apparent indifference to football was frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have enjoyed playing the game since I was a small kid, and that habit too has taken a hit since I came to Bangalore. The first time I went to play on a weekend, a guy with a Red and Gold shawl draped around his neck came to the ground and ordered everyone who couldn&amp;rsquo;t speak Kannada out of the ground. Since then, I have come to realize and acknowledge the power of the Red and Gold colors in Bangalore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do manage to play the game once in a while, mainly at a ground in JP Nagar. I am planning to soon join fellow Malayalees playing in a ground in Koramangala.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for watching Football, I have bought a Videocon d2h which gives me all the sports channels I want, and all the Malayalam channels the diamond pack offers is an added advantage. No more arguments with the cable TV guy about NEO Sports and NEO Cricket being two channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to watch and play a lot of football.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>