<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>{code that works}</title>
    <link>https://sdqali.in/categories/learn/index.xml?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</link>
    <description>Recent content on {code that works}</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <atom:link href="/categories/learn/index.xml?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>My experience working remotely</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/04/11/my-experience-working-remotely/?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/04/11/my-experience-working-remotely/?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;There has been a lot of debate in the tech community about working remotely and the willingness of employers to allow this option to their employees. At the very beginning of my career as a programmer, I had the opportunity to work on a distributed team. While the team was distributed, I was still working from an office and for almost half of the duration of my work on the team I had team members sitting beside me in the same office. Because of this, my scenario may not be representative of the population of programmers who work remotely. However, there are a number of things I learned from the experience that I would like to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-team&#34;&gt;The Team&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was part of a four developer team, three of whom including me were co-located at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thoughtworks.com/&#34;&gt;ThoughtWorks&lt;/a&gt; office in Bangalore. Our lead developer worked out of his house in the United Kingdom. While he had a great deal of experience writing software, the other team members had 1 year experience. This was the first ever team I was going to be part of and possibly the place where I would pick up important skills and learn a lot. We were writing mostly Ruby and JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-schedule&#34;&gt;The schedule&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our day would start with the three of us in Bangalore splitting in to a pair and a lone developer and working on code. The other developer would join around 9:00 AM GMT (~ 2:30 PM IST) and the lone developer would pair with him. Later, as the work day ended in India, the lead developer would continue to work till his day was over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;communication&#34;&gt;Communication&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would have a short (~5 minutes) Skype call at the beginning of the UK work day, where we would discuss our progress and any thing else that needed to be shared. We later moved this to the end of the India work day, because this ensured the developers in India could discuss pressing matters and blockers with the lead developer and come back with this context the following day. We always had a private I.R.C. channel running where we could jump in and discuss things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-tools&#34;&gt;The tools&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While pairing remotely, we almost always used Emacs running in the no-window mode inside a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gnu.org/software/screen/&#34;&gt;GNU screen&lt;/a&gt; session. This was great as it was a fast and glitch-free experience. Coding in an IDE and sharing the desktop was too slow. This is where I picked up my Emacs skills. While pairing, we were constantly on a Skype call talking to each other. Being glued to the computer screen for hiurs while talking to somebody over Skype with an earphone plugged in to ears can be a tiring experience. Fortunately, we made sure to take sufficient breaks in between.
We used ThoughtWorks&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thoughtworks-studios.com/mingle-agile-project-management&#34;&gt;Mingle&lt;/a&gt; as our project management tool and card wall and it proved to be really useful for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;sane-practices&#34;&gt;Sane practices&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were writing a client side JavaScript application and we were spending most of our time in an SSH session. How did we manage to make sure that things were not breaking? We did have to open up the application in our browsers to see how things got rendered and ensure that the UI workflow we were creating did not break. There are three things that helped us here. While none of these are specific to working remotely, these made life easy for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;good-code-design&#34;&gt;Good code design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took great efforts to encapsulate and structure our JavaScript code in to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model%E2%80%93view%E2%80%93controller&#34;&gt;MVC&lt;/a&gt;. This enabled us to focus on and test individual parts of the application while making sure that the rest of the application would not break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;extensive-unit-tests&#34;&gt;Extensive unit tests&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wrote extensive unit tests for our JavaScript code. This kept our code working while evolving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;headless-js-tests&#34;&gt;Headless JS tests&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Rhino&#34;&gt;Rhino&lt;/a&gt; to run JavaScript tests headlessly. This meant that we could run our tests from our terminals, while both developers looked at the results without having to bring up a browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of these were done because we were a distributed team, it was the way we used to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;mentoring&#34;&gt;Mentoring&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was great to have more experienced developers to work alongside in the same room as you. I got to pair with them and ask questions if I was unable to grasp something. However during the latter half of my work as part of the team, it was just me and the senior developer from U.K. While he took great effort to mentor me, the time difference made it harder for me because for the first half of my work day, I was coding alone and did not have some body experienced to ask questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I would say that with the right people and the right tools, you can make remote work a good experience for your team. However, if there is someone that needs to be mentored, having the mentor co-located would be a great advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Spiral of Learning</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/05/30/the-spiral-of-learning/?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/05/30/the-spiral-of-learning/?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An hour ago, I was staring at a problem on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.4clojure.com/&#34; title=&#34;4clojure&#34;&gt;4clojure&lt;/a&gt; website. Last weekend, I found myself wandering through Zed Shaw&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://c.learncodethehardway.org/&#34; title=&#34;Learn C The Hard Way&#34;&gt;Learn C the Hard Way&lt;/a&gt;. Three days before that, I was taking a stab at figuring what kind of visualizations would make sense if you want to come up with the mother of all comparison&amp;rsquo;s between two of football&amp;rsquo;s greatest ever players. Four days before that, I was looking at some classifiers. Five weeks ago, I was totally lost in &lt;a href=&#34;http://learnyousomeerlang.com/&#34; title=&#34;Learn You Some Erlang For Great Good&#34;&gt;Learn You Some Erlang&lt;/a&gt;, and three weeks before that I was trying to make sense of all the hype around Node.js.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a pattern that I have experienced throughout the last three years of my life. The technologies and tools might have been different, but the experience and the pain that leaves me in have been consistent and consistently high, respectively. I would pick up something, throw all my energy at it and would learn some stuff. And then, the day when I don&amp;rsquo;t have the energy or enthusiasm for anything comes up. I would sit there jumping between Wikipedia pages. This loss of interest would be temporary, and the following day I would have all the energy and enthusiasm in the world. And then the bad thing happens - I don&amp;rsquo;t go and pick up what I left mid-way. I would get fascinated by something totally new or something I had left halfway through two weeks ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing, I have 32 pet projects in my ~/src/play folder. Only one of them is in a complete state. Those projects totally differ from each other on what they intend to achieve. I have an OCR in there and I have a half-cooked version of what is a web interface for VLC. I have a lot of Shell scripts, Lisp snippets, Haskell, Clojure, Python, Ruby and Java in there. All semi-cooked and to be frank utterly useless. And every time I think about this, I feel bad.
&lt;div class=&#34;signup col-lg-12 col-lg-offset-0 col-md-12 col-md-offset-0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-lg-6 col-lg-offset-0 col-md-6 col-md-offset-0&#34;&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Finding this article useful?&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      My posts with working code - tested and verified - and actionable explanations for specific programming problems. Delivered each week for free.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-lg-6 col-lg-offset-0 col-md-6 col-md-offset-0&#34; id=&#34;mc_embed_signup&#34;&gt;
    &lt;form action=&#34;//codethatworks.us14.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=52d266a23636b031a38de6d70&amp;amp;id=b7e69e463e&#34; method=&#34;post&#34; id=&#34;mc-embedded-subscribe-form&#34; name=&#34;mc-embedded-subscribe-form&#34; class=&#34;validate&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; novalidate&gt;
      &lt;div id=&#34;mc_embed_signup_scroll&#34;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;mc-field-group form-group&#34;&gt;
          &lt;label for=&#34;mce-FNAME&#34;&gt;First Name&lt;/label&gt;
          &lt;input type=&#34;text&#34; value=&#34;&#34; name=&#34;FNAME&#34; class=&#34;form-control&#34; id=&#34;mce-FNAME&#34;&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;mc-field-group form-group&#34;&gt;
          &lt;label for=&#34;mce-EMAIL&#34;&gt;Email Address&lt;/label&gt;
          &lt;input type=&#34;email&#34; value=&#34;&#34; name=&#34;EMAIL&#34; class=&#34;email form-control&#34; id=&#34;mce-EMAIL&#34;&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;mce-responses&#34; class=&#34;form-group&#34;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&#34;response&#34; id=&#34;mce-error-response&#34; style=&#34;display:none&#34; class=&#34;alert alert-success&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;div class=&#34;response&#34; id=&#34;mce-success-response&#34; style=&#34;display:none&#34; class=&#34;alert alert-success&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;button type=&#34;submit&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-success&#34; id=&#34;mc-embedded-subscribe&#34; name=&#34;subscribe&#34;&gt;Join the Newsletter&lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;div style=&#34;position: absolute; left: -5000px;&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;text&#34; name=&#34;b_52d266a23636b031a38de6d70_b7e69e463e&#34; tabindex=&#34;-1&#34; value=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/form&gt;
    &lt;p class=&#34;no-spam&#34;&gt;I won&#39;t send you spam. Unsubscribe at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

I have been thinking about this a lot lately and increasingly getting concerned. I have slowly realized that there is a lot of stuff that I know bits of, but there is nothing that I have mastered. What I am doing is essentially traveling on a spiral of learning. Despite the fact that I drop and pickup new stuff every other week, I have realized that I do come back to things I abandoned. For example, I have made about 7 stabs at learning Haskell. Each time, either of these things happen - I lose interest because for want of focus or I hit an abrupt spike on the learning curve and fall back hard. But every time I go back, I have observed that I have become a better Haskell programmer. I understand functional programming much better than what I did when I took my first stab at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I have sat down and thought about it, this cycle has happened on almost all the stuff that I have picked up to learn. Arabic, Node.js, Rails, Clojure, Erlang, whatever I always come back to these for a short period of time, only to leave it abruptly. But whenever I leave, I leave with a slightly better understanding of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I am going through (Apologies for the bad diagram):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sdqali.in/images/learning_spiral.png&#34; alt=&#34;Learning Spiral&#34; title=&#34;Learning Spiral&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This diagram was created using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dabbleboard.com/&#34; title=&#34;Dabbleboard&#34;&gt;Dabbleboard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, one would want the slope of the climb to be constant and time period spent one thing to be longer. In my case, the slop is erratic and the frequency of switching between stuff is big. Over time, there is an accumulation of knowledge and it has a positive gradient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have come to realize that I am not the only one going through this. I have seen a lot of others struggling with the same spiral. From talking to people about this, one possible solution seems to be to put in a strong effort to come back to what you love most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, I am not even sure what that is. If my life depended on picking something, I would pick football. May be I should try and do football visualizations or start writing about the areas of football that interest me the most - how football acts as a mirror for the society where it gets played. I am going to try this for some time and see how that turns out. As you can see, I just signed up for one more thing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Crash and then You Learn</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/05/29/you-crash-and-then-you-learn/?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/05/29/you-crash-and-then-you-learn/?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I picked up my bicycle, climbed on it and spotted the blood on my elbows and the bunch of curious onlookers in front of the pan shop nearby, I did not feel fear or embarrassment. I had an immeasurable amount of happiness welling inside me. I had finally done what I should have about 20 years ago - I had finally managed to crash my bicycle and leave with plenty of scars to show for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am 25, and until two weeks ago I could not ride a bicycle. Two weeks ago, during a Saturday afternoon, I got on a bicycle and rode it around a football field. Well, what is so special about that, you might ask. It was pretty special to me because it was the first time I had rode a bicycle, where my definition of &amp;lsquo;ride&amp;rsquo; is &amp;lsquo;ride with a level of confidence that removes the fear on falling down!&amp;rsquo;. When it finally happened, it was like what Kevin Garnett &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3_gL_H9zAY8&#34;&gt;described&lt;/a&gt; when he finally won an NBA with the Celtics after years of disappointment with the Minnesota Timberwolves - &amp;ldquo;I Just Knocked the Bully Out&amp;rdquo;. Yes, I was emotional. No, I did not cry. But it had been a long time coming, and the journey was painful. Here is the story of me learning to cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-beginning&#34;&gt;The beginning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a kid, I did not learn to ride a bicycle. Looking back, I don&amp;rsquo;t know why. All my friends from childhood, who lived in the same neighbourhood as me learned to ride when they were small kids. I think I had developed an aversion to it even when I was a kid. It must have had something to do with me liking swimming in the streams and playing more than riding a bicycle. And yeah, there was the minor detail about neither me or any of my close friends actually owning a cycle.
When I was growing up, I spent most of my time in a residential school. In there, bicycles were a part of your fantasies about the outside world. People talked about it, fantasized about it, but never rode one. Looking back, I wonder what I did during all those vacations I had. I played more football, swam more in the streams and generally went around the village. The fact that I did not know how to ride a bicycle did not bother me in the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-frustration&#34;&gt;The frustration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began to notice this fact and get worried about it when I went to college. Where I went to colllege, Yamaha RX 100s were as uncompromise-able part of life as strike actions and political rallies. This realization soon turned in to a fear. I was keen on learning and tried it on numerous occasions in our football field. But college has an uncompromising way of dealing with such lack of abilities, and that meant that there was a big emotional barrier to overcome. I failed miserably. You see, I am kind of tall, and never fell down from a bicycle. I remember trying to ride the bicycle in the ground in pouring monsoon rains. I was not getting it. As the rain around me grew in force and malice, my impatience and frustration multiplied. That was it. I decided that I would never attempt it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite all those failings, the thing that did most to drain my confidence and enthusiasm did not happen on a bicycle. That important place in my life goes to a Mahindra jeep. Back in college, a group of my friends had this really old crazy Mahindra jeep. A lot of people used it to learn to drive or to hone their driving skills. My baggage of experiences (or the lack of it) meant that I never touched the driving wheel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-shock&#34;&gt;The shock&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One fine Sunday afternoon, we were returning after lunch at this awesome, little place that served kerala rice meals and fish. (This place is called &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ashwathi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and I recommend that if you go to Trivandrum, you should totally go there.) One of my friends who was still learning to drive was driving the jeep and it had around 12 of us inside it. Another friend of mine - S - was instructing him. When we reached the hostel and the football field, S continued to instruct the other friend. All of a sudden, I was inspired. I wanted to learn this thing. It certainly had to be less painful than learning to bicycle, I thought. I asked S if he could teach me. S immediately said Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hostel campus has a road that goes around the five or six buildings and the road&amp;rsquo;s sides are dotted with big, tall cedar trees. I climbed to the driving seat and S took the other front seat. My other fiend sat in the back. I started driving the jeep dead-slowly in the football ground. After 5 minutes or so, I was growing confident and suggested that we take it to the road. S okayed it and we began slowly driving on the road around the buildings. My confidence was soaring by now, and I was growing comfortable with the idea that I could control this behemoth of a machine. I went around the buildings four times. We were on the fag end of the road, where a right hand turn would take us to the road that ran parallel to the football field. I took the right turn, and was bringing the steering wheel back to its normal position. The old Mahindra, like its million cousins was a pain to steer. I had passed the curve and I had not yet managed to steer the jeep back to the straight position. There was a huge cedar tree on the right side about 6 meters away. I was going at 20kmph and thought I still had a lot of time to steer it back. My friend sitting in the back did not think so and shouted out that we were headed for the tree. And then, all hell broke loose. I rammed the accelerator down, thinking it was the brake, and the jeep sped in to the cedar tree. I dont remember how fast it was, but it was pretty fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We survived. I had to shell out around 6k to repair the right side of the jeep. I had managed to spectacularly break the bumper, the suspension and the brake on the right side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This incident left me with an absolute terror of vehicles and the road. When we finally managed to get the jeep repaired, my friends advised me to continue learning. I remember sitting there behind the wheels of the jeep in the football field - hands trembling, head shaking and heart racing. The fear of ending up killing somebody on the road and was real and strong. At that moment, I gave up. I decided that I would never attempt to drive in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fascination&#34;&gt;The fascination&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving to Bangalore almost three years ago changed my life in more ways than one. Playing football, the thing around which my days revolved around during college ended up being something I did once in a while. Reaching places where people played football proved to be very difficult. I remember having to hop on two buses to get to IISc. to play a game of football on Sundays and I equally remember a game of football in a ground in JP Nagar being interrupted by one of those ultra-Kannadiga politicians turning up and decreeing that only Kannadigas could play. I did discover this awesome gang that played football everyday at the Koramangala Post Office grounds. I was a regular there for a long time. Walking for 30 minutes at 6:00 AM was proving to be difficult. I really wanted to be able to transport myself to different quarters fast. Bicycle, anyone?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-retry&#34;&gt;The retry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started trying to learn to ride. My brother, who is 11 years younger than me tried to help me. But then, it never took off. The pain and embarrassment of showing off my noob-ishness on a street where the onlookers were people who slightly admired me was too much. The learning sessions lasted about ten minutes each and ended with me being left totally frustrated with myself. This was not going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;and-then-it-happened&#34;&gt;And then, it happened&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to IISc on a Saturday two weeks ago. The desire to learn had returned to me. IISc has a big football field, an my friend suggested that I ride around the field. I rode the bike and after the initial struggling to gain balance, it just came to me. I could do this thing. I was doing it. It was far from perfect, but I was comfortable, and I had balance. As I completed my first round around the football field, I felt the kind of happiness that I have seldom felt in my life. I really could do this. Three hours of riding around the ground and 15 minutes on the road that increasingly looked like the road where I had the jeep accident later, I knew that I had cracked it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-road&#34;&gt;The road&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following Friday I borrowed a friend&amp;rsquo;s bicycle. I was vary excited. I kept on telling people that I had to leave early, lest I end up under one of those sad-looking blue &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bmtcinfo.com/site/index.jsp&#34; title=&#34;BMTC&#34;&gt;BMTC&lt;/a&gt; buses. The memory of riding the bicycle on to the road from the parking lot would live with me forever. It was around 5:00pm and that is not the kind of time when a cycling noob would want to ride on Bangalore&amp;rsquo;s roads. I was afraid, and I was not making up the fear about the buses. But I knew that this time no fear of life or failure would hold me back. In that crazy rush-hour traffic, I rode home. And no, I did not end up under a bus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the following day, I practiced for close to four hours. I was getting very comfortable. And on Sunday, I rode close to 20 kilometers, more than half of it on the Bannerghatta road. There was crazy amount of traffic, I was still afraid of the buses. In fact a blue BMTC bus almost knocked me out of the road. But that had more to do with the driver of the bus being a total moron than me making any mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-crash&#34;&gt;The crash&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was returning from this ride full of pride and a more than healthy dose of confidence. I had rode 20 kilometers on some of Bangalore&amp;rsquo;s craziest roads and had done well. As I approached the place I live, I was riding pretty fast. On the penultimate turn, I sped before I had come out of the curve, and I the bicycle and me crashed hard on the tarmac. From the pain and the amount of skidding my body did on the tarmac and the flight of my spectacles, I guessed it would have been spectacular. I had a bunch of keys in my jeans pockets and one of those decided to embed it&amp;rsquo;s end to my thigh. There was a lot of blood. The pair of jeans survived, and so did my knees and elbows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-aftermath&#34;&gt;The aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I regularly ride the bicycle to the office these days. I still have not mastered it. I am still afraid of the blue BMTC buses. I still get confused when that motherly lady with the small kid decides it is a great idea to step in front of a bicycle. But, what the heck? I will ride the bicycle like I should have 20 years ago - full of pride and joy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bullet proof Jenkins setup</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/02/03/bullet-proof-jenkins-setup/?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/02/03/bullet-proof-jenkins-setup/?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#39;post&#39;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div dir=&#34;ltr&#34; style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; trbidi=&#34;on&#34;&gt;&lt;div&gt;In this
      post, I will describe how a neat setup and some discipline will
      ensure a Jenkins that can be rolled back and recreated very easily
      - a bullet proof Jenkins setup.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I have been working on
      configuring our Jenkins instance. This was the first time I had
      played around with Jenkins. I am fairly comfortable
      with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thoughtworks-studios.com/go-agile-release-management&#34;
              target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt; from ThoughtWorks Studios. All of
      my past teams used Go as their tool for continuous
      delivery.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;One of the things I found very different from
      Go in Jenkins is the absence of the notion of a Pipeline as the
      basic entity of build, as proposed
      in &lt;a href=&#34;http://continuousdelivery.com/&#34;
            target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Continuous Delivery&lt;/a&gt;. Although there are
      plugins to make this available in Jenkins, we decided to go with
      Jenkins&#39; model of Jobs.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Another difference I spotted is
      that when a custom task is defined as part of a Job, Jenkins
      creates a shell script with all the steps while executing the
      Job. In Go, each of the steps will have to be defined as a custom
      command.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We wanted to ensure that our Jenkins
      configuration is version controlled. While this is a huge win, one
      of the ways this situation deteriorates is when a large number of
      changes are made to the configuration over a period of time and
      these is not checked in. So we decided to take this one step
      further and ensure that these changes are automatically checked
      in. There are instructions on how to do this, but we had to do
      some tweaking to get this working for us.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

These are the steps to setup a bullet proof Jenkins setup. This assumes that Jenkins is running on a Linux box.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Create a Git repository in Jenkins&#39; base directory - This is generally &lt;i&gt;/var/lib/jenkins&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2.&amp;nbsp;Create a&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;.gitignore&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;file to exclude Jenkins workspaces.&amp;nbsp;The Jenkins base directory is the home directory for the Jenkins user created to run Jenkins. This means that there will be a number of&amp;nbsp;Linux user specific files like&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;.ssh/ , .gem&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;etc.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;These files need to be specified in the .gitignore file. A sample .gitignore file is listed below.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/1732836.js?file=.gitignore&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;3. Setup a Jenkins job to check in the changed configuration files every day at midnight. (Or whatever time interval you choose). Add a custom task with the following steps:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/1732873.js?file=gistfile1.sh&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;While this ensures that the configuration is more or less tracked well, there are times when somebody makes a massive change in the configuration. This is where the most important piece of the bullet proof configuration comes in - team discipline. The team should ensure that big changes are checked in as soon add possible. This can be easily done by triggering the Jenkins job manually, without having to ssh in to the Jenkins box.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Credits:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1.  The Jenkins community documentation provided a nice &lt;a href=&#34;http://jenkins-ci.org/content/keeping-your-configuration-and-data-subversion&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;starting point&lt;/a&gt; for this.&lt;br /&gt;2.  The .gitignore file was forked from &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/780105&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this gist&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sit&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;goog_1138400375&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sit&lt;/a&gt;. I have added some project specific stuff to it.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why your project should have a Getting Started guide.</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/01/17/why-your-project-should-have-a-getting-started-guide./?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/01/17/why-your-project-should-have-a-getting-started-guide./?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#39;post&#39;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;My new team at work is writing a bunch of Rails applications. This is one of those codebases that one would call &#34;legacy&#34; without much argument. Most of these apps have their own patched, vendorized Rails versions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Getting up and running was an absolute pain. This project existed before Bundler and the list of gem dependencies are not checked in. I got the output of running &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;gem list&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; on a colleague&#39;s box, wrote a Ruby script to generate a shell script that installs all the gems. When I tried running the tests in one of those apps, I got a nice error. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It looked obvious that we were using patched Rails versions. Surprisingly, theses were not checked in to the vendor/ directory. This was proving to be a pain, and today I sat with a team member and wrote a developer guide to get started on the project. We actually had to pull patched Rails tar balls from a remote box and untar them to vendor/ directory. I was really surprised that these patches had not been checked in. We checked in all the patches. Apart from the Rails patches, there was a gem that had to be checked in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is why I think every project needs a Getting Started guide:&lt;br&gt;1. As a developer joining a new team, I want to look at the code as soon as I can. For me, this involves reading and running the tests.&lt;br&gt;2. Due to various reasons, a project may have patches and dependencies. Being very specific to the project, there is no way a new developer on the team would figure out these hidden dependencies.&lt;br&gt;3. There needs to be a single place where all the dependencies are specified.&lt;br&gt;4. While spoon-feeding someone may not be the best way to get them started, a little bit of hand-holding will not do anyone any harm. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest problems I see with things like these guides is that as the application and it&#39;s dependencies evolve, the guides are not updated to reflect these changes. The only possible time the guide will be updated is when a new developer joins the team, follows these instructions and finds the need to update the guide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TWU Graduation</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2009/09/22/twu-graduation/?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2009/09/22/twu-graduation/?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I had predicted, the last week of training was hectic, chaotic and crazy. Although we ended up leaving the whole project simulation in jeopardy, we learned a lot of things, especially how things that work smoothly at one second can go wrong very very wrong the next second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had decided beforehand that I would volunteer for roles that I want to do in my career, and that at the same time would leave me out of my comfort zone. I played the BA role for two days, and although I made lots of mistakes, I did certain things well. I was appreciated for the e-mails I sent out that day. And I got some nice feedback from the head of training, and I am sure his words will help me in my way forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once BA-ing was out of the way, I was ready for some coding. But it was a learning experience in itself. On the first day of coding, I and pair spent the whole day staring at our monitor wondering why something ridiculously simple did not work the way it was supposed to do. Later in the day, we discovered that it was because somebody had written code that was simply swallowing an exception instead of throwing it up or doing something about it then and there. One feedback that I had got from my Dev trainers had warned me of exactly this sort of a thing happening, and I could see why he was very serious about this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day was luckier for me, as the pair I was part of actually managed to contribute towards completing one functionality. And we were given the t-shirts that we would wear for our graduation from TWU. During the night, I had to spend some time (read the whole night) trying to re-factor the code I had written for my assignment. In the morning, I was too tired, too sleepy and too giddy to wake up and could not attend the project simulation. I turned up in the afternoon, and found all my colleagues having lots of fun, playing dodge-ball. I learned that the project simulation had failed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a graduation ceremony at the office. Receiving the certificate from the MD, wearing our special edition t-shirts and graduation hats was a great experience. I wonder why Kerala University cannot have a graduation ceremony for B.Tech students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_bZ_kjFIgY0w/Srh7h88cjtI/AAAAAAAABQA/uq5OEtmKWkc/s320/DSC06527.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;TWU-14 graduates&#34; title=&#34;TWU-14 graduates&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TWU-14 graduates. I am somewhere in there, even I dont know where I am!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the evening, we had a graduation party at a nice place called &amp;lsquo;Take5&amp;rsquo;. The food was great, and all souls who enjoy alcohol had an even better time. I sat there with my glass of orange juice. While there was party around us in full flow, I had a nice conversation with a co-worker about philosophy and how life is sometimes very unfair. Intellectually stimulating conversation in a not-so-simulating environment! But I had to leave early, as I had to head home and appear at the Regional Passport Office, Malappuram to prove that I was indeed Sadique Ali K M. More about the passport story later!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The university experience was great, and I learned a lot from trainers and co-workers, met lots of interesting people and made friends with some of them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A lot to learn</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2009/08/21/a-lot-to-learn/?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2009/08/21/a-lot-to-learn/?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The past few days have just flown by. I had to learn so much things and did not have much time to do it. Most days, I sleep around 2:00 in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was in college, I had friends who were already working. I used to wonder why sometimes they did not reply to a mail I sent, or did not ping me back when I pinged them on IM. Well, now I know! If any of you are reading this, guys, please pardon me for not understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had an assignment to submit and I got the feedback that the work I had done was &amp;lsquo;Poor&amp;rsquo;. Had a tough time, when I got the response. But having thought about the feedback given to me about the assignment, I now understand that there are a lot of thins I need to learn, there are changes to be made in the way I approach coding, and there are some stuff to be un-learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope I will be able to cope with the pressure and move forward.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
