<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>{code that works}</title>
    <link>https://sdqali.in/categories/internet/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on {code that works}</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <atom:link href="https://sdqali.in/categories/internet/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The fear of being wrong on the Internet</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/10/15/the-fear-of-being-wrong-on-the-internet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/10/15/the-fear-of-being-wrong-on-the-internet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;All of us have opinions-some strong, some weak; some we care deeply about, some we couldn&amp;rsquo;t care less. We often express those opinions to others and sometimes people agree, sometimes they don&amp;rsquo;t. Debating with others about our opinions helps us crystallise or completely discard them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am fairly opinionated about a lot of things and have debates about them with friends and co-workers. Yet when it comes to opinions on the Internet, I shy away. Every single day, I come across issues and incidents about which I have opinions and every time I stare at what somebody else wrote, consider replying and ultimately close the tab after a minute. This happens on almost all the Internet communities I frequent - Twitter, Guardian&amp;rsquo;s Comment is Free, Guardian&amp;rsquo;s Football blogs and Hacker News.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have lately been thinking why this is happening to me and I realise that the root of this is my fear of being wrong on the Internet. Now, I am wrong a lot of the time. I have been wrong in the past and like most of humanity, I will be on occasions in the future. I am not afraid of it. In real life arguments outside the Internet, when you are wrong, people will point out what part of an argument you are wrong about and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During pretty much all the debates I have in real life, we disagree. From issues as wide as programming languages, to tech conferences to the nature of federalism in India, we mostly disagree. At lunch tables, bars, Friday nights in restaurants, we disagree. We disagree to the point where we will be visibly upset. And yet, in the end, we shake hands, hug each other, finish our drinks or dinners and go our way. And invariably both sides would have learned from each other in the duration of the debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Internet, things are different. It is extremely hard to express certain things in writing, especially on a forum where the pace of the debate is intense and there is a churn of people and acceptance levels. The fact that written conversation lacks any tone does not help one bit. People have to assume each other&amp;rsquo;s motivations and perspective and it leads to snide and caustic replies followed by more snide and caustic replies. And when there is enough quorum for a lynch mob, the person who has the minority opinion gets textually beaten up. And in the end, everyone goes their own way, without patching up and not having learned anything from each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now there are homogeneous communities where this does not happen often. People mostly get along and try to tackle the debate and not the man. But when that one person with an opinions countering the majority&amp;rsquo;s turns up, the debate takes a back seat and the regulars go in studs up and tackles the person instead of his debate which is oftentimes requires less energy to prove wrong than abusing the person expressing the opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a teenager the average YouTube comment thread will lead with &amp;ldquo;You are a faggot!&amp;rdquo; in reply to an opinion he disagrees with, places and people who consider themselves learned and sophisticated lead with comments of the &amp;ldquo;Oh, at least you can spell!&amp;rdquo; genre. Neither helps in expressing disagreement with the opinion, all the while being dangerously effective at expressing one&amp;rsquo;s displeasure for the person with the opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having said this, I still frequent these forums because I still learn a lot of things from people there. I am mostly a silent lurker and I think I will continue to be, in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Tinfoil setup</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/08/17/my-tinfoil-setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/08/17/my-tinfoil-setup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I try to be careful when I use the internet. This is not because I do illegal stuff—I just don&amp;rsquo;t like the idea of random websites tracking me across the web, recording everything I do, and then serving me advertisements. I don&amp;rsquo;t like the idea of technocracies like Facebook collecting and storing data about me, even after I have explicitly quit their colourful walled garden. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I don&amp;rsquo;t like Google tracking what websites I read by pretending to provide a service to the creators of those websites in the form of CDN and Analytics. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I don&amp;rsquo;t want marketing optimisation services to track me and put me in their funnel, unless I explicitly want to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that when I browse the web, I treat cookies, javascript code and third party content with suspicion. Over the years, my setup has evolved in to something that makes my internet use safe, all the while being useful. These are some of the things I do to ensure that sites are not tracking me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;use-different-browsers-as-sandboxes&#34;&gt;Use different browsers as sandboxes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I run at least 5 browsers. I use Firefox as my primary browser to read and access email. I run Safari to access my work email, our Mingle &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; instance, our in-house knowledge sharing network etc. I run Chromium when I am working on JavaScript and CSS because I find the development tools nothing short of a joy to use. I also have to use Google Chrome from time to time because that is what a lot of our customers use to access our product and sometimes I have to test our systems on Google Chrome. This separation of browsing into sandboxes makes it easy to control your usage patterns on a website. I have my Firefox set up to use DuckDuckGo as the search engine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-aggressive-etc-hosts&#34;&gt;An aggressive /etc/hosts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a long (5731 lines) &lt;em&gt;/etc/hosts&lt;/em&gt; file. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I use this method to filter out stuff because it is a text file and it is easy to make sense of what it does. I adopted it from &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/leto/Util&#34;&gt;Duke Leto&amp;rsquo;s Util&lt;/a&gt; repository. His file blocks a wide variety of website and over time I have added all the domains for social networks, advertising networks and marketing automation sites that I have come across to it. This ensures that when I navigate to a website and it has a bunch of tracking code from Facebook in the form of Like/Share buttons, my system won&amp;rsquo;t even load these resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;disable-third-party-cookies&#34;&gt;Disable third party cookies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third party cookies are great for tracking people across websites, often without the their knowledge or permission. My observation is that in my every day use of the web, there is nothing beneficial to me arising from websites&amp;rsquo; use of third party cookies. I block third party cookies on browsers. Most browsers allow third party cookies by default, but make it reasonably easy to block them. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ghostery&#34;&gt;Ghostery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ghostery.com/&#34;&gt;Ghostery&lt;/a&gt; is a browser plugin that blocks a large number of advertising, marketing and banner content on web pages. Ghostery is available for all the major browsers. While setting up Ghostery, one has to be careful to choose settings in such a way that all sites in Ghostery&amp;rsquo;s available list of dodgy websites get blocked, because the default settings allow some sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;noscript&#34;&gt;NoScript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://noscript.net/&#34;&gt;NoScript&lt;/a&gt; is a browser plugin for the Mozilla suite that allows users to verify the content being loaded by webpages and execute them if and only if the user trusts the content. It works really well and allows you to configure exceptions for the websites you absolutely trust. The only flipside of this is that a large percentage of the web is dependent on JavaScript and plugins and when you browse the web with NoScript, it appears way different to you from the one without NoScript. But at this point, I am willing to make that compromise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;self-destructing-cookies&#34;&gt;Self destructing cookies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self destructing cookies is a Firefox plugin that destroys cookies and LocalStorage the moment you close a tab associated with a site.  It allows whitelists, so you can configure exceptions for sites you trust. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/self-destructing-cookies/&#34;&gt;plugin&amp;rsquo;s profile&lt;/a&gt; has a more comprehensive story on why you should use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tor-bundle&#34;&gt;Tor Bundle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This goes without saying. If you read articles of political nature on the web, please install the Tor bundle &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and do your reading there. Tor has a community behind it and actively patches it against vulnerabilities. The project&amp;rsquo;s F.A.Q. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is a good starting point to learn more about Tor and how to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am in no way claiming that you would be saved from tracking if you use this setup. This is not the perfect setup. I am sure Google knows to some extent I do on the web. I am sure Facebook still has a lot of data about me. However, this is a good starting point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;I &lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/11/why-i-am-not-on-facebook/&#34;&gt;deleted my Facebook account&lt;/a&gt; over two year ago. But it is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zdnet.com/firm-facebooks-shadow-profiles-are-frightening-dossiers-on-everyone-7000017199/&#34;&gt;now known&lt;/a&gt; that Facebook keeps a dossier on people, even the ones that does not have an account, simply because they happen to be in the address books of people who give Facebook access to their address, falling for Facebook&amp;rsquo;s cajoling.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Google provides a &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/speed/libraries/devguide&#34;&gt;Content Delivery Network&lt;/a&gt; for the popular JavaScript libraries. They also have a free analytics service.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Mingle is the best project management tool out there. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to take my word for it, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thoughtworks.com/mingle&#34;&gt;try it for yourself&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;The hosts file is used by the networking stack on a system to map hostnames to IP addresses. This allows a user to block domains by looping them back to 127.0.0.1. Wikipedia, as always have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hosts_%28file%29&#34;&gt;good article&lt;/a&gt; about it.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;CNET - &lt;a href=&#34;http://howto.cnet.com/8301-11310_39-20042703-285/disable-third-party-cookies-in-ie-firefox-and-google-chrome/&#34;&gt;Disable third-party cookies in IE, Firefox, and Google Chrome&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;The Tor Bundle is a fork of Firefox configured to enhance anonymity and prevent tracking. It comes configured to use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.torproject.org/&#34;&gt;Tor network&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.torproject.org/docs/faq.html.en&#34;&gt;Tor F.A.Q.&lt;/a&gt;, on Tor Project&amp;rsquo;s website.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When Link titles were for the early adopters</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/08/11/when-link-titles-were-for-the-early-adopters/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/08/11/when-link-titles-were-for-the-early-adopters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While doing some reading up on the comparative merits of using footnotes and hyperlinks in web pages, I came across an article &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; from 1998 by Jakob Nielsen &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; about using the then nascent &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;title&lt;/em&gt; attribute on hyperlinks to inform users as to where clicking on a URL is going to take them. It is a very interesting read and makes passionate if not compelling arguments in favour of using the title attribute to improve the usability of a web page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is something interesting in the article that made me think about the evolution of the web. To quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;early-adoption-of-link-titles-recommended&#34;&gt;Early Adoption of Link Titles Recommended&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally, I advise against using new Web technologies for the first year after they have been introduced. In most cases, using anything new is asking for trouble and will alienate users with older browsers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Link titles are an exception to the need to wait a year. First, their use does not hurt users with browsers that don&amp;rsquo;t display link titles (assuming you follow the guideline to keep the link anchor understandable when the link title is not displayed). Second, a browser that does not understand link titles will simply skip them. Since the title is not a new tag or otherwise intended to influence the layout of the page, the page will look exactly the same whether or not the browser does anything with the link titles. The only downside is that link titles will add approximately 0.1 seconds to the download time for a typical Web page over a modem connection. This is a rather harsh penalty, but worth paying because of the increased navigation usability for those users who do get to see the link titles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of that again. This was written when the &lt;em&gt;title&lt;/em&gt; attribute was a new addition to the specification and the attribute was available to only a small percentage of internet users &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The fact that this was written in 1998 shows how young the web really is, and how fast it has grown. Nielsen advises people to adopt the new technology, putting aside his usual reservation for adopting new technologies which may break the web for people with older browsers. The care people paid to backward compatibility and usability is amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second paragraph highlights the importance of not breaking things when you want to take things forward. Sure, there are cases when you want to push technologies forward with such passion and aggression that the only way you would take the web forward involves breaking some things. In this case, title being an attribute made sure that old browsers would continue to render pages like they used to while new browsers would push the envelop, even if by a very small margin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A short and rather unscientific survey of some of my favourite websites shows me that today, not many use the title attribute. The Guardian does not use the attribute, while The Hindu uses the attribute to show a user when an article was first published and when it was last edited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sdqali.in/images/the_hindu_title_tooltip.png&#34; alt=&#34;The Hindu adds a title with time stamps of when an article was created and edited&#34; title=&#34;The Hindu shows title for hyperlinks&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of the other websites I frequent seems to use it. Nielsen&amp;rsquo;s own website does a great job of utilising it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sdqali.in/images/nielsen_title_tooltip_original_size.png&#34; alt=&#34;Nielsen&#39;s blog Alertbox adds a title for links&#34; title=&#34;Nielsen&#39;s blog Alertbox shows title for hyperlinks&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the title attribute is not exactly a panacea. XMLPlease &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; makes some compelling arguments against the title attribute &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The argument that the title attribute is rendered in small fonts is a very important one. For some reason, browsers even today choose to render tooltips that are used to display the titles as yellow boxes and does not respect font sizes, styles or zooming preferences. This can be demonstrated on Nielsen&amp;rsquo;s own website, viewing the same page shown in the previous image, but with a high zoom level. Despite the high zoom level, the tool tip and hence the title are displayed in small fonts. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sdqali.in/images/nielsen_title_tooltip_zoom.png&#34; alt=&#34;Tooltip boxes does not change size when a web page is zoomed in&#34; title=&#34;Nielsen&#39;s Alertbox shows tooltip boxes does not change size when a web page is zoomed in.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important thing the quote includes is the &lt;em&gt;0.1 seconds&lt;/em&gt; penalty a title attribute adds to the load time for a website. I have not checked the state of this now, but I doubt if it has any non-negligible effect on the load time. The web has made great progress. But I digress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally have come to like footnotes. They make the pages look organised, and let&amp;rsquo;s the author provide enough details about a topic with out having to drag the entire article towards that topic. Does this mean that we should make all links footnotes? I like this idea on some level, but I am continuing to read more about this topic and will write about it in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nngroup.com/articles/using-link-titles-to-help-users-predict-where-they-are-going/&#34;&gt;Using Link Titles to Help Users Predict Where They Are Going.&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Jakob Nielsen, Ph.D. is one of the pioneers of web usability. He publishes his thoughts around the subject on his blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nngroup.com/articles/&#34;&gt;Alertbox&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;The title attribute was proposed in RFC 1866, &lt;a href=&#34;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1866#section-5.7&#34;&gt;section 5.7.3&lt;/a&gt;, in 1995. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.blooberry.com/indexdot/html/supportkey/a.htm&#34;&gt;Internet Explorer 4.0B1&lt;/a&gt; which was released in April, 1997 was the first browser to implement the attribute.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;In April, 1997, when the attribute was first used by Internet Explorer 4.0B1, Netscape Navigator had &lt;em&gt;81.13 %&lt;/em&gt; of the browser market share, while Internet Explorer was far behind at &lt;em&gt;12.13 %&lt;/em&gt;. By April, 1998, around the time Nielsen wrote his article, Internet Explorer had grown to &lt;em&gt;22.7 %&lt;/em&gt; of the market share, while Netscape Navigator had been pegged back to &lt;em&gt;70 %&lt;/em&gt;. Both data points are from Wikipedia&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Usage_share_of_web_browsers#Reports_from_before_year_2000&#34;&gt;summary&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cc.gatech.edu/gvu/user_surveys/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;GVU WWW user surveys&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from January, 1994 to October, 1998.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xmlplease.com/&#34;&gt;XMLPlease&lt;/a&gt; is a collection of articles and tutorials around XML technologies by Jesper Tverskov.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Why the title attribute is 99% bad. From &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xmlplease.com/footnotes#s1.&#34;&gt;The benefits of footnotes in webpages - XMLPlease&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Both screen shots were taken with the page rendered on Safari 6.0.5 (8536.30.1) on Mac OS X.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When URL shortening results in longer URLs</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/08/11/when-url-shortening-results-in-longer-urls/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/08/11/when-url-shortening-results-in-longer-urls/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have previously &lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/07/17/social-networks-and-url-shorteners/&#34;&gt;written&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/23/dear-content-creator-your-url-shortener-is-pointless/&#34;&gt;how social networks&lt;/a&gt; use URL shortening as a way of obscuring and swallowing information about sharing of content on their platform. In Twitter&amp;rsquo;s case, this means that all URLs are automatically &amp;lsquo;shortened&amp;rsquo; with their &lt;em&gt;t.co&lt;/em&gt; domain. All their official clients take this shortening into account when you create a Tweet so as to avoid a round trip across the network to figure out if the tweet is short enough. But what happens if you are posting a URL that does not require any shortening? Something interesting happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember how tweets are of 140 characters each? Similarly, all URLs piped through &lt;em&gt;t.co&lt;/em&gt; are of 22 characters. That means when you post a tweet that has a URL in it, 22 characters get used for the URL. This catch-all shortening results in scenarios like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sdqali.in/images/aggressive_url_shortening.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Twitter client shortening qz.com&amp;quot;&#34; title=&#34;Twitter client shortening qz.com&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typing the 6 characters in &lt;em&gt;qz.com&lt;/em&gt; resulted in number of characters left to go from &lt;code&gt;107&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;85&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There you have it. A URL of 6 characters gets &amp;lsquo;shortened&amp;rsquo; to 22 characters. This once again shows how Twitter, like other social networking sites want to control the data about how URLs get shared.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fusing the old media and the new</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/08/10/fusing-the-old-media-and-the-new/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/08/10/fusing-the-old-media-and-the-new/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From Kara Swisher&amp;rsquo;s well written &lt;a href=&#34;http://allthingsd.com/20130807/dear-jeff-bezos-heres-what-i-saw-as-an-analog-nobody-in-the-mailroom-of-the-washington-post/?mod=thisweek&#34;&gt;open letter to Jeff Bezos&lt;/a&gt; in the light of the latter&amp;rsquo;s announcement that he has bought the Washington Post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, the most important trick is to deeply inculcate the joy of Internet journalism, without losing (actually restoring to some degree, after recent cutbacks) the great editorial values and breakthrough journalism of the Post. Fusing the old-media storytelling and news-integrity values that I learned at the Post with the Internet values of speed and personality — and, well, some level of fun at the right times — is critical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, make it clear that it is possible to do great journalism in an Internet way — even more possible because you’re freer and, most of all, readers want to read it that way. That entails inspiring the staffers of the newspaper to create content that is — as it has been — accurate, ethically sound, of high quality, but also much more compelling, and delivered in a way that modern customers want to consume it. Formulate those big stories primarily on the Web, and allow a conversation with readers to bubble up from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please go ahead and read it, if you have not. It is long, but it is all stuff and no fluff. And it features a cat picture, if you are into that kind of things. The important thing is it makes a number of interesting, personal observations about the Post&amp;rsquo;s hesitation to embrace the web, gained from Swisher&amp;rsquo;s years at the Post during the rise of the Internet and expresses hope and apprehension about Bezos&amp;rsquo;s stewardship of the legendary news paper. The above quote stood out for me. It perfectly expresses both the potential and the pitfalls that await the Post under the aegis of a man of the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Internet in Yemen : A Tale of Woe</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/08/08/internet-in-yemen--a-tale-of-woe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/08/08/internet-in-yemen--a-tale-of-woe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Haykal Bafana paints a &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.haykal.sg/index.php/yemen1/20-ec/20-internet-in-yemen-a-tale-of-woe&#34;&gt;sad picture&lt;/a&gt; of the state of internet access in Yemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each time a saboteur cuts the fiber optic lines in Marib, Internet access in Sanaa and even eastern Yemeni regions such as Hadhramaut are affected severely. Many have asked me before : why should a sparsely populated desert area like Marib be so critical to Yemen&amp;rsquo;s Internet service? A detour into the murky history of Yemeni telecommunications is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite some of the world&amp;rsquo;s most important undersea cable networks &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; passing through Yemen&amp;rsquo;s maritime borders and one of them having two landing points &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; inside Yemen, the country&amp;rsquo;s sole internet provider buys internet from Saudi Arabia&amp;rsquo;s STC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a fascinating story about the confluence of politics, corruption and technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I-ME-WE&#34;&gt;I-ME-WE&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Europe_India_Gateway&#34;&gt;Europe India Gateway&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EASSy&#34;&gt;EASSy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fiber-Optic_Link_Around_the_Globe#Segment_FLAG_Alcatel-Lucent_Optical_Network_.28FALCON.29&#34;&gt;Falcon&lt;/a&gt; pass through Yemeni maritime borders. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cablemap.info/&#34;&gt;Greg&amp;rsquo;s Cablemap&lt;/a&gt; provides an interactive map of the under sea cable system.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Falcon has landing points and Al Hudaydah and Al Ghaydah.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My thoughts on Android fragmentation -  It is not a bad thing</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/07/30/my-thoughts-on-android-fragmentation----it-is-not-a-bad-thing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/07/30/my-thoughts-on-android-fragmentation----it-is-not-a-bad-thing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;OpenSignal released the July 2013 edition &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of their State of Android report. Among many things like the dominance of Samsung, HTC&amp;rsquo;s faltering performance and Motorola&amp;rsquo;s struggle, it points out that the Android device landscape is more fragmented than ever. Out of &lt;em&gt;682000&lt;/em&gt; devices surveyed for the report, &lt;em&gt;11868&lt;/em&gt; distinct devices were seen. This has met with cries of anguish from Developers and the usual suspects &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a very important point in the OpenSignal report that gets ignored or does not get as much focus as it deserves. To quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For consumers, extreme fragmentation means that they can get exactly the phone they want – big or small, cheap or expensive, with any number of different feature combinations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of people, especially from the Valley and in love with Apple&amp;rsquo;s excellent devices point this out as evidence of Android&amp;rsquo;s cheapness. I think Android fragmentation is not a bad thing. I will try to make this point below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;fragmentation-means-android-provides-à-la-carte-smartness&#34;&gt;Fragmentation means Android provides &lt;em&gt;à la carte&lt;/em&gt; smartness.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple provides well-engineered, extremely well-designed our-way-or-high-way devices. These are loved by a lot of people and evidently work very well for them. But fragmentation means  that Android is able to be a vehicle for devices with &lt;em&gt;à la carte&lt;/em&gt; smartness. Want a big screen? Or you feel you want a small screen to fit your hand? There is an Android device for you.
Want a really good camera? Or you don&amp;rsquo;t care about taking photos? There is an Android device for both cases.
Does not want WiFi support on your device because you live in a part of the of the world where you would pretty much never encounter a WiFi hot-spot? Or you always have a hot-spot near you? No problem. There are Android devices that fit either use cases.
Are you a programmer in the valley and can afford pretty much any smart device you want? Or you are a daily wage laborer in rural India? No problem. There are Android devices for both of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;fragmentation-allows-android-to-put-smart-devices-in-more-hands&#34;&gt;Fragmentation allows Android to put smart devices in more hands.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fragmentation caused by manufacturers from Asia who make devices tailored for the budgets of the emerging markets they serve has pushed smart device adoption forward. In a market like India, local manufacturers like Karbonn and Micromax provide competition for Samsung. According to a recent study &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,  Micromax and Karbonn occupy the 2nd and 3rd spot in the smart device market with 19.3% and 8.6%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;seriously-smart-devices-are-not-about-the-developers&#34;&gt;Seriously, smart devices are not about the developers.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers seem to have a negative view towards the fragmentation on the Android platform. This is understandable because they have to spend money and effort to support a large number of devices and screen sizes. In my opinion Developers are wrong to think that smart devices are about them. It is about the users. The average smart device user in my village back home in India does not care about your cool new app that delivers commodity X to the doorsteps or lets you ask for a black taxi. He cares about being able to browse, update Facebook and make Skype calls. And that is okay because Facebook, Microsoft and Google have the Engineering strength and money to build apps that cater to the whole spectrum of Android devices. Of course, you will have trouble if you want to do with your app and will choose instead to not support those devices at the low end of the spectrum. That is okay. These smart device owners won&amp;rsquo;t miss you, because they don&amp;rsquo;t need your app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://opensignal.com/reports/fragmentation-2013/&#34;&gt;Android Fragmentation Report July 2013 - OpenSignal&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://daringfireball.net/linked/2013/07/30/bbc-android&#34;&gt;Daring Fireball taking yet another dig at Android&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://cmrindia.com/more-than-73-5-million-mobile-handsets-shipped-in-india-during-january-april-2013-a-yoy-growth-of-11-1/&#34;&gt;CMR’s India Monthly Mobile Handsets Market Review, April 2013, June 2013&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dear Content Creator, Your URL Shortener Is Pointless</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/23/dear-content-creator-your-url-shortener-is-pointless/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/23/dear-content-creator-your-url-shortener-is-pointless/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;People love URL shorteners. They are everywhere. You can use one of
&lt;a href=&#34;http://goo.gl&#34;&gt;the giants&lt;/a&gt;, or use one of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly&#34;&gt;URL Shortening As A Service&lt;/a&gt; options available
or you can run one on your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But none of that matters. Apart from adding to the redirect hell
prevalent on the web today and giving you a minor branding push, custom
URL shorteners does not add anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People started using these shortening services because of two
reasons. The first reason was the necessity to share
ugly URLs like
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://example.com/reports.php?start=2001&amp;amp;end=2010&amp;amp;item=Foo%20bar&#34;&gt;http://example.com/reports.php?start=2001&amp;amp;end=2010&amp;amp;item=Foo%20bar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and
they wanted to make it easier on the eyes of people. The second reason
was the limit on the number of characters allowed in a post by micro blogging services
like Twitter and Identi.ca.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once they became popular, people started using it everywhere, even in places like Facebook posts where there were
no limit on the number of characters in a post or comment. People also
started shortening URLs that were not particularly ugly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, the social networks
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/07/17/social-networks-and-url-shorteners/&#34;&gt;got on the game&lt;/a&gt;
and from that point, every single URL shared on those social networks had to go
through one more extra redirect. Some &lt;a href=&#34;http://royal.pingdom.com/2010/09/22/is-the-web-heading-toward-redirect-hell/&#34;&gt;had predicted&lt;/a&gt; this redirect
hell long ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the social networks were setting up their own
&lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.twitter.com/blog/introducing-twitter-web-analytics&#34;&gt;analytics service&lt;/a&gt;
around the URLs their users shared on them, content creators started
using their own custom URL shorteners. The BBC uses &lt;em&gt;bbc.in&lt;/em&gt;, the
Guardian uses &lt;em&gt;gu.com&lt;/em&gt; and Business Insider uses &lt;em&gt;read.bi&lt;/em&gt;. And it is
not just big players in the content space that uses URL
shorteners, this is prevalent among blogs too. For example,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.arabist.net/&#34;&gt;The Arabist&lt;/a&gt; uses &lt;em&gt;arb.st&lt;/em&gt;, which is in turn
hosted by &lt;em&gt;bit.ly&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But once Twitter, Facebook and Google+ came to the table and decided to
take their pound of meat from the redirect hell, all this custom URL
shortening became pointless. These social networks do not expose any data about the
shared URL. In Twitter&amp;rsquo;s case for example, all you as a website know is
that some traffic came to a particular page from a URL that looks like
&lt;em&gt;t.co/Foobar&lt;/em&gt;. If you want to make more sense of the who, when and how
aspects of your content being shared on Twitter, you have to ask
Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the fact that those shortened URLs are &lt;em&gt;short&lt;/em&gt; are does not serve
much purpose because Twitter automatically
wrap a &lt;em&gt;t.co&lt;/em&gt; URL around anything you post to it and show the a link
with the original URL as the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So content creators, please stop running your own URL shortening
services and contributing to the redirect hell. The web will be a better
place for it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I am not on Facebook</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/11/why-i-am-not-on-facebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/11/why-i-am-not-on-facebook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday a colleague of mine asked me if I was on Facebook. He
was genuinely surprised by my reply that I was not and he wanted to know
 why. For the next 20 minutes or so, I explained to him why I quit
 Facebook and does not want anything to do with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not the first time I have had to explain my absence from Facebook. In this post I will explain my attitude towards Facebook in a more structured manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broadly, these are the points I will touch upon:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Narcissism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Symmetric nature of sharing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The social pressure to &amp;lsquo;friend&amp;rsquo; someone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low signal to noise ratio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;narcissism&#34;&gt;Narcissism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have observed that Facebook makes people a lot more narcissistic than
they are in their real life. Facebook does this by providing a
convenient avenue to channel people&amp;rsquo;s self-love and then use the social
pressure of the system to create incentive for people to use this
avenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an example that explains this well. I have seen people go to beautiful hill-sides and instead of enjoying
the nature around them, they start shooting photos of themselves with
the scenery in the background. This is a carefully executed ritual and
involves careful posing and choosing spots that maximises potential
&lt;strong&gt;Likes&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Comments&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have done this and observed a lot of people do it. Looking back, I
wish  had spent that time observing and appreciating the beauty of the
scenery around me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, one might point out that generating content as a fodder
for social networks is endemic to all social networks and no just
Facebook. This is where the lure of the &lt;strong&gt;Likes&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Comments&lt;/strong&gt; and the
social pressure to gather them comes in to play. Being able to generate
&lt;strong&gt;Likes&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Comments&lt;/strong&gt; becomes closely tied to your identity on
Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;symmetric-nature-of-sharing&#34;&gt;Symmetric nature of sharing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook relationships are fundamentally symmetric i.e. if &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; is your
&lt;strong&gt;Friend&lt;/strong&gt;, then you are &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;Friend&lt;/strong&gt; as well. This is drastically
different from the way relationship manifest in Twitter. The issue with
this symmetric relationship is that if &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; would like to consume the
content that you post to Facebook, he will have to be your &lt;strong&gt;Friend&lt;/strong&gt;
which immediately results in you having to consume content posted by
&lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt;. This becomes increasingly annoying if you do not particularly like
cat pictures but Bob who likes cat pictures would likes to view the
photos you share. All of a sudden, you find yourself staring at cat
pictures from Bob.
Facebook later introduced asymmetric sharing with the concept of
&lt;strong&gt;Subscribe&lt;/strong&gt;, but unless you were a celebrity, you still got friendship
requests from people who would like to view your posts.
There is an obvious solution to this problem - just don&amp;rsquo;t accept that
friendship request from Bob. But unfortunately, this is easier said than
done, for the reason I talk about next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-social-pressure-to-friend-someone&#34;&gt;The social pressure to &amp;lsquo;friend&amp;rsquo; someone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You get a friendship request from Alice who is a colleague. You do not
necessarily consider Alice a friend and you do not share common
interests. At that point you find yourself having to accept Alice as a &lt;strong&gt;Friend&lt;/strong&gt; on Facebook because of the social
pressures associated with it.
You could be clever and ask Facebook to hide the updates from Alice, but
then you have to be an expert who knows where exactly Facebook decides
to hide the settings that allow you to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;low-signal-to-noise-ratio&#34;&gt;Low signal to noise ratio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could be a manifestation of the large number of people on Facebook
and the relative esoteric and geeky nature of other social networks I
use, like Twitter. I have observed that my Facebook home page contained
a lot of noise compared to my Twitter stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find useful content on Twitter whereas my Facebook home page showed me
a lot of obscure photo-shopped images, animated GIFs and useless FUD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;quitting-facebook&#34;&gt;Quitting Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After suspending, deleting and re-creating my Facebook profile once I
deleted it for good in July, 2011. I let people whom I consider as
friends know that I would be available on my phone and through email. I
started calling up my friends instead of &lt;strong&gt;Liking&lt;/strong&gt; their updates and
photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blocking-facebook&#34;&gt;Blocking Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a well known fact that Facebook tracks people on the web using the
myriad of widgets, plugins and buttons they have managed to spread to
most of the web. My response has been to block anything to do with
Facebook. I use the cheap and simple way of using my &lt;strong&gt;/etc/hosts&lt;/strong&gt; to
accomplish this. After many changes, this is how the Facebook related
part of it looks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34; style=&#34;background: #f0f3f3&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;line-height: 125%&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;127.0.0.1 facebook.com
127.0.0.1 fbcdn.com
127.0.0.1 fbcdn.net
127.0.0.1 login.facebook.com
127.0.0.1 static.ak.connect.facebook.com
127.0.0.1 static.ak.fbcdn.com
127.0.0.1 static.ak.fbcdn.net
127.0.0.1 www.facebook.com
127.0.0.1 www.fbcdn.com
127.0.0.1 www.fbcdn.net
127.0.0.1 www.login.facebook.com
127.0.0.1 www.static.ak.connect.facebook.com
127.0.0.1 www.static.ak.fbcdn.com
127.0.0.1 www.static.ak.fbcdn.net
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current incarnation is adapted from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://nonzen.in/2012/06/17/etchosts.html&#34;&gt;Sajith Sasidharan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There. That is my Facebook story.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Networks and their URL Shorteners</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/07/17/social-networks-and-their-url-shorteners/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/07/17/social-networks-and-their-url-shorteners/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been noticing lately that much of the traffic that my blog
receives comes from Twitter&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;t.co&lt;/strong&gt; domain or Google+&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;strong&gt;plus.url.google.com&lt;/strong&gt; domain. I don&amp;rsquo;t receive much traffic and I don&amp;rsquo;t
particularly care about the amount of traffic. However, when I
see traffic from Google+ or Twitter, I know that somebody is discussing
or sharing my posts and I am curious to know who is doing that. But if I
look at where the traffic comes from, with the hope that I will be able
to find Tweets or Google+ updates where people are talking about my
content, all I would be able to see is a &lt;strong&gt;t.co&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;plus.url.google.com&lt;/strong&gt;
URL that redirects to my page. While it is mildly frustrating, I have
been thinking why both Twitter and Google+ replace every URL users share
on their network and replace it with their own URLs that does a redirect
to the original content being shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I finally understand why. Data about user&amp;rsquo;s sharing content is
of huge interest to a lot of people, most importantly marketers. URL
shortening services like &lt;a href=&#34;http://bitly.com&#34;&gt;bit.ly&lt;/a&gt; have been able to
come up with some interesting analysis about content sharing trends. The
difference now is that the social networks themselves have taken over
URL shortening and by way of that capturing and hiding user&amp;rsquo;s sharing
habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this scenario. You find something interesting on the web that
you would like your followers and friends to see. It could be a new interesting
startup, a programmer&amp;rsquo;s rant, a tutorial, a new framework or the
Internet&amp;rsquo;s most favourite thing - cat pictures. You have a browser
plugin that nicely shortens the rather long URL and gives you a new
&lt;strong&gt;bit.ly&lt;/strong&gt; URL. You share it on Twitter. Twitter does not post the nice
&lt;strong&gt;bit.ly&lt;/strong&gt; URL. Instead, it converts it into a &lt;strong&gt;t.co&lt;/strong&gt; URL that redirects
to the &lt;strong&gt;bit.ly&lt;/strong&gt; URL. From that point onwards, all &lt;strong&gt;bit.ly&lt;/strong&gt; knows is that
a lot of people are sharing a particular &lt;strong&gt;t.co&lt;/strong&gt; URL. Unless they figure
out where the &lt;strong&gt;t.co&lt;/strong&gt; URL redirects to or does a Twitter search for the
URL, they don&amp;rsquo;t have a clear idea of who shared the URL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the impact of this, lets look at another
scenario. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/HonestFrank&#34;&gt;Francis Keogh&lt;/a&gt;, a journalist
with the BBC shares a piece of Football transfer news on Twitter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/e2tqA.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Screenshot of tweet saying &#39;West Ham close on deal to sign Mali striker Modibo Maiga&#39;&amp;quot;&#34; title=&#34;Screenshot of tweet saying &#39;West Ham close on deal to sign Mali striker Modibo Maiga&#39;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He obviously uses a shortened URL generated with BBC&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;bbc.in&lt;/strong&gt;
shortener. BBC, being the media company they are have huge interest in
knowing who shares their content, when and where. But all that their
analytics system setup around &lt;strong&gt;bbc.in&lt;/strong&gt; will be able to tell is that a
lot of traffic is coming from the URL &lt;a href=&#34;http://t.co/a0Sh34av&#34;&gt;http://t.co/a0Sh34av&lt;/a&gt; which is not of much use to
them because it strips the &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt; aspects of the act of
sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now here comes the money part of it. There is somebody who has full
knowledge of this sharing - Twitter. They know who, when and where the
content was shared by. If media companies and others want to figure out
who shares their content, you have to ask Twitter. And it looks like to
me that Twitter won&amp;rsquo;t give that information away easily. Twitter could
charge these companies and I would think that there will be a lot of
companies interested in buying this data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I showed an example of how Twitter does this, Google+ does
something very similar. And I would assume Facebook does the same with
its &lt;strong&gt;fb.me&lt;/strong&gt; URL shortener. I am not sure, and I can not verify because I
don&amp;rsquo;t have a Facebook account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, social networks that are about sharing hides knowledge
about the content people share behind a system that only they have
access to and can potentially make a lot of money from that data. Pretty
clever of them, if you ask me.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>