<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>{code that works}</title>
    <link>https://sdqali.in/categories/talk/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on {code that works}</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <atom:link href="https://sdqali.in/categories/talk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>D3.js Workshop</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/01/d3.js-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/01/d3.js-workshop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I did a &lt;a href=&#34;http://d3js.org&#34;&gt;d3.js&lt;/a&gt; workshop at ThoughtWorks Bangalore yesterday (31st
July, 2012). I split the workshop in to two parts. The first was a basic
introduction to d3.js - SVG, Scaling, Axes etc. The second part
was an exercise to hack together a Scatterplot with some Cricket
dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 30 people attended the workshop. I spent too much time on the first part and hence we did not have enough
time to complete the second part. This was the first ever workshop I have done
and my time plan was way off. I should fix it the next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great learning experience for me. In the process of preparing
for it and conducting it, I realised that giving talks and conducting
workshops are way different. For a talk, you have the freedom to pick
examples that are easy to explain. For a workshop, the examples have to
be easy to understand and easy to put together during the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really looking forward to watching the video of the workshop and
learning from my mistakes. Unfortunately, the video camera had some
issues and ended up recording only the first 10 minutes of the 1 hour
workshop. That was not fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the 10 minutes the camera managed to capture was still
helpful. I realized that I no longer have the annoying habit of saying
&amp;ldquo;Right&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; when speaking in front of a crowd. I appear a lot more calm
and collected. I am really happy to see that slowly but surely, I am
getting better at this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the slides in &lt;a href=&#34;http://lab.hakim.se/reveal-js/&#34;&gt;reveal.js&lt;/a&gt; and the
slides are &lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/visualizations/d3-workshop/index.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The examples I used are &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sdqali/d3-dojo&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>XConf 6 - Data, My Heart!</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/07/16/xconf-6---data-my-heart/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/07/16/xconf-6---data-my-heart/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday,  Srijayanth Sridhar (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/craftybones&#34;&gt;@craftybones&lt;/a&gt;) and I gave a talk at XConf, ThoughtWorks India&amp;rsquo;s internal conference series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talked about visualising data, and the various visualisations that one could use to answer questions about the dataset you have. We looked at two particular datasets -  one showing the consumption of juice at the fresh juice counter in office and one about Indian and Pakistani players. We looked at various visualizations like Area charts, Box Plots, Chord Diagrams, Line Charts, Pie Charts, Donut Charts, Small Multiples, Spark Lines, Stack Charts and Treemaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk went well and we got a lot of good feedback. I thought it was an engaging session for the audience because the visualisations we showed revealed a great deal about juice consumption in the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am waiting for the video of our talk to be made available. Last time I gave a talk at XConf, I made a lot of stupid mistakes like saying &amp;ldquo;Right&amp;rdquo; a many many times. I believe I did not make the same mistake this time. But I will have to wait and see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting together this talk took a lot of effort, the biggest of them being the process of typing out large number of ledgers. We had planned to visualise about 6 months worth of data, but ended up using only 1 month&amp;rsquo;s worth. We learned a lot of things in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, Srijayanth did most of the hardwork, while I helped put together the visualisations and the presentation, which incidentally used &lt;a href=&#34;http://imakewebthings.com/deck.js/&#34;&gt;deck.js&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks, man!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can take a look at the presentation &lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/visualizations/datamyheart/presentation/index.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The code for the whole thing can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sdqali/datamyheart&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; on Github.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>VodQA NCR: Maintaining Large Test Suites</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/06/24/vodqa-ncr-maintaining-large-test-suites/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/06/24/vodqa-ncr-maintaining-large-test-suites/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/craftybones&#34;&gt;Srijayanth Sridhar&lt;/a&gt; and I did a talk yesterday at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thoughtworks.com/events/the-testing-spirit&#34;&gt;vodQA NCR&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk was about what makes maintenance of large test suites a pain and the
things that have worked for us and we have seen work for other teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It went well and we got a lot of good feedback from the crowd. The prezi for the talk is below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;prezi-player&#34;&gt;&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34; media=&#34;screen&#34;&gt;.prezi-player { width: 550px; } .prezi-player-links { text-align: center; }&lt;/style&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;prezi_igcdltanud6-&#34; name=&#34;prezi_igcdltanud6-&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:D27CDB6E-AE6D-11cf-96B8-444553540000&#34; width=&#34;550&#34; height=&#34;400&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;movie&#34; value=&#34;http://prezi.com/bin/preziloader.swf&#34;/&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34;/&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreenInteractive&#34; value=&#34;true&#34;/&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34;/&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;bgcolor&#34; value=&#34;#ffffff&#34;/&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;prezi_id=igcdltanud6-&amp;amp;lock_to_path=0&amp;amp;color=ffffff&amp;amp;autoplay=no&amp;amp;autohide_ctrls=0&#34;/&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;preziEmbed_igcdltanud6-&#34; name=&#34;preziEmbed_igcdltanud6-&#34; src=&#34;http://prezi.com/bin/preziloader.swf&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; allowFullScreenInteractive=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; width=&#34;550&#34; height=&#34;400&#34; bgcolor=&#34;#ffffff&#34; flashvars=&#34;prezi_id=igcdltanud6-&amp;amp;lock_to_path=0&amp;amp;color=ffffff&amp;amp;autoplay=no&amp;amp;autohide_ctrls=0&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;prezi-player-links&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Maintaining Large Test Suites&#34; href=&#34;http://prezi.com/igcdltanud6-/maintaining-large-test-suites/&#34;&gt;Maintaining Large Test Suites&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://prezi.com&#34;&gt;Prezi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Banyan Tree: Football and Politics</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2011/12/05/banyan-tree-football-and-politics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2011/12/05/banyan-tree-football-and-politics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#39;post&#39;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div dir=&#34;ltr&#34; style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; trbidi=&#34;on&#34;&gt;&lt;div dir=&#34;ltr&#34; style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; trbidi=&#34;on&#34;&gt;I recently did a talk on football and the politics behind it, as part of the Banyan Tree talk series at ThoughtWorks. The slides from the talk can be found &lt;a href=&#34;http://speakerdeck.com/u/sdqali/p/football-as-a-lense&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; on Speakerdeck.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;It was great fun for me. I thought I did well. It is a topic I know my way around. The history behind the El Clasico - the Spanish civil war, Franco, the trade unions and Di Stefano was discussed. We also looked at The Old Firm. I also talked about Athletic Bilbao&#39;s use of football as a form of cultural resistance. The last parts of the talk were about multiculturalism, united Europe and football as a globalized game.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;About 20 people turned up and while most of them liked it, some had the opinion that they needed to understand more European history to fully appreciate it.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>