<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sadique Ali</title>
    <link>https://sdqali.in/categories/life-reflection-football/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sadique Ali</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <atom:link href="https://sdqali.in/categories/life-reflection-football/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Yet another week in Bangalore</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2009/08/16/yet-another-week-in-bangalore/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2009/08/16/yet-another-week-in-bangalore/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yet another week of my Bangalore life has unfolded. It was tougher, and better than the first two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned lots of new stuff, stuff that would greatly help me in my profession. I made friends with new people. But most important of all, I got some feedback on some of the things I do in life. It was kind of very scary, to be honest. But then I realized that the feedback will let me improve. I am trying hard to use the feedback in the most positive way possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally was able to enjoy some football. It was the friendly between Netherlands and England. Since England was playing away, Sony Pix did not care to telecast it. I had to listen to BBC Radio 5 Live on the web. It was kind of nostalgic. It reminded of the Saturday and Sunday evenings, when I would sit and listen to the commentary of English Premier League on BBC World Service. The only place where people watched live football was in the local sports club, and I was not allowed to go there after the evenings. So I would sit and listen to the commentary, broken every five minutes by the latest breaking news, alerts on goals in football matches elsewhere, and tennis and golf updates. I think football commentary on Radio is more descriptive and the commentators (at least the better ones) really manage to give you a mental picture of the distribution of players on the field, and the movement of players. The commentary on Radio 5 Live was good too. May be I am biased; the commentary I used to hear on World Service seems to be better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I watched the first day of English Premier Leagues. Chelsea seems to have transformed under Ancellotti; they passed the ball brilliantly. The only flipside for Chelsea fans would have been the sight of Stephen Hunt celebrating the opening goal. A collision with the former Reading winger two seasons ago left Chelsea goalkeeper Petr Cech with an injured head and the Czech still wears protective head-gear while playing. The Stamford Bridge faithful let Hunt know they did not like him by booing every instant he touched the ball. But Hunt did manage to score the new season&amp;rsquo;s first goal. Didier Drogba scored two amazing goals –the first was a breathtaking free kick. The second one looked more like an attempted cross and Drogba admitted it in the post match interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal ran riot against Everton, and they won 6-1. It was sad to see some of the Goodison Park faithful booing David Moyes&amp;rsquo;s team. Wigan beat Aston Villa to earn the first surprise result of the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friends had a get together back at Manjeri. Talked to them while the party was on. Really miss those guys! Wanted to be there.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bangalore Journal</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2009/08/08/bangalore-journal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2009/08/08/bangalore-journal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my 13th day in Bangalore. And the first week of my training at ToughtWorks has gone by. I learned lots of stuff, talked to some great people and made friends with some of them. I still have not overcome the difficulties of adapting to life in the City. May be I will soon, or I never will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had planned to post everyday about my experiences in TWU. But I did not have much time. The sessions last till 5:00 pm, and then I will be very tired to do much. I am really missing football. I had hoped to play with my friend Aneesh on last Sunday, but we were not allowed to play as one old guy who turned up decided that only regulars could play there. Sigh !!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the positive things have been that my flatmate is an amazing person. He is a leftist, and it seems we share the same view on all kind of issues. We have heated and passionate discussions/debates/arguments about all kind of things under the sun -politics, the economy, religion and technology. The fact that we have the same views on almost all issues allows us to go deep in to the subject and have very intellectually simulating discussions. The discussions continue till late in the night. He is a software engineer of tremendous experience, and I hope I will learn some things from him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the personal front, I have a big decision to make, but I am confused like anything. For the time being, I am going to play the &amp;lsquo;wait-and-watch&amp;rsquo; game. Hope things turn out well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The football season is kicking off tomorrow with the FA Community Shield. Looking forward to watching ManUtd in the new kit, with Rooney playing as the striker. The transfer market has almost died down, with Xabi Alonso&amp;rsquo;s move to Madrid being the last significant transfer. Sunderland is splashing lots of money, Darren Bent being the latest player to be on the payroll at the Stadium of Light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happened to read the incredible story of Wimbledon AFC&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/sport/football/news/5989930/AFC-Wimbledon-face-Luton-Town-in-Blue-Square-Premier-after-four-promotions.html&#34;&gt;remarkable rise&lt;/a&gt; through the Football pyramid. The fact that thy are playing Luton Town in the season opener is kind of an irony. Wimbledon AFC&amp;rsquo;s rise and Luton Town&amp;rsquo;s fall epitomizes everything the game of football represents - ecstasy and agony; pain and joy; dizzying heights and demoralizing lows. Good luck to AFC Wimledon! They did a tremendous job of rebuilding after their proud club was &amp;lsquo;moved&amp;rsquo; to Milton Keynes and re-branded as MK Dons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During one of heated debates with my friend, he made the point that the issue of Palestine had become one of &amp;lsquo;my ego&amp;rsquo;. I know I am emotional about Palestine, but is it a matter of ego for me? I am not sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next week will see me and my fellow trainees at ThoughtWorks get some hands-on coding training. I am really looking forward to it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>