<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Social Network Twitter on Sadique Ali</title>
    <link>http://sdqali.in/categories/social-network-twitter/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Social Network Twitter on Sadique Ali</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://sdqali.in/categories/social-network-twitter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Dear Content Creator, Your URL Shortener Is Pointless</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/23/dear-content-creator-your-url-shortener-is-pointless/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/23/dear-content-creator-your-url-shortener-is-pointless/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;People love URL shorteners. They are everywhere. You can use one of
&lt;a href=&#34;http://goo.gl&#34;&gt;the giants&lt;/a&gt;, or use one of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly&#34;&gt;URL Shortening As A Service&lt;/a&gt; options available
or you can run one on your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But none of that matters. Apart from adding to the redirect hell
prevalent on the web today and giving you a minor branding push, custom
URL shorteners does not add anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People started using these shortening services because of two
reasons. The first reason was the necessity to share
ugly URLs like
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://example.com/reports.php?start=2001&amp;amp;end=2010&amp;amp;item=Foo%20bar&#34;&gt;http://example.com/reports.php?start=2001&amp;amp;end=2010&amp;amp;item=Foo%20bar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and
they wanted to make it easier on the eyes of people. The second reason
was the limit on the number of characters allowed in a post by micro blogging services
like Twitter and Identi.ca.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once they became popular, people started using it everywhere, even in places like Facebook posts where there were
no limit on the number of characters in a post or comment. People also
started shortening URLs that were not particularly ugly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, the social networks
&lt;a href=&#34;http://sdqali.in/blog/2012/07/17/social-networks-and-url-shorteners/&#34;&gt;got on the game&lt;/a&gt;
and from that point, every single URL shared on those social networks had to go
through one more extra redirect. Some &lt;a href=&#34;http://royal.pingdom.com/2010/09/22/is-the-web-heading-toward-redirect-hell/&#34;&gt;had predicted&lt;/a&gt; this redirect
hell long ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the social networks were setting up their own
&lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.twitter.com/blog/introducing-twitter-web-analytics&#34;&gt;analytics service&lt;/a&gt;
around the URLs their users shared on them, content creators started
using their own custom URL shorteners. The BBC uses &lt;em&gt;bbc.in&lt;/em&gt;, the
Guardian uses &lt;em&gt;gu.com&lt;/em&gt; and Business Insider uses &lt;em&gt;read.bi&lt;/em&gt;. And it is
not just big players in the content space that uses URL
shorteners, this is prevalent among blogs too. For example,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.arabist.net/&#34;&gt;The Arabist&lt;/a&gt; uses &lt;em&gt;arb.st&lt;/em&gt;, which is in turn
hosted by &lt;em&gt;bit.ly&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But once Twitter, Facebook and Google+ came to the table and decided to
take their pound of meat from the redirect hell, all this custom URL
shortening became pointless. These social networks do not expose any data about the
shared URL. In Twitter&amp;rsquo;s case for example, all you as a website know is
that some traffic came to a particular page from a URL that looks like
&lt;em&gt;t.co/Foobar&lt;/em&gt;. If you want to make more sense of the who, when and how
aspects of your content being shared on Twitter, you have to ask
Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the fact that those shortened URLs are &lt;em&gt;short&lt;/em&gt; are does not serve
much purpose because Twitter automatically
wrap a &lt;em&gt;t.co&lt;/em&gt; URL around anything you post to it and show the a link
with the original URL as the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So content creators, please stop running your own URL shortening
services and contributing to the redirect hell. The web will be a better
place for it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>