<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>{code that works}</title>
    <link>https://sdqali.in/tags/food/index.xml?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</link>
    <description>Recent content on {code that works}</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <atom:link href="/tags/food/index.xml?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>On Halal Burgers</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/09/17/on-halal-burgers/?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/09/17/on-halal-burgers/?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;What would you like to have today?&amp;rdquo; The lady at the counter cheerfully asks. I smile back at her, take another cursory glance at the menu and with a sigh say &amp;ldquo;I will take the Teriyaki Salmon Sandwich, please!&amp;rdquo;. I take another look at all the menu and can&amp;rsquo;t help notice how sad I am. The assortment of meat preparations bundled between two pieces of bread that could have been mine is long and diverse. I suck my teeth and promise myself that I will be paying the butcher a visit in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On those days when I fail to pack lunch to work, I find myself repeating this ritual, save for the substitution of Tuna—or Red Snapper if I am lucky—for the Salmon. The restaurant may change, and sometimes wraps smile at me instead of sandwiches, but the pain at having to let go of that goodness of beef or chicken remains the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love meat. I grew up eating a lot of it, in a community that likes it so much that we have it for breakfast. (Writing that sentence just reminded me of plates of hot &lt;em&gt;porotta&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; served with beef curry. Those were the days!) I am one of those people who try to eat only Halal &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; meat. Part of it is my religious belief and part of it is just habit. I grew up in Malabar where pretty much all meat you could buy was Halal. I have in the past consumed non-Halal meat, but somewhere along the line I decided to eat only Halal meat and I have stuck to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a running joke among me and my colleagues about this hypothetical restaurant named Halal Hipster that I would open. I would like to point out that I am no Hipster—last time I checked, I still needed a Visa to enter Haight-Ashbury. The name comes from my idea for a restaurant that serves American classics prepared with Halal meat so that people like me who love meat have the opportunity to appreciate them. I have often thought about what this restaurant would be like. The place will be dishing out Burgers, Hot Dogs and Wings; all made with Halal meat. Oh and Pizza—how could I leave out pizza? Every time I visit a restaurant in San Francisco and grudgingly order the vegetarian option, I will make an entry or three in the hypothetical menu at Halal Hipsters. Take for example last Friday when we went to Calzone&amp;rsquo;s at North Beach. While all around me Cheese Steaks and Chicken invoked into Calzones were being partaken, I was eating a Margherita pizza. It was a delicious pizza but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help think how delicious their Chicken pizza would be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Halal Hipsters remains a fragment of our imagination, I do have the opportunity to indulge in my love for meat. I regularly buy stuff from &lt;em&gt;Al Salama&lt;/em&gt;, the butchers at Jones Street. I buy chicken, lamb and beef and create &lt;em&gt;Biriyanis&lt;/em&gt; and curries. I am not a great cook by any means, but as I have &lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/08/09/biriyani-and-me/&#34;&gt;said elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;, I have watched a lot of &lt;em&gt;Biriyani&lt;/em&gt; being prepared and I would like to believe that I do a pretty good job of it. But there are times when a &lt;em&gt;Biriyani&lt;/em&gt; or a curry wouldn&amp;rsquo;t satisfy one&amp;rsquo;s hunger for meaty goodness. There are only a handful of things that can do it as grandly as that American classic, the humble burger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love making—and eating—burgers. I must admit that I am not a purist when it comes to burgers—I don&amp;rsquo;t grill my burgers. And I end up adding a lot of evidently &lt;em&gt;Malabari&lt;/em&gt; things to the ground beef I buy from the butcher—cardamom, crushed pepper corns, cumin seed etc. My burgers end up being what would have happened if people in Malabar had invented the burger, which I guess is fair considering I like my &lt;em&gt;Malabari&lt;/em&gt; spices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I start by mixing (or am I supposed to say incorporating?) portions of my collection of spices in to the ground beef. I invariably end up adding chilli powder, cumin powder, coriander, crushed pepper corns, crushed cardamom, cloves and cinnamon. Ground garlic and ginger get an appearance when I am in the mood to wield the mortar and pestle. An egg and a pinch of bread crumbs act as the binder for the patty. I like slices of onion, tomatoes and finely chopped cabbage on my burger. I have not really shopped around for the right bread to make burgers. I end up using whatever is handy at the moment—whole wheat bread, rye bread or that delicious Moroccan semolina bread that the butcher sometimes stocks. As I said, I am no purist. I like a fine coating of mayonnaise on the bread, but I am not too strict about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t grill my burgers mostly because I don&amp;rsquo;t have a grill. I would like to try it, but for the time being, I do fine with a frying pan coated with the thinnest layer of oil possible. The purist may laugh at this, but I would like to believe that the end justifies the means in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sdqali.in/images/burger.png&#34; alt=&#34;Masala Burger&#34; title=&#34;Masala Burger&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Porotta&lt;/em&gt; is a layered flat bread from Kerala. Read more &lt;a href=&#34;http://riascollection.blogspot.com/2013/04/homemade-kerala-porotta-with-video.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;In Islam, &lt;em&gt;Halal&lt;/em&gt; refers to anything that is permissible. When applied to food, there are rules as to what is allowed and what is not. More information can be found at the Islamic Food and Nutrition Council of America&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ifanca.org/cms/wpages/detail/4ca47c89-ec4c-41ba-ac38-1c111b830f0c&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biriyani and me</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/08/09/biriyani-and-me/?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/08/09/biriyani-and-me/?utm_source=site&amp;utm_medium=feed</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I love Biriyani. That is an understatement. I absolutely love Biriyani.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started when I was very young. In fact, as far back as I can remember, I have loved Biriyani. A lot of people in my family - my father, a paternal uncle and his wife were cooks, and specialists in cooking for special occasions. In Malabar, that meant people employed them to cook at weddings, engagements, &lt;em&gt;Iftars&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Parasavathinu Kontu Pokals&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mudikalachils&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. They would cook up a storm of Biryani, &lt;em&gt;Neychor&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Porotta&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pathiri&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and curries of beef, chicken and mutton. Of all these things, the Biriyanis were the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My uncle was regarded the best of them. He made large quantities of rich, tender, aromatic goodness of meat, rice and spices. He does not have kids and always treated the kids of his siblings as his own. This meant that I had insider access, or a ring side view to the making of a large number of delicious Biriyanis in and around the our small town. Whenever there was a function that called for a big cauldron of Biriyani, he would set out the following evening. Sometimes I got to tag along, if the place was nearby or was at some relative&amp;rsquo;s place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The long process of making the Biriyani would start some time after mid night when a bunch of people would gather to start slicing the large quantity of onions and carrots that would go in the meat as well as for the layering. In my small town, this work is mostly done by neighbours and relatives who volunteer their time. Apart from the time, they also volunteer the tears caused by the onions. They would get a lot of gratitude at the end of the event and unlimited amount of black tea laced with the just right percentage of lemon while they worked. When the onions are done, they move on to carrots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 3:00 in the morning, another important step of the process happens when the meat for the Biriyani is brought from the butchers. The delivery typically includes the meat for the Biriyani as well as some offal. The offal would be cooked later in the morning with tapioca and served as breakfast for the volunteers. Once the meat arrives, it is cleaned, and left on tables to drain the water off. There will be people, most often youngsters fascinated by the Biriyani making process who would be entrusted with guarding the meat from adventurous crows and other birds. Their reward would come in the form of lemon teas and the tapioca for breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the meat is cleaned and drained off water, focus shifts to cooking the breakfast of tapioca and tea. Once this is done and everybody had their breakfast, the main part of the Biriyani process begins. Temporary ovens are made with laterite stones, arranged as a triangle. At around 9:00, green chilies, garlic and ginger are crushed in large quantities. Tomatoes are cut, the rice for the Biriyani is cleaned and drained and cans of &lt;em&gt;ghee&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; are opened and left to warm near the oven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then the fire and smoke begins. First to go in to the cauldron is the &lt;em&gt;ghee&lt;/em&gt; and the butter. Once these and some vegetable oil heat up, the onions go for a swim. Salt and spices are thrown in and the onions are heated to golden brown. The meat is added, stirred and fried for a few minutes. Yogurt and chopped cilantro and mint leaves go in, followed by lemon juice. The cauldron is covered with a heavy lid and the meat is left to cook in the melody of spices, lemon juice and yogurt. The focus shifts to the other component of the Biriyani - the rice. As a child, I always used to look forward to this step and not because of the rice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another cauldron is setup for the rice and &lt;em&gt;ghee&lt;/em&gt; and butter is heated in it. Onions, raisins and cashew nuts are thrown in and fried to golden brown. This is my favourite part as the fried onions, raisins and cashew nuts are kept aside. When I was a kid, I used to grab handfuls of the nicely fried, caramelized goodness. The Biriyani crew generally sneered at this practice, but my uncle who lead the team always smiled and winked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cleaned rice is added to the cauldron with some carrots, water is poured and the cauldron is covered with a heavy lid like the cauldron with the meat and is left to cook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the meat and rice are done, both cauldrons are opened and one of the iconic parts of the process - the Dum begins. Rice is taken and layered over the meat. A layer of the fried onions, raisins and cashew nut is sprinkled. Melt &lt;em&gt;ghee&lt;/em&gt; is poured over this layer accompanied with chopped cilantro and mint leaves and saffron infused rose water. This layering is repeated three or four times till the all the rice is layered. The cauldron is covered with the heavy lid and is sealed by applying a dough of &lt;em&gt;maida&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; along the edge. Hot coal from under the cauldron is poured over the lid. The dum ensures that the flavours are locked in and the melody of meat, rice, vegetables and spices are cooked to a tasty concoction, infused with the spices and saffron. For children like me at that time, the dum itself was a treat. The &lt;em&gt;maida&lt;/em&gt; would have been baked into a nice smoky cake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At around 11:30, the dum is broken to reveal the Biriyani. The work for the Biriyani gang is not done yet. Serving it to people, ensuring that everyone gets the right amount of meat and rice is an endeavour in itself. I will write about it in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opportunity I had to have a ring side view of large quantities of Biriyani being cooked up made me a Biriyani fan for life. Wherever I go, I try the local take on Biriyani. I have had a variety of Biriyani - classic Malabari, Hyderabadi, Bangalore style, Thalappaakkettu, Ambur, Mughalai, Pakistani. I liked every single one of them. But the classic Malabari Biriyani is the one I really crave, because of how much it reminds me of home, child hood and good times. Oh and it is really tasty too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been cooking Biriyani for a while now. I think I make a good specimen, but it still has room for improvement and I am working on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Iftar&lt;/em&gt;: The evening meal consumed when Muslims break their fast. Read more &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iftar&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Parasavathinu Kontu Pokal&lt;/em&gt;: A social custom prevalent among the Mappila community and the larger populace of Malabar. The word literally translates in to &amp;ldquo;Taking for delivering a baby&amp;rdquo;. In Malabar, when a woman is pregnant with her first child, she goes to her house from her husband&amp;rsquo;s house to give birth. This is done with a ceremony that involves white Sarees, prayers and of course great food. It is really difficult to find an English phrase that describes it. The interesting thing about this ceremony is that youngsters pretty much disown this ceremony when it take place in their households or relatives. Most youngsters in Malabar would not claim that they attended one of these ceremonies.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mudikalachil&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Aqiqah&lt;/em&gt;: A Muslim ritual performed for newborns that involve shaving off a newborn&amp;rsquo;s hair, sacrificing an animal and naming him/her.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Neychor&lt;/em&gt;: A Malabari Ghee Rice. Read more &lt;a href=&#34;http://shabscuisine.blogspot.com/2008/10/ghee-rice-neychor.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Porotta&lt;/em&gt;: A layered flat bread from Kerala. Read more &lt;a href=&#34;http://riascollection.blogspot.com/2013/04/homemade-kerala-porotta-with-video.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pathiri&lt;/em&gt;: Thin pan cake made out of cooked rice flour from Malabar. A mainstay in any Malabari feast spread. Read more &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pathiri&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghee&lt;/em&gt;: A type of clarified butter used in Indian cooking. Read more &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghee&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maida&lt;/em&gt;: Refined wheat flour. Read more &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maida_flour&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
