<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Code Rails Best Practices on Sadique Ali</title>
    <link>http://sdqali.in/categories/code-rails-best-practices/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Code Rails Best Practices on Sadique Ali</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://sdqali.in/categories/code-rails-best-practices/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why your project should have a Getting Started guide.</title>
      <link>http://sdqali.in/blog/2012/01/17/why-your-project-should-have-a-getting-started-guide./</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sdqali.in/blog/2012/01/17/why-your-project-should-have-a-getting-started-guide./</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#39;post&#39;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;My new team at work is writing a bunch of Rails applications. This is one of those codebases that one would call &#34;legacy&#34; without much argument. Most of these apps have their own patched, vendorized Rails versions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Getting up and running was an absolute pain. This project existed before Bundler and the list of gem dependencies are not checked in. I got the output of running &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;gem list&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; on a colleague&#39;s box, wrote a Ruby script to generate a shell script that installs all the gems. When I tried running the tests in one of those apps, I got a nice error. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It looked obvious that we were using patched Rails versions. Surprisingly, theses were not checked in to the vendor/ directory. This was proving to be a pain, and today I sat with a team member and wrote a developer guide to get started on the project. We actually had to pull patched Rails tar balls from a remote box and untar them to vendor/ directory. I was really surprised that these patches had not been checked in. We checked in all the patches. Apart from the Rails patches, there was a gem that had to be checked in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is why I think every project needs a Getting Started guide:&lt;br&gt;1. As a developer joining a new team, I want to look at the code as soon as I can. For me, this involves reading and running the tests.&lt;br&gt;2. Due to various reasons, a project may have patches and dependencies. Being very specific to the project, there is no way a new developer on the team would figure out these hidden dependencies.&lt;br&gt;3. There needs to be a single place where all the dependencies are specified.&lt;br&gt;4. While spoon-feeding someone may not be the best way to get them started, a little bit of hand-holding will not do anyone any harm. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest problems I see with things like these guides is that as the application and it&#39;s dependencies evolve, the guides are not updated to reflect these changes. The only possible time the guide will be updated is when a new developer joins the team, follows these instructions and finds the need to update the guide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>