<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sadique Ali</title>
    <link>https://sdqali.in/tags/malabar/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sadique Ali</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <atom:link href="https://sdqali.in/tags/malabar/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The SNDP - NSS political experiment of 1980s</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2014/02/09/the-sndp---nss-political-experiment-of-1980s/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2014/02/09/the-sndp---nss-political-experiment-of-1980s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, at the annual congregation of the Sree Narayana Dharma Paripalana (S.N.D.P.) Yogam, it&amp;rsquo;s leaders - Vellaapalli Nadesan and his son Thushaar announced that the Yogam is about to form their own political party that will unite Hindus of Kerala under one umbrella. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; S.N.D.P. and it&amp;rsquo;s leaders are no strangers to threatening to announce their intent to form a political party. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; They did the same in 2012, generating much talk in Kerala&amp;rsquo;s political landscape. The latest announcement is likely to suffer the same fate as these earlier announcements. To understand why the Yogam is highly unlikely to form a party of their own, one needs to look at the time when they indeed had their own political party - to the late 1970s; and the 1980 election to the Kerala legislature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Socialist Republican Party (S.R.P.) formed in 1976 with the blessings of the Yogam and the almost farcical level of communal politics that resulted in it&amp;rsquo;s aftermath - helped in large by the Nair Service Society (N.S.S.) formation of the National Democratic Party (N.D.P.) offers a great lesson in the often communal nature of class politics in Kerala and how the constant on the other side of the aisle - the Left - reacts to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1970s was a torrid time period in the political landscape in Kerala. Achutha Menon&amp;rsquo;s C.P.I.-led government ruled for 8 years from 1969 - the longest term any government has ruled Kerala. Menon&amp;rsquo;s C.P.I. ruled with the help of the Indian National Congress, the Kerala Congress and the Indian Union Muslim League (I.U.M.L.). In the slug fest between the C.P.I. and the C.P.I.(M) after the Communist party&amp;rsquo;s split down the middle, the Church stood with the C.P.I., reluctantly siding with the same people against whom they lead an annual procession from the St. George Forane Church, the burial place of the martyrs of the police shooting of 1957. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I.N.C. had started distancing from communal politics and this meant that the S.N.D.P. and the N.S.S. found themselves without political parties willing to carry their flags. And they decided to change this situation. N.S.S.&amp;rsquo;s National Democratic Party (N.D.P.) came to being in 1974, immediately followed by S.N.D.P.&amp;rsquo;s Socialist Republican Party (S.R.P.) in 1976.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noticing that these announcements came in the aftermath of the agitation led by the Ezhava, Nair and Christian communities against the State&amp;rsquo;s Education Bill aimed at ending corruption and bringing parity to the appointment of teachers in colleges. The appointment of teachers to colleges that receive State aid remains a contentions issue in Kerala politics to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1979, after Achutha Menon had stepped down and infighting in Congress led to two governments that lasted only 11 months, another temporary alliance took over governance under I.U.M.L.&amp;rsquo;s Muhammed Koya and his cabinet comprised of a member of the N.D.P. This marriage of convenience made The Hindu remark in an editorial&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The front-men have so far been drawn from forces who were communal and sectarian in their own local right and specialize in making an appeal to primordial sentiments. The new gang up, which is likely to prove shortlived is an abomination thrust up on the people of Kerala.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As predicted by The Hindu, the government lasted only 2 months and the State went to an early election in January of 1980. But by this time, something monumental had happened - the C.P.I. and the C.P.I.(M) had decided to consolidate under a grand Left Democratic Front and this meant that the Congress found themselves in the United Democratic Front with such parties as the Kerala Congress, the N.D.P. and the S.R.P. In the election, the electorate firmly voted for the Left&amp;rsquo;s coalition and both S.R.P. and the N.D.P. failed miserably. The L.D.F. won 93 of the 140 seats and 50.04 per cent of the votes, while the U.D.F. won 46 seats and 40.10 per cent of the votes. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The communal appeal of the U.D.F. was glaringly obvious and it was too much for the electorate to digest. The Ezhava voters that S.R.P. thought would form it&amp;rsquo;s base voted for the Left. It is also worth noting that a large per cent of (nearly 60%) of laborers belonging to the upper caste Nair community and the lower caste Ezhava community were members of the Left parties. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The S.R.P. and N.D.P. experiments lost their momentum and went through splits before being politically irrelevant by the end of 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;SNDP makes political plans clear. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thehindu.com/news/national/kerala/sndp-makes-political-plans-clear/article5639766.ece&#34;&gt;The Hindu, February 1, 2014&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;SNDP Yogam to launch Hindu party. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thehindu.com/todays-paper/tp-national/tp-kerala/sndp-yogam-to-launch-hindu-party/article3608451.ece&#34;&gt;The Hindu, July 6, 2012&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;During the liberation struggle against the first Communist government of Kerala, a police shooting resulted in the death of seven followers of the Roman Catholic Church in Angamaly. The seven martyrs of the Church were buried in a common tomb at the cemetery of St. George Forane Church at Angamaly. The Church&amp;rsquo;s famous slogan &lt;em&gt;Angamali kallarayil, njangade sawdharaanakkil, aa kallarayanu kattayyam, pakaram njangal choodikkum&lt;/em&gt; (If it is indeed our Brothers who sleep in the tomb at Angamaly, that tomb be witness, we will have our revenge.) originated after this incident.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;The Official Webportal of the Government of Kerala - &lt;a href=&#34;http://kerala.gov.in/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=3776:history-of-kerala-legislature&#34;&gt;History of the Kerala Legislature&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;George Mathew - &lt;em&gt;Communal Road to a Secular Kerala&lt;/em&gt;. Concept Publishing Company, Jan 1, 1989.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fireworks in the paddy fields - memories of a summer</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/05/27/fireworks-in-the-paddy-fields---memories-of-a-summer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/05/27/fireworks-in-the-paddy-fields---memories-of-a-summer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like most people, I like certain songs for their ability to bring back memories of times, places and people from the past that you don&amp;rsquo;t everyday bring out from the cellars of time, wipe away the cobwebs and dust and gaze at. &lt;em&gt;Kannu Nattu Kaathirunnittum&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; from the movie &lt;em&gt;Kathaavasheshan&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; evokes memories of childhood, the daily struggle to survive and the inability to resist the hegemony of those around you who call the shots. But, there are not many songs that does it for me quite like the Malayalam song &lt;em&gt;Alliyaambal Kadavil&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally written for the movie &lt;em&gt;Rosi&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, produced in 1965 and sang by the doyen of Malayalam film music K.J. Yesudas, the song is a meditation in love. The lyrics describe the hero&amp;rsquo;s nostalgia for a time and a person in the past and the deep love he had for her. I never particularly like this version. Growing up, it was something that my old Sony AM radio played frequently and all that talk of love did not make much sense to me. At an age when I could understand and appreciate the song, it had been appropriated by Mimicry artists, often used to add flavor to their portrayal of the stereotypical drunkard&amp;rsquo;s character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead it is an adaptation of this song for the 2009 movie &lt;em&gt;Loudspeaker&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and sung by Yesudas&amp;rsquo;s son Vijay and more importantly a flourish, an after thought to the recording of the song that makes me listen to it in loop. Instead of evoking memories of love, it evokes in me a deep nostalgia for a childhood filled with the smells, sounds and sights of paddy fields. In the adapted version of the song, at the very end, after the sweet lyrics proclaiming and ultimately eulogizing the love the older protagonist had for his companion of younger days, the two protagonists sit on the dykes of a post-harvest paddy field and watch fireworks go off in the distance. The light from the fireworks illuminate the horizon and the hearts of the characters and the viewers and the sound of the fireworks slowly spread through the paddy fields, get assimilated in to the darkness and emptiness of the night around them. And then, you are brought back to the pain and suffering of the two characters from the heady microcosm of love that is the song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I connect with that particular instance because when I was a child watching the fireworks at the end of the local &lt;em&gt;Pooram&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; was one of the simple pleasures you would afford to, mostly because it was free. During the nights of the fireworks, we went to the paddy fields of the summer, paddy fields that had been stripped of their green and brown clothes of paddy with shiny, serrated sickles and strong hands, some adorned with bangles and some adorned with the enchanted &lt;em&gt;Noolu&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; from the local mosque. While the main purpose for which they had been maintained and split in to pieces had culminated with the harvest, these fields had another purpose to serve - in the summer they lay in wait to provide the populace of the villages stages for entertainment - football in the evenings and &lt;em&gt;Poorams&lt;/em&gt; and *Ganamela*s &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the nights when the &lt;em&gt;Pooram&lt;/em&gt; had fireworks, the kids would take up seats on the dykes early enough and start the long wait in anticipation. And then it would begin, first in slow measured bursts and then in persistent frenzy.  As they go up, their many colors of light would fill the sky and your heart and then their sound would dissipate, sucked in to the darkness of the summer night, to be spread across the vastness of the paddy fields, across the stream that bisects them and in to the hills in the east where the stream originates from. But you would not get time to reflect on the sound&amp;rsquo;s journey for long, for the next burst would go up, illuminating before being sucked away, like it&amp;rsquo;s predecessor. Until the last burst, that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the last burst goes through it&amp;rsquo;s short yet majestic lifespan of 20 seconds and is fast dissipating, you feel sadness. The worry about getting something to eat that you had held back for long comes back to remind you it has not gone away, you start thinking about the bully at the school and you remember the realization you had yesterday that you may not after all be getting new sets of clothes for this year&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Eid&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the populace begins to leave the paddy fields, enthusiastically waxing lyrical about the beauty of the fireworks and complaining how it was not as majestic as the one they had witnessed in the nearby town, all in the same breath. In the midst of the cacophony, if you listen carefully enough, you can hear somebody promising to be in time for the seven-a-side football match in the neighbouring village. That match would be played on yet another paddy field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Kannu Nattu Kaathirunnittum : A song from the movie &lt;em&gt;Kathaavasheshan&lt;/em&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Kathaavasheshan :  A 2004 Malayalam film directed by T. V. Chandran. More on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kathavasheshan&#34;&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Alliyaambal Kadavil : A Malayalam movie song originally performed in 1965 and reproduced in 2009. A video can be found &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ubsCuvJripk&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Rosi : A 1965 Malayalam movie.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Loudspeaker : A 2009 movie that featured an adaptation of the song and starring Mammootty. More on &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loudspeaker_%28film%29&#34;&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Pooram : Village festival in Kerala, usually associated with temples.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Noolu : Enchanted thread worn on the wrist or around the biceps. Usually black in color.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Gaanamela : Live music performances, usually on temporary stages erected on paddy fields, playgrounds etc.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;Eid : &lt;em&gt;Eid-ul-Fitr&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Eid-al-Adha&lt;/em&gt;, the two annual Muslim celebrations.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Giving up the Samba for the Tiki-taka</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/21/giving-up-the-samba-for-the-tiki-taka/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/21/giving-up-the-samba-for-the-tiki-taka/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A shot flew over the bar. The goal keeper showed great urgency in
collecting the ball from behind the goal. Instead of kicking it forward, he pushed the ball
gently out to the centre back. As the opposition forward streamed
forward to close him down, the defender moved the ball swiftly and pushed it to
the right back who was level with the penalty box. Another push and the
central mid fielder was brought in to the play. A through ball to the
left found the player on the left wing and as the opposing
right back zoomed in to focus, he played it back to his left back. As
the left back controlled the ball, his
team repositioned themselves to start from scratch all over again. To build
from the back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have watched football in the recent past, you would recognise a
pattern here. You would see the unmistakable Barcelona blueprint. Except
that I am not describing Barcelona. Not even Spain. In fact when the
initial shot flew over the bar, there was no collective sigh of relief
from a crowd [packed till the heavens](&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://mkbarcelona.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/200311-005.jpg&amp;quot;&#34;&gt;http://mkbarcelona.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/200311-005.jpg&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;),
there was no eager ball boy to throw the ball back at the keeper and
there was no one in the dug out shouting instructions at the
players. Hell, there was not even a dug out near the touch line. The
keeper ran to the construction site where the ball had found it&amp;rsquo;s way
through and ran back all the way to get the play restarted. As he was
still was running back, the left back of my opponents walked back to his
position, his face embellished with a smile bore out of his pride
of having bent his shot around the cashew tree inside the
ground.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This place is home. As I run back to my own position of a centre back, I realize
that my heart is beginning to swell with pride and my mind with perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have come home to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kottakkal&#34;&gt;Kottakkal&lt;/a&gt; to celebrate Eid-ul-Fitr and find myself in the
middle of this engrossing contest. I grew up here and know almost all
these lads since I was a kid. The change in their playing style and more
importantly what they appreciate and look for in a player is astronomic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kottakkal is in Malappuram, one of the handful of football crazy islands
in a sea of Cricket named India. I am immensely proud of the fact that I
was born and raised here and learned to play football here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sdqali.in/images/football_flags.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;L to R - Flags of England, Brazil and Portugal&amp;quot;&#34; title=&#34;L to R - Flags of England, Brazil and Portugal&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malappuram loves football and that is a proper understatement. Makeshift
stadiums on paddy fields attract 10k+ crowd during the hot
summer. People attend weddings wearing their football team shirts. Being
able to play football well is a matter of pride and local enterprises
spend a lot of money to sponsor local tournaments and local teams. There
are people who have never flown a flag of India, but who decorates the
streets with their favourite football team&amp;rsquo;s flags. Family connections
are forgotten and friendships are forged based on what teams people
support. 12 foot cut-outs of players adorn streets when major
tournaments are around the corner. Elderly men discuss the role of a
withdrawn forward while sipping glasses of tea in tea shops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sdqali.in/images/poster_portugal.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Poster of the Portugal team&amp;quot;&#34; title=&#34;Poster of the Portugal team&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People of Malappuram madly love Brazil. While there is a significant
minority that subscribes to the other Latin American school of football
hailing from Argentina
and there does exist pockets that adore the Italians, the Germans, the
Portuguese and the English, Brazil is king. The fans of Brazil in
Malappuram are large in number, immensely proud and deafeningly
vocal. The Brazilian way of playing is revered and kids copy moves and
fashion their game around Brazilian legends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sdqali.in/images/poster_brazil.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Poster of the Brazil team&amp;quot;&#34; title=&#34;Poster of the Brazil team&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one can not escape the growing feeling that things are
changing. While it would be ridiculous to even suggest that Brazil&amp;rsquo;s fan
base in Malappuram is eroding, people are moving away from the
Brazilian style. Announcements through the tannoy for tournaments
mention tiki-taka more than they mention the samba, the wee lad on the
left who threads in delicious through balls forward would rather be
called &lt;em&gt;Iniesta&lt;/em&gt; than &lt;em&gt;Kaka&lt;/em&gt; and when you are leading the game, you
openly announce that your team is going to perform &lt;em&gt;tiki-taka&lt;/em&gt; till the
opposition catches up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This change in style has been brought up by two independent events. As
you guessed correctly, the first is the astronomical rise of the
all conquering, beautiful Barcelona way. The second, and less obvious
factor is the abandonment of the Brazilian way by none other than the
likes of Brazil&amp;rsquo;s former coach Dunga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazil of the yesteryears were pleasing on the eye and effective. This added
with the opportunities to watch the best of Brazilian talent strut it
out in Europe made the powerful style the accepted style in Malappuram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dunga&amp;rsquo;s Brazil played a brand of football that was effective, but not
necessarily pleasing on the eye. He deployed two screening midfielders
in front of the back four and sought to control the game rather than go
out and go for the neck. There are arguments, no less from the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/football/blog/2012/aug/14/olympics-exposed-flaw-brazilian-football&#34;&gt;great Jonathan Wilson&lt;/a&gt;
that Brazil had been playing with this safety first approach for a long
time now. However under Dunga, Brazil played with a level of pragmatism
that had not been seen from them before. This is symbolised by Dunga&amp;rsquo;s
use of Felipe Melo a tenacious, hard tackling, no nonsense defensive
midfielder. Melo and Brazil beat most of the teams that came across
their path and went on to win the Copa America. Brazil started grinding
out results, although it has to be said that their graft looked more
beautiful than watching some of the lesser teams like England trying to
grind out a result. Brazil were no longer exciting to watch. This would
go on till Dunga&amp;rsquo;s departure after a Dutch team who were more organised
than them and showed more desire knocked them out of the World Cup in
2010. Incidentally, Felipe Melo was sent off in that match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile in Catalonia, a master named Pepe Guardiola had assembled a
team that was mighty effective, beautiful and had the neutrals purring
with admiration. Barcelona was in vogue and the definition of beautiful
football in Malappuram changed gradually from Brazilian flair to the
measured, controlled infusion of the right amount of passing, pressing
and possession. Through balls, or &amp;ldquo;passing the ball to space&amp;rdquo; as Xavi
Hernandez &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/football/2011/feb/11/xavi-barcelona-spain-interview&#34;&gt;would have you believe&lt;/a&gt; became more valuable than step
overs. People demanded passes from goalkeepers instead of a kick
forward. Brazil fans started grudgingly accepting the fact that the
Barcelona way was beautiful. The effectiveness of the Barcelona way was
something you could not doubt, evidenced by their steam rolling of
everyone in sight. On the other hand, effectiveness of the Dunga way was
questionable after the World Cup exit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there is a quantum shift in playing style and appreciation, Brazil
is still the most popular team. Despite their love for the Barcelona
way, fans of Brazil continue to be fans of Brazil. Kids go out to the
paddy fields and laterite rockbeds and play in the Bercelona way but when they
 come back, they huddle in front of TVs and cheer for Brazil. After all, if there is one
thing worse than inglorious performances from one&amp;rsquo;s team for a football
fan, it is the shame of having to switch allegiances.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>