<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>{code that works}</title>
    <link>https://sdqali.in/categories/visualisation/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on {code that works}</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <atom:link href="https://sdqali.in/categories/visualisation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Curse of the Community Shield?</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/15/curse-of-the-community-shield/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/15/curse-of-the-community-shield/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Click on the image to see the visualisation:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/visualizations/community_shield/index.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sdqali.in/images/community_shield.png&#34; alt=&#34;Community Shield visualisation&#34; title=&#34;Community Shield Visualisation&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The football season in Europe began this weekend with countries hosting
their equivalents of the &lt;em&gt;Super Cup&lt;/em&gt;. For those confused as to what a
super cup, the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super_cup&#34;&gt;Wikipedia entry&lt;/a&gt; is a good
starting point. Super cups, at least in European national
leagues are curtain-raisers for the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FA &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FA_Community_Shield&#34;&gt;Community Shield&lt;/a&gt;
is England&amp;rsquo;s Super Cup and it pits the winners of the FA Cup against the
winners of the Premier League from the previous season. This year&amp;rsquo;s game saw Manchester City
beat Chelsea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winning the Community Shield at the beginning of the
season is considered a bad omen by a lot of football fans - an indicator that the team who win it
would not win the subsequent league season. This supposed curse is
widely discussed in
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.redcafe.net/f6/curse-community-shield-165424/&#34;&gt;fan forums&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/football/2005/jan/26/theknowledge.sport&#34;&gt;blog posts&lt;/a&gt;. And
what would be complete on the Internet without a &lt;a href=&#34;http://9gag.com/gag/5030472&#34;&gt;dinosaur thinking
aloud&lt;/a&gt; about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Community Shield win has the
potential to positively influence how a football team performs in the
season. People love winning and a victory against an opposition that
beat them to win another trophy last season should act as a confidence
booster. But does this happen? What correlation exists between winning a
Super Cup and the team&amp;rsquo;s performance in the subsequent season?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to see this and decided to create this visualisation. It shows
teams that won the Community Shield since 1908 and their position in the
table for the ensuing season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visualisation is &lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/visualizations/community_shield/index.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;winners&#34;&gt;Winners&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you observe the visualisation, there are a lot of seasons for which
there are no winners. These seasons fall in to two sets. The first set
signify the time period when the world wars meant there was no
Football. The second set is more interesting in that invitation teams
won the Community Shield and since these teams don&amp;rsquo;t compete in the
League, they are absent from the visualisation. The invitation
teams to have won the Community Shield are &lt;em&gt;English Professionals XI&lt;/em&gt;,
&lt;em&gt;English Amateurs XI&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;English World Cup XI&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also some seasons when there are two winners shown on the
visualisation. This is due to the fact that until early 1990s, a draw in
a Community Shield match meant that the teams shared the trophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;obervations&#34;&gt;Obervations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Until the 1970s, winners of the Community Shield did not do well in
the league.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From 1908 to 1970, only 6 teams went on to win the league after
winning the curtain raiser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The lowest point belongs Manchester City, who won the league in the
&lt;sup&gt;1936&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;37&lt;/sub&gt; season and the Community Shield in 1937 and then went on to
get relegated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since the 1970s winners of Community Shield had better performances in
the league.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This trend was first set by the all conquering Merseyside teams of the
1970s and 1980s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Between 1970 and 1990, 6 teams went on to win the league after winning
Community  Shield.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manchester United set a similar trend in the early 2000s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After 1970s, the winners of Community Shield have done well. Winners
finished 6th or better in all seasons since 1970, except for 5 times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like winning the Community Shield no longer incur a curse on the winners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;code&#34;&gt;Code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data was pulled from Wikipedia and cleaned up using Excel. The
visualisation was created using &lt;a href=&#34;http://d3js.org&#34;&gt;d3.js&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, the code and data used for this project is available on
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sdqali/community_shield&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;. I would greatly appreciate
feedback on this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>D3.js Workshop</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/01/d3.js-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/01/d3.js-workshop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I did a &lt;a href=&#34;http://d3js.org&#34;&gt;d3.js&lt;/a&gt; workshop at ThoughtWorks Bangalore yesterday (31st
July, 2012). I split the workshop in to two parts. The first was a basic
introduction to d3.js - SVG, Scaling, Axes etc. The second part
was an exercise to hack together a Scatterplot with some Cricket
dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 30 people attended the workshop. I spent too much time on the first part and hence we did not have enough
time to complete the second part. This was the first ever workshop I have done
and my time plan was way off. I should fix it the next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great learning experience for me. In the process of preparing
for it and conducting it, I realised that giving talks and conducting
workshops are way different. For a talk, you have the freedom to pick
examples that are easy to explain. For a workshop, the examples have to
be easy to understand and easy to put together during the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really looking forward to watching the video of the workshop and
learning from my mistakes. Unfortunately, the video camera had some
issues and ended up recording only the first 10 minutes of the 1 hour
workshop. That was not fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the 10 minutes the camera managed to capture was still
helpful. I realized that I no longer have the annoying habit of saying
&amp;ldquo;Right&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; when speaking in front of a crowd. I appear a lot more calm
and collected. I am really happy to see that slowly but surely, I am
getting better at this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the slides in &lt;a href=&#34;http://lab.hakim.se/reveal-js/&#34;&gt;reveal.js&lt;/a&gt; and the
slides are &lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/visualizations/d3-workshop/index.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The examples I used are &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sdqali/d3-dojo&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualisation - How European clubs dominate their leagues</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/07/21/visualisation---how-european-clubs-dominate-their-leagues/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/07/21/visualisation---how-european-clubs-dominate-their-leagues/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Click &lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/visualizations/league_champions/index.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the visualisation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a visualization showing how various European football clubs have
dominated their respective national leagues over various time
periods. The visualization shows data for England, France, Germany,
Italy, Netherlands and Spain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visualization is self-explanatory. You can choose a league to view
from the dropdown and then choose the sliders to select an era for which you want to look
at the data. For fine adjustment, after clicking on either slider, you
can use your keyboard to select a time period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;interesting-trends&#34;&gt;Interesting Trends&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Athletic_Bilbao&#34;&gt;Athletic Bilabo&lt;/a&gt; was very dominant in Spain during the first 20 years
of the La Liga from 1930 to 1950. However, throughout the rest of the
time period, FC Barcelona and Real Madrid CF have absolutely dominated
La Liga.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Torino_F.C.&#34;&gt;Torino&lt;/a&gt; dominated Italian
football in the 1940&amp;rsquo;s, winning 5 league titles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Except for the period between 2002 and 2008, French Ligue 1 had a lot
of variety in terms of League champions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Borussia_M%C3%B6nchengladbach&#34;&gt;Borussia Mönchengladbach&lt;/a&gt;
had a golden period in the 1970&amp;rsquo;s, winning 5 titles. They have never
won the Bundesliga in any other decade. While it would appear that
Bayern Munich totally dominates German football, they won exactly 1
title in the 40 years between 1927 and 1967.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regardless of the era, Ajax has dominated Dutch football.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the 30 year period between 1962 and 1992, the English league
invariable went to Merseyside. Liverpool won 13 and Everton won 4.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;motivation&#34;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I happened to read this
&lt;a href=&#34;http://frenchfootballweekly.com/2012/07/13/paris-saint-germain-forget-the-fans-its-all-about-winning/&#34;&gt;brilliant piece&lt;/a&gt;
from French Football Weekly on how Paris Saint-Germain&amp;rsquo;s and their
Qatari owners&amp;rsquo; desire to buy their way in to success may not be in the
best interest of the French game. Among other things, the author points
out that the last five years have shown that anybody can mount a title
challenge and this kind of diversity in contenders for the title is
unique in Europe. That was an Aha! moment. While the list of French
champions for the last five years reads &amp;ldquo;Lyon, Bordeaux, Marseille,
Lille, Montpellier&amp;rdquo;, few would have forgotten how Lyon won 7 consecutive
titles from the 2001-2002 season to 2007-2008 season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kept me thinking about during certain time periods, certain teams
tend to dominate their leagues to a great extend. Other illustrious
examples similar to Lyon include Manchester United in the 1990s,
Liverpool in the 1970s and 80s, Torino in the 1940s and Borussia
Mönchengladbach in 1970s. I decided to create the above visualization to
make sense of this trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exaplanation&#34;&gt;Exaplanation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treemapping&#34;&gt;Treemap&lt;/a&gt;. A treemap
recursively divides area to in to rectangles, and the area of any node
is proportional to it&amp;rsquo;s value. This is a treemap of depth &lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt;, where the
relationship is essentially &lt;code&gt;Club -&amp;gt; Championship Years&lt;/code&gt;. You can see a
more comprehensive example of a Treemap visualization with more depth &lt;a href=&#34;http://mbostock.github.com/d3/ex/treemap.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;code&#34;&gt;Code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the data was obtained from Wikipedia. I used
&lt;a href=&#34;http://d3js.org&#34;&gt;d3.js&lt;/a&gt; to create the visualizations, and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://jqueryui.com/demos/slider/&#34;&gt;jQueryUI&lt;/a&gt; for the sliders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have put the code and the data used for creating this visualization
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sdqali/league_champions&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; on Github. Feel free
to take the data and code and make more awesome visualizations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>XConf 6 - Data, My Heart!</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/07/16/xconf-6---data-my-heart/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/07/16/xconf-6---data-my-heart/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday,  Srijayanth Sridhar (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/craftybones&#34;&gt;@craftybones&lt;/a&gt;) and I gave a talk at XConf, ThoughtWorks India&amp;rsquo;s internal conference series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talked about visualising data, and the various visualisations that one could use to answer questions about the dataset you have. We looked at two particular datasets -  one showing the consumption of juice at the fresh juice counter in office and one about Indian and Pakistani players. We looked at various visualizations like Area charts, Box Plots, Chord Diagrams, Line Charts, Pie Charts, Donut Charts, Small Multiples, Spark Lines, Stack Charts and Treemaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk went well and we got a lot of good feedback. I thought it was an engaging session for the audience because the visualisations we showed revealed a great deal about juice consumption in the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am waiting for the video of our talk to be made available. Last time I gave a talk at XConf, I made a lot of stupid mistakes like saying &amp;ldquo;Right&amp;rdquo; a many many times. I believe I did not make the same mistake this time. But I will have to wait and see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting together this talk took a lot of effort, the biggest of them being the process of typing out large number of ledgers. We had planned to visualise about 6 months worth of data, but ended up using only 1 month&amp;rsquo;s worth. We learned a lot of things in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, Srijayanth did most of the hardwork, while I helped put together the visualisations and the presentation, which incidentally used &lt;a href=&#34;http://imakewebthings.com/deck.js/&#34;&gt;deck.js&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks, man!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can take a look at the presentation &lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/visualizations/datamyheart/presentation/index.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The code for the whole thing can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sdqali/datamyheart&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; on Github.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Indian and Pakistani cricketers - who make better debuts?</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/05/11/indian-and-pakistani-cricketers---who-make-better-debuts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/05/11/indian-and-pakistani-cricketers---who-make-better-debuts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently a friend and I had an argument about who makes better debuts among Indian and Pakistani cricket players. Now, I am not into cricket. But I do watch the odd matches here and there and am generally aware of what is going on in the game. My stand was that Pakistani players make better debuts compared to Indian players, while my friend was adamant that Indian players make better debuts. My friend is more of a cricket guy than I ever was and he asked me what is the basis of my stand. It was just a gut feel for me and I had to leave it as there was no way for me to prove that my gut feel was correct. But I did want to try, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to see if I could prove my theory. Luckily, Cricinfo has all this data, although they dont make it easy for you to get it. I wrote some scripts to pull this data and decided to visualise this using the awesome d3 library. In the end, this became more about figuring out d3 than winning the argument, but doing this was fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;batsmen&#34;&gt;Batsmen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/visualizations/debuts/batsmen.html&#34;&gt;This scatter-plot&lt;/a&gt; shows debut batting performances by all the test players to have ever played for India and Paskistan (Except those players whose batting averages were not computed). As you would have guessed, the blue bubbles are Indian players and the green ones are Pakistanis. The number of runs scored by the each batsman is on the x-axis and batting average in the debut series is on the y-axis. The size of the bubble is representative of the highest score the player scored in the debut series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned some interesting things from this graph:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sunil Gavaskar made an amazing debut. His score card for his debut series in 1971 against the might West Indies of 1970&amp;rsquo;s read like this - Matches: 4, Total Runs: 774, High Score: 220, Batting Average: 154.80, 100s: 4, 50s: 3. That is incredible and adding him to this plot would have totally skewed this plot. So technically, I did not learn about Gavaskar&amp;rsquo;s amazing debut from this plot, but from the process of plotting it. But you get the idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It looks like Indian batsmen have historically made slightly better debuts. From my not-so-keen-cricket-lover point of view, anybody who scored 150 runs at an average of 40 had a good debut series. (I chose that arbitrarily, but if you are more of a cricket fan than me, you would have better scales to spot a good debut, and you can draw your own conclusions :-)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bowlers&#34;&gt;Bowlers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/visualizations/debuts/bowlers.html&#34;&gt;This scatter-plot&lt;/a&gt; shows debut bowling performances by all the test players to have ever played for India and Paskistan (Except those players who took no wickets and hence is not of interest to us). The X-axis shows bowling average and the Y-axis shows number of wickets. The size of the bubble is representative of the number of wickets the bowler had in his best bowling performance in the debut series. Since it is indicative of only the wickets, players with best performances of &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; and &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;76&lt;/sub&gt; would be shown with bubbles of same size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting bits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pakistani bowlers make better debuts than Indian bowlers. In the crowd of players with a bowling average of less than 35 and 5 wickets of above, Pakistani players dominate. (Again, disclaimer about arbitrary scales to measure a good performance :-)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are a number of Indian bowlers like Dilip Doshi, Shivlal Yadav, Ravichandran Ashwin and Srinivas Venkataraghavn whose debut performances were clear outliers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-code&#34;&gt;The Code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the code I used to pull data from Cricinfo, the actual dataset and the Javascript code that generated these plots is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sdqali/debuts&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; on Github. Feel free to use the dataset to create better visualisations than mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;credits&#34;&gt;Credits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Srijayanth (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/craftybones&#34;&gt;@craftybones&lt;/a&gt;) helped me a lot with d3 and choosing the colors for the visualisation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>