<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>{code that works}</title>
    <link>https://sdqali.in/categories/life/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on {code that works}</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <atom:link href="https://sdqali.in/categories/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A rainy distraction</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/11/21/a-rainy-distraction/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/11/21/a-rainy-distraction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Far away, the Sutro TV tower was hardly visible in the haze of rain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;So, this is what you were talking about in the morning? I thought it was the other calculation. You are right!&amp;rdquo;. You suddenly feel happy and detect the smugness creeping to your face. I was right, I told you so, you want to say. But you don&amp;rsquo;t. &amp;ldquo;Not today! The smugness will have to die.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the thick rain drops fall on your naked torso, causing that ever so little note of pain that you have come to like and seek, you roll the muddy football under your feet and look up. Hands go up on the right flank and the young lad hugging his touch line is impatient and the wave of his hands are frantic. You turn your head and survey the left flank. Nothing going there, you quickly realise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;We should focus on the lazy load. That will give us more boost.&amp;rdquo; You node and look away, to the beads of rain crawling down the window pane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lofted ball is a tough one when playing in mud and rain, and you know you have to make that extra push. So you dig deeper, connect your instep with the ball and push a little bit harder. The ball flies, over the old man caught in the middle; and the expression on the face of the young lad on the right flank changes from frantic impatience to anticipation. And then you feel the warm body behind you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;So do you think we should go ahead with the first approach?&amp;rdquo;. You turn in your chair, nod again and notice that the rain is in full fury over the Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the ball flies away and you begin to turn and run, you feel the cold hard foot of the lad behind you on your right calf muscle. You feel the pain and turn to face him. &amp;ldquo;Oh, that lad! He always has his knives out when he plays against me.&amp;rdquo;, you realise. It is okay. He smiles, and you smile back and run away to the centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hmmm&amp;hellip; this does not look like the right approach. What do you think?&amp;rdquo; You try harder to snap back from that Monsoon day in the paddy field and offer your opinion. It is cold and you notice that water on the roof is starting to flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Not today. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to have an argument today&amp;rdquo;. He tackled, he tackled late, and he probably did it deliberately. It is okay - because it is June, it is raining like mad and you are in a muddy paddy field, playing football. Over on the right flank, the cousin lunges in with a sliding tackle and completely misses the player and the ball. He goes sliding in the mud, and it is a pretty sight. The sister-in-law would not be happy though and when we get back she will glare at him - glares of disapproval. Why do grown up men do this? And then as you try to avoid eye contact with her, her glare would have asked you &amp;ldquo;Is this what you fly half way across the world for?&amp;rdquo;. You will smile that nervous smile and nod uneasily. &amp;ldquo;Not today sister&amp;hellip; I am not going to argue with you!&amp;rdquo;. For it is June and it is raining&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I think we are stuck. What do you think we should do?&amp;rdquo;. You painfully realise that the present wants you back. Damn!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hey, let&amp;rsquo;s step back and look at it again. We will sort it out!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Halal Burgers</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/09/17/on-halal-burgers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/09/17/on-halal-burgers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;What would you like to have today?&amp;rdquo; The lady at the counter cheerfully asks. I smile back at her, take another cursory glance at the menu and with a sigh say &amp;ldquo;I will take the Teriyaki Salmon Sandwich, please!&amp;rdquo;. I take another look at all the menu and can&amp;rsquo;t help notice how sad I am. The assortment of meat preparations bundled between two pieces of bread that could have been mine is long and diverse. I suck my teeth and promise myself that I will be paying the butcher a visit in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On those days when I fail to pack lunch to work, I find myself repeating this ritual, save for the substitution of Tuna—or Red Snapper if I am lucky—for the Salmon. The restaurant may change, and sometimes wraps smile at me instead of sandwiches, but the pain at having to let go of that goodness of beef or chicken remains the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love meat. I grew up eating a lot of it, in a community that likes it so much that we have it for breakfast. (Writing that sentence just reminded me of plates of hot &lt;em&gt;porotta&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; served with beef curry. Those were the days!) I am one of those people who try to eat only Halal &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; meat. Part of it is my religious belief and part of it is just habit. I grew up in Malabar where pretty much all meat you could buy was Halal. I have in the past consumed non-Halal meat, but somewhere along the line I decided to eat only Halal meat and I have stuck to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a running joke among me and my colleagues about this hypothetical restaurant named Halal Hipster that I would open. I would like to point out that I am no Hipster—last time I checked, I still needed a Visa to enter Haight-Ashbury. The name comes from my idea for a restaurant that serves American classics prepared with Halal meat so that people like me who love meat have the opportunity to appreciate them. I have often thought about what this restaurant would be like. The place will be dishing out Burgers, Hot Dogs and Wings; all made with Halal meat. Oh and Pizza—how could I leave out pizza? Every time I visit a restaurant in San Francisco and grudgingly order the vegetarian option, I will make an entry or three in the hypothetical menu at Halal Hipsters. Take for example last Friday when we went to Calzone&amp;rsquo;s at North Beach. While all around me Cheese Steaks and Chicken invoked into Calzones were being partaken, I was eating a Margherita pizza. It was a delicious pizza but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help think how delicious their Chicken pizza would be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Halal Hipsters remains a fragment of our imagination, I do have the opportunity to indulge in my love for meat. I regularly buy stuff from &lt;em&gt;Al Salama&lt;/em&gt;, the butchers at Jones Street. I buy chicken, lamb and beef and create &lt;em&gt;Biriyanis&lt;/em&gt; and curries. I am not a great cook by any means, but as I have &lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/08/09/biriyani-and-me/&#34;&gt;said elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;, I have watched a lot of &lt;em&gt;Biriyani&lt;/em&gt; being prepared and I would like to believe that I do a pretty good job of it. But there are times when a &lt;em&gt;Biriyani&lt;/em&gt; or a curry wouldn&amp;rsquo;t satisfy one&amp;rsquo;s hunger for meaty goodness. There are only a handful of things that can do it as grandly as that American classic, the humble burger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love making—and eating—burgers. I must admit that I am not a purist when it comes to burgers—I don&amp;rsquo;t grill my burgers. And I end up adding a lot of evidently &lt;em&gt;Malabari&lt;/em&gt; things to the ground beef I buy from the butcher—cardamom, crushed pepper corns, cumin seed etc. My burgers end up being what would have happened if people in Malabar had invented the burger, which I guess is fair considering I like my &lt;em&gt;Malabari&lt;/em&gt; spices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I start by mixing (or am I supposed to say incorporating?) portions of my collection of spices in to the ground beef. I invariably end up adding chilli powder, cumin powder, coriander, crushed pepper corns, crushed cardamom, cloves and cinnamon. Ground garlic and ginger get an appearance when I am in the mood to wield the mortar and pestle. An egg and a pinch of bread crumbs act as the binder for the patty. I like slices of onion, tomatoes and finely chopped cabbage on my burger. I have not really shopped around for the right bread to make burgers. I end up using whatever is handy at the moment—whole wheat bread, rye bread or that delicious Moroccan semolina bread that the butcher sometimes stocks. As I said, I am no purist. I like a fine coating of mayonnaise on the bread, but I am not too strict about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t grill my burgers mostly because I don&amp;rsquo;t have a grill. I would like to try it, but for the time being, I do fine with a frying pan coated with the thinnest layer of oil possible. The purist may laugh at this, but I would like to believe that the end justifies the means in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sdqali.in/images/burger.png&#34; alt=&#34;Masala Burger&#34; title=&#34;Masala Burger&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Porotta&lt;/em&gt; is a layered flat bread from Kerala. Read more &lt;a href=&#34;http://riascollection.blogspot.com/2013/04/homemade-kerala-porotta-with-video.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;In Islam, &lt;em&gt;Halal&lt;/em&gt; refers to anything that is permissible. When applied to food, there are rules as to what is allowed and what is not. More information can be found at the Islamic Food and Nutrition Council of America&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ifanca.org/cms/wpages/detail/4ca47c89-ec4c-41ba-ac38-1c111b830f0c&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biriyani and me</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/08/09/biriyani-and-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/08/09/biriyani-and-me/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I love Biriyani. That is an understatement. I absolutely love Biriyani.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started when I was very young. In fact, as far back as I can remember, I have loved Biriyani. A lot of people in my family - my father, a paternal uncle and his wife were cooks, and specialists in cooking for special occasions. In Malabar, that meant people employed them to cook at weddings, engagements, &lt;em&gt;Iftars&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Parasavathinu Kontu Pokals&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mudikalachils&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. They would cook up a storm of Biryani, &lt;em&gt;Neychor&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Porotta&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pathiri&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and curries of beef, chicken and mutton. Of all these things, the Biriyanis were the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My uncle was regarded the best of them. He made large quantities of rich, tender, aromatic goodness of meat, rice and spices. He does not have kids and always treated the kids of his siblings as his own. This meant that I had insider access, or a ring side view to the making of a large number of delicious Biriyanis in and around the our small town. Whenever there was a function that called for a big cauldron of Biriyani, he would set out the following evening. Sometimes I got to tag along, if the place was nearby or was at some relative&amp;rsquo;s place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The long process of making the Biriyani would start some time after mid night when a bunch of people would gather to start slicing the large quantity of onions and carrots that would go in the meat as well as for the layering. In my small town, this work is mostly done by neighbours and relatives who volunteer their time. Apart from the time, they also volunteer the tears caused by the onions. They would get a lot of gratitude at the end of the event and unlimited amount of black tea laced with the just right percentage of lemon while they worked. When the onions are done, they move on to carrots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 3:00 in the morning, another important step of the process happens when the meat for the Biriyani is brought from the butchers. The delivery typically includes the meat for the Biriyani as well as some offal. The offal would be cooked later in the morning with tapioca and served as breakfast for the volunteers. Once the meat arrives, it is cleaned, and left on tables to drain the water off. There will be people, most often youngsters fascinated by the Biriyani making process who would be entrusted with guarding the meat from adventurous crows and other birds. Their reward would come in the form of lemon teas and the tapioca for breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the meat is cleaned and drained off water, focus shifts to cooking the breakfast of tapioca and tea. Once this is done and everybody had their breakfast, the main part of the Biriyani process begins. Temporary ovens are made with laterite stones, arranged as a triangle. At around 9:00, green chilies, garlic and ginger are crushed in large quantities. Tomatoes are cut, the rice for the Biriyani is cleaned and drained and cans of &lt;em&gt;ghee&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; are opened and left to warm near the oven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then the fire and smoke begins. First to go in to the cauldron is the &lt;em&gt;ghee&lt;/em&gt; and the butter. Once these and some vegetable oil heat up, the onions go for a swim. Salt and spices are thrown in and the onions are heated to golden brown. The meat is added, stirred and fried for a few minutes. Yogurt and chopped cilantro and mint leaves go in, followed by lemon juice. The cauldron is covered with a heavy lid and the meat is left to cook in the melody of spices, lemon juice and yogurt. The focus shifts to the other component of the Biriyani - the rice. As a child, I always used to look forward to this step and not because of the rice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another cauldron is setup for the rice and &lt;em&gt;ghee&lt;/em&gt; and butter is heated in it. Onions, raisins and cashew nuts are thrown in and fried to golden brown. This is my favourite part as the fried onions, raisins and cashew nuts are kept aside. When I was a kid, I used to grab handfuls of the nicely fried, caramelized goodness. The Biriyani crew generally sneered at this practice, but my uncle who lead the team always smiled and winked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cleaned rice is added to the cauldron with some carrots, water is poured and the cauldron is covered with a heavy lid like the cauldron with the meat and is left to cook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the meat and rice are done, both cauldrons are opened and one of the iconic parts of the process - the Dum begins. Rice is taken and layered over the meat. A layer of the fried onions, raisins and cashew nut is sprinkled. Melt &lt;em&gt;ghee&lt;/em&gt; is poured over this layer accompanied with chopped cilantro and mint leaves and saffron infused rose water. This layering is repeated three or four times till the all the rice is layered. The cauldron is covered with the heavy lid and is sealed by applying a dough of &lt;em&gt;maida&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; along the edge. Hot coal from under the cauldron is poured over the lid. The dum ensures that the flavours are locked in and the melody of meat, rice, vegetables and spices are cooked to a tasty concoction, infused with the spices and saffron. For children like me at that time, the dum itself was a treat. The &lt;em&gt;maida&lt;/em&gt; would have been baked into a nice smoky cake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At around 11:30, the dum is broken to reveal the Biriyani. The work for the Biriyani gang is not done yet. Serving it to people, ensuring that everyone gets the right amount of meat and rice is an endeavour in itself. I will write about it in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opportunity I had to have a ring side view of large quantities of Biriyani being cooked up made me a Biriyani fan for life. Wherever I go, I try the local take on Biriyani. I have had a variety of Biriyani - classic Malabari, Hyderabadi, Bangalore style, Thalappaakkettu, Ambur, Mughalai, Pakistani. I liked every single one of them. But the classic Malabari Biriyani is the one I really crave, because of how much it reminds me of home, child hood and good times. Oh and it is really tasty too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been cooking Biriyani for a while now. I think I make a good specimen, but it still has room for improvement and I am working on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Iftar&lt;/em&gt;: The evening meal consumed when Muslims break their fast. Read more &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iftar&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Parasavathinu Kontu Pokal&lt;/em&gt;: A social custom prevalent among the Mappila community and the larger populace of Malabar. The word literally translates in to &amp;ldquo;Taking for delivering a baby&amp;rdquo;. In Malabar, when a woman is pregnant with her first child, she goes to her house from her husband&amp;rsquo;s house to give birth. This is done with a ceremony that involves white Sarees, prayers and of course great food. It is really difficult to find an English phrase that describes it. The interesting thing about this ceremony is that youngsters pretty much disown this ceremony when it take place in their households or relatives. Most youngsters in Malabar would not claim that they attended one of these ceremonies.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mudikalachil&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Aqiqah&lt;/em&gt;: A Muslim ritual performed for newborns that involve shaving off a newborn&amp;rsquo;s hair, sacrificing an animal and naming him/her.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Neychor&lt;/em&gt;: A Malabari Ghee Rice. Read more &lt;a href=&#34;http://shabscuisine.blogspot.com/2008/10/ghee-rice-neychor.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Porotta&lt;/em&gt;: A layered flat bread from Kerala. Read more &lt;a href=&#34;http://riascollection.blogspot.com/2013/04/homemade-kerala-porotta-with-video.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pathiri&lt;/em&gt;: Thin pan cake made out of cooked rice flour from Malabar. A mainstay in any Malabari feast spread. Read more &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pathiri&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghee&lt;/em&gt;: A type of clarified butter used in Indian cooking. Read more &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghee&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maida&lt;/em&gt;: Refined wheat flour. Read more &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maida_flour&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fireworks in the paddy fields - memories of a summer</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/05/27/fireworks-in-the-paddy-fields---memories-of-a-summer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/05/27/fireworks-in-the-paddy-fields---memories-of-a-summer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like most people, I like certain songs for their ability to bring back memories of times, places and people from the past that you don&amp;rsquo;t everyday bring out from the cellars of time, wipe away the cobwebs and dust and gaze at. &lt;em&gt;Kannu Nattu Kaathirunnittum&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; from the movie &lt;em&gt;Kathaavasheshan&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; evokes memories of childhood, the daily struggle to survive and the inability to resist the hegemony of those around you who call the shots. But, there are not many songs that does it for me quite like the Malayalam song &lt;em&gt;Alliyaambal Kadavil&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally written for the movie &lt;em&gt;Rosi&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, produced in 1965 and sang by the doyen of Malayalam film music K.J. Yesudas, the song is a meditation in love. The lyrics describe the hero&amp;rsquo;s nostalgia for a time and a person in the past and the deep love he had for her. I never particularly like this version. Growing up, it was something that my old Sony AM radio played frequently and all that talk of love did not make much sense to me. At an age when I could understand and appreciate the song, it had been appropriated by Mimicry artists, often used to add flavor to their portrayal of the stereotypical drunkard&amp;rsquo;s character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead it is an adaptation of this song for the 2009 movie &lt;em&gt;Loudspeaker&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and sung by Yesudas&amp;rsquo;s son Vijay and more importantly a flourish, an after thought to the recording of the song that makes me listen to it in loop. Instead of evoking memories of love, it evokes in me a deep nostalgia for a childhood filled with the smells, sounds and sights of paddy fields. In the adapted version of the song, at the very end, after the sweet lyrics proclaiming and ultimately eulogizing the love the older protagonist had for his companion of younger days, the two protagonists sit on the dykes of a post-harvest paddy field and watch fireworks go off in the distance. The light from the fireworks illuminate the horizon and the hearts of the characters and the viewers and the sound of the fireworks slowly spread through the paddy fields, get assimilated in to the darkness and emptiness of the night around them. And then, you are brought back to the pain and suffering of the two characters from the heady microcosm of love that is the song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I connect with that particular instance because when I was a child watching the fireworks at the end of the local &lt;em&gt;Pooram&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; was one of the simple pleasures you would afford to, mostly because it was free. During the nights of the fireworks, we went to the paddy fields of the summer, paddy fields that had been stripped of their green and brown clothes of paddy with shiny, serrated sickles and strong hands, some adorned with bangles and some adorned with the enchanted &lt;em&gt;Noolu&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; from the local mosque. While the main purpose for which they had been maintained and split in to pieces had culminated with the harvest, these fields had another purpose to serve - in the summer they lay in wait to provide the populace of the villages stages for entertainment - football in the evenings and &lt;em&gt;Poorams&lt;/em&gt; and *Ganamela*s &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the nights when the &lt;em&gt;Pooram&lt;/em&gt; had fireworks, the kids would take up seats on the dykes early enough and start the long wait in anticipation. And then it would begin, first in slow measured bursts and then in persistent frenzy.  As they go up, their many colors of light would fill the sky and your heart and then their sound would dissipate, sucked in to the darkness of the summer night, to be spread across the vastness of the paddy fields, across the stream that bisects them and in to the hills in the east where the stream originates from. But you would not get time to reflect on the sound&amp;rsquo;s journey for long, for the next burst would go up, illuminating before being sucked away, like it&amp;rsquo;s predecessor. Until the last burst, that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the last burst goes through it&amp;rsquo;s short yet majestic lifespan of 20 seconds and is fast dissipating, you feel sadness. The worry about getting something to eat that you had held back for long comes back to remind you it has not gone away, you start thinking about the bully at the school and you remember the realization you had yesterday that you may not after all be getting new sets of clothes for this year&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Eid&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the populace begins to leave the paddy fields, enthusiastically waxing lyrical about the beauty of the fireworks and complaining how it was not as majestic as the one they had witnessed in the nearby town, all in the same breath. In the midst of the cacophony, if you listen carefully enough, you can hear somebody promising to be in time for the seven-a-side football match in the neighbouring village. That match would be played on yet another paddy field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Kannu Nattu Kaathirunnittum : A song from the movie &lt;em&gt;Kathaavasheshan&lt;/em&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Kathaavasheshan :  A 2004 Malayalam film directed by T. V. Chandran. More on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kathavasheshan&#34;&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Alliyaambal Kadavil : A Malayalam movie song originally performed in 1965 and reproduced in 2009. A video can be found &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ubsCuvJripk&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Rosi : A 1965 Malayalam movie.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Loudspeaker : A 2009 movie that featured an adaptation of the song and starring Mammootty. More on &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loudspeaker_%28film%29&#34;&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Pooram : Village festival in Kerala, usually associated with temples.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Noolu : Enchanted thread worn on the wrist or around the biceps. Usually black in color.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Gaanamela : Live music performances, usually on temporary stages erected on paddy fields, playgrounds etc.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;Eid : &lt;em&gt;Eid-ul-Fitr&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Eid-al-Adha&lt;/em&gt;, the two annual Muslim celebrations.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First week in San Francisco</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/01/21/first-week-in-san-francisco/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/01/21/first-week-in-san-francisco/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I moved to San Francisco last week and is just getting acquainted with
the city. This blog
post is a summary of my first impressions of SF to share with a lot of friends whom I have not been able to keep in touch and who have been wondering what I am up to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;it-is-cold-here&#34;&gt;It is cold here&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I landed in SF without enough winter wear. I had a windbreaker that I
used in Bangalore and provided more than adequate warmth back in
Bangalore. Soon, I realised that it won&amp;rsquo;t be enough. Temperatures were
under 10 C. I had to get a proper jacket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-views-are-stunning&#34;&gt;The views are stunning&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty much wherever you are in the city, you have nice views - the bay,
the Golden Gate bridge or the downtown. As a bonus, the place where
ThoughtWorks put me up has nice views of the bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;vehicles-actually-stop-for-pedestrians&#34;&gt;Vehicles actually stop for pedestrians&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking to work on Bangalore&amp;rsquo;s roads was a tough experience because
nobody waited for the pedestrians to cross and the red signals were
eaten away by bikers eager to squeeze in. Walking on SF&amp;rsquo;s streets is a
pleasant experience. Sidewalks are wide and clean and when you have to
cross the road, vehicles actually stop and let you pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;diversity&#34;&gt;Diversity&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SF is a place with huge racial, religious and cultural diversity. There
is something for everyone here. From the busy people in the Financial
District to the guy selling weed at the Fisherman&amp;rsquo;s wharf to the people
roaming the market street, SF has a lot of variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-golden-gate-bridge-is-magnificent&#34;&gt;The Golden Gate bridge is magnificent&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks stunning in the pictures. It looks even better when you see it
up close.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Books read in 2012</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/01/02/books-read-in-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/01/02/books-read-in-2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34; media=&#34;screen&#34;&gt;
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;gr_grid_widget_1357149317&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3106983-persepolis&#34; title=&#34;Persepolis: The Story of a Childhood &amp; The Story of a Return&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Persepolis: The Story of a Childhood &amp; The Story of a Return&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://d.gr-assets.com/books/1348087872m/3106983.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1301.Moneyball&#34; title=&#34;Moneyball: The Art of Winning an Unfair Game&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Moneyball: The Art of Winning an Unfair Game&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://d.gr-assets.com/books/1348252265m/1301.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/7008234-miramar&#34; title=&#34;Miramar&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Miramar&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://d.gr-assets.com/books/1255925775m/7008234.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/12516807-pathummayude-aadu&#34; title=&#34;Pathummayude Aadu | പാത്തുമ്മയുടെ ആട്&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Pathummayude Aadu | പാത്തുമ്മയുടെ ആട്&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://d.gr-assets.com/books/1315809717m/12516807.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/10413697-balyakalasakhi&#34; title=&#34;Balyakalasakhi&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Balyakalasakhi&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://d.gr-assets.com/books/1297407463m/10413697.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13170523-premalekhanam&#34; title=&#34;Premalekhanam&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Premalekhanam&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://d.gr-assets.com/books/1323256439m/13170523.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13645110-ntuppuppaakkoraanaendaarnnu&#34; title=&#34;Ntuppuppaakkoraanaendaarnnu | ന്റുപ്പൂപ്പാക്കൊരാനേണ്ടാർന്ന്&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Ntuppuppaakkoraanaendaarnnu | ന്റുപ്പൂപ്പാക്കൊരാനേണ്ടാർന്ന്&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://d.gr-assets.com/books/1336751497m/13645110.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/149667.HMS_Ulysses&#34; title=&#34;HMS Ulysses&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;HMS Ulysses&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://d.gr-assets.com/books/1348300733m/149667.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2517.My_Name_is_Red&#34; title=&#34;My Name is Red&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;My Name is Red&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://d.gr-assets.com/books/1356116413m/2517.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/11084145-steve-jobs&#34; title=&#34;Steve Jobs&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Steve Jobs&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://d.gr-assets.com/books/1327861368m/11084145.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/16668338-our-lady-of-alice-bhatti&#34; title=&#34;Our Lady of Alice Bhatti&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Our Lady of Alice Bhatti&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://d.gr-assets.com/books/1355464983m/16668338.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/548914.The_Little_Schemer&#34; title=&#34;The Little Schemer&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The Little Schemer&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://d.gr-assets.com/books/1347456079m/548914.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1713426.Predictably_Irrational&#34; title=&#34;Predictably Irrational: The Hidden Forces That Shape Our Decisions&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Predictably Irrational: The Hidden Forces That Shape Our Decisions&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://d.gr-assets.com/books/1255573980m/1713426.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;br style=&#34;clear: both&#34;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/user/show/16009093-sadique-ali&#34; class=&#34;gr_grid_branding&#34; style=&#34;font-size: .9em; color: #382110; text-decoration: none; float: right; clear: both&#34;&gt;Sadique Ali&#39;s favorite books »&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;noscript&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Share &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com&#34;&gt;book reviews&lt;/a&gt; and ratings with Sadique, and even join a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/group/&#34;&gt;book club&lt;/a&gt; on Goodreads.&lt;/noscript&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Giving up the Samba for the Tiki-taka</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/21/giving-up-the-samba-for-the-tiki-taka/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/21/giving-up-the-samba-for-the-tiki-taka/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A shot flew over the bar. The goal keeper showed great urgency in
collecting the ball from behind the goal. Instead of kicking it forward, he pushed the ball
gently out to the centre back. As the opposition forward streamed
forward to close him down, the defender moved the ball swiftly and pushed it to
the right back who was level with the penalty box. Another push and the
central mid fielder was brought in to the play. A through ball to the
left found the player on the left wing and as the opposing
right back zoomed in to focus, he played it back to his left back. As
the left back controlled the ball, his
team repositioned themselves to start from scratch all over again. To build
from the back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have watched football in the recent past, you would recognise a
pattern here. You would see the unmistakable Barcelona blueprint. Except
that I am not describing Barcelona. Not even Spain. In fact when the
initial shot flew over the bar, there was no collective sigh of relief
from a crowd [packed till the heavens](&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://mkbarcelona.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/200311-005.jpg&amp;quot;&#34;&gt;http://mkbarcelona.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/200311-005.jpg&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;),
there was no eager ball boy to throw the ball back at the keeper and
there was no one in the dug out shouting instructions at the
players. Hell, there was not even a dug out near the touch line. The
keeper ran to the construction site where the ball had found it&amp;rsquo;s way
through and ran back all the way to get the play restarted. As he was
still was running back, the left back of my opponents walked back to his
position, his face embellished with a smile bore out of his pride
of having bent his shot around the cashew tree inside the
ground.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This place is home. As I run back to my own position of a centre back, I realize
that my heart is beginning to swell with pride and my mind with perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have come home to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kottakkal&#34;&gt;Kottakkal&lt;/a&gt; to celebrate Eid-ul-Fitr and find myself in the
middle of this engrossing contest. I grew up here and know almost all
these lads since I was a kid. The change in their playing style and more
importantly what they appreciate and look for in a player is astronomic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kottakkal is in Malappuram, one of the handful of football crazy islands
in a sea of Cricket named India. I am immensely proud of the fact that I
was born and raised here and learned to play football here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sdqali.in/images/football_flags.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;L to R - Flags of England, Brazil and Portugal&amp;quot;&#34; title=&#34;L to R - Flags of England, Brazil and Portugal&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malappuram loves football and that is a proper understatement. Makeshift
stadiums on paddy fields attract 10k+ crowd during the hot
summer. People attend weddings wearing their football team shirts. Being
able to play football well is a matter of pride and local enterprises
spend a lot of money to sponsor local tournaments and local teams. There
are people who have never flown a flag of India, but who decorates the
streets with their favourite football team&amp;rsquo;s flags. Family connections
are forgotten and friendships are forged based on what teams people
support. 12 foot cut-outs of players adorn streets when major
tournaments are around the corner. Elderly men discuss the role of a
withdrawn forward while sipping glasses of tea in tea shops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sdqali.in/images/poster_portugal.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Poster of the Portugal team&amp;quot;&#34; title=&#34;Poster of the Portugal team&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People of Malappuram madly love Brazil. While there is a significant
minority that subscribes to the other Latin American school of football
hailing from Argentina
and there does exist pockets that adore the Italians, the Germans, the
Portuguese and the English, Brazil is king. The fans of Brazil in
Malappuram are large in number, immensely proud and deafeningly
vocal. The Brazilian way of playing is revered and kids copy moves and
fashion their game around Brazilian legends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sdqali.in/images/poster_brazil.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Poster of the Brazil team&amp;quot;&#34; title=&#34;Poster of the Brazil team&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one can not escape the growing feeling that things are
changing. While it would be ridiculous to even suggest that Brazil&amp;rsquo;s fan
base in Malappuram is eroding, people are moving away from the
Brazilian style. Announcements through the tannoy for tournaments
mention tiki-taka more than they mention the samba, the wee lad on the
left who threads in delicious through balls forward would rather be
called &lt;em&gt;Iniesta&lt;/em&gt; than &lt;em&gt;Kaka&lt;/em&gt; and when you are leading the game, you
openly announce that your team is going to perform &lt;em&gt;tiki-taka&lt;/em&gt; till the
opposition catches up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This change in style has been brought up by two independent events. As
you guessed correctly, the first is the astronomical rise of the
all conquering, beautiful Barcelona way. The second, and less obvious
factor is the abandonment of the Brazilian way by none other than the
likes of Brazil&amp;rsquo;s former coach Dunga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazil of the yesteryears were pleasing on the eye and effective. This added
with the opportunities to watch the best of Brazilian talent strut it
out in Europe made the powerful style the accepted style in Malappuram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dunga&amp;rsquo;s Brazil played a brand of football that was effective, but not
necessarily pleasing on the eye. He deployed two screening midfielders
in front of the back four and sought to control the game rather than go
out and go for the neck. There are arguments, no less from the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/football/blog/2012/aug/14/olympics-exposed-flaw-brazilian-football&#34;&gt;great Jonathan Wilson&lt;/a&gt;
that Brazil had been playing with this safety first approach for a long
time now. However under Dunga, Brazil played with a level of pragmatism
that had not been seen from them before. This is symbolised by Dunga&amp;rsquo;s
use of Felipe Melo a tenacious, hard tackling, no nonsense defensive
midfielder. Melo and Brazil beat most of the teams that came across
their path and went on to win the Copa America. Brazil started grinding
out results, although it has to be said that their graft looked more
beautiful than watching some of the lesser teams like England trying to
grind out a result. Brazil were no longer exciting to watch. This would
go on till Dunga&amp;rsquo;s departure after a Dutch team who were more organised
than them and showed more desire knocked them out of the World Cup in
2010. Incidentally, Felipe Melo was sent off in that match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile in Catalonia, a master named Pepe Guardiola had assembled a
team that was mighty effective, beautiful and had the neutrals purring
with admiration. Barcelona was in vogue and the definition of beautiful
football in Malappuram changed gradually from Brazilian flair to the
measured, controlled infusion of the right amount of passing, pressing
and possession. Through balls, or &amp;ldquo;passing the ball to space&amp;rdquo; as Xavi
Hernandez &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/football/2011/feb/11/xavi-barcelona-spain-interview&#34;&gt;would have you believe&lt;/a&gt; became more valuable than step
overs. People demanded passes from goalkeepers instead of a kick
forward. Brazil fans started grudgingly accepting the fact that the
Barcelona way was beautiful. The effectiveness of the Barcelona way was
something you could not doubt, evidenced by their steam rolling of
everyone in sight. On the other hand, effectiveness of the Dunga way was
questionable after the World Cup exit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there is a quantum shift in playing style and appreciation, Brazil
is still the most popular team. Despite their love for the Barcelona
way, fans of Brazil continue to be fans of Brazil. Kids go out to the
paddy fields and laterite rockbeds and play in the Bercelona way but when they
 come back, they huddle in front of TVs and cheer for Brazil. After all, if there is one
thing worse than inglorious performances from one&amp;rsquo;s team for a football
fan, it is the shame of having to switch allegiances.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Crash and then You Learn</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/05/29/you-crash-and-then-you-learn/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/05/29/you-crash-and-then-you-learn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I picked up my bicycle, climbed on it and spotted the blood on my elbows and the bunch of curious onlookers in front of the pan shop nearby, I did not feel fear or embarrassment. I had an immeasurable amount of happiness welling inside me. I had finally done what I should have about 20 years ago - I had finally managed to crash my bicycle and leave with plenty of scars to show for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am 25, and until two weeks ago I could not ride a bicycle. Two weeks ago, during a Saturday afternoon, I got on a bicycle and rode it around a football field. Well, what is so special about that, you might ask. It was pretty special to me because it was the first time I had rode a bicycle, where my definition of &amp;lsquo;ride&amp;rsquo; is &amp;lsquo;ride with a level of confidence that removes the fear on falling down!&amp;rsquo;. When it finally happened, it was like what Kevin Garnett &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3_gL_H9zAY8&#34;&gt;described&lt;/a&gt; when he finally won an NBA with the Celtics after years of disappointment with the Minnesota Timberwolves - &amp;ldquo;I Just Knocked the Bully Out&amp;rdquo;. Yes, I was emotional. No, I did not cry. But it had been a long time coming, and the journey was painful. Here is the story of me learning to cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-beginning&#34;&gt;The beginning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a kid, I did not learn to ride a bicycle. Looking back, I don&amp;rsquo;t know why. All my friends from childhood, who lived in the same neighbourhood as me learned to ride when they were small kids. I think I had developed an aversion to it even when I was a kid. It must have had something to do with me liking swimming in the streams and playing more than riding a bicycle. And yeah, there was the minor detail about neither me or any of my close friends actually owning a cycle.
When I was growing up, I spent most of my time in a residential school. In there, bicycles were a part of your fantasies about the outside world. People talked about it, fantasized about it, but never rode one. Looking back, I wonder what I did during all those vacations I had. I played more football, swam more in the streams and generally went around the village. The fact that I did not know how to ride a bicycle did not bother me in the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-frustration&#34;&gt;The frustration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began to notice this fact and get worried about it when I went to college. Where I went to colllege, Yamaha RX 100s were as uncompromise-able part of life as strike actions and political rallies. This realization soon turned in to a fear. I was keen on learning and tried it on numerous occasions in our football field. But college has an uncompromising way of dealing with such lack of abilities, and that meant that there was a big emotional barrier to overcome. I failed miserably. You see, I am kind of tall, and never fell down from a bicycle. I remember trying to ride the bicycle in the ground in pouring monsoon rains. I was not getting it. As the rain around me grew in force and malice, my impatience and frustration multiplied. That was it. I decided that I would never attempt it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite all those failings, the thing that did most to drain my confidence and enthusiasm did not happen on a bicycle. That important place in my life goes to a Mahindra jeep. Back in college, a group of my friends had this really old crazy Mahindra jeep. A lot of people used it to learn to drive or to hone their driving skills. My baggage of experiences (or the lack of it) meant that I never touched the driving wheel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-shock&#34;&gt;The shock&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One fine Sunday afternoon, we were returning after lunch at this awesome, little place that served kerala rice meals and fish. (This place is called &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ashwathi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and I recommend that if you go to Trivandrum, you should totally go there.) One of my friends who was still learning to drive was driving the jeep and it had around 12 of us inside it. Another friend of mine - S - was instructing him. When we reached the hostel and the football field, S continued to instruct the other friend. All of a sudden, I was inspired. I wanted to learn this thing. It certainly had to be less painful than learning to bicycle, I thought. I asked S if he could teach me. S immediately said Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hostel campus has a road that goes around the five or six buildings and the road&amp;rsquo;s sides are dotted with big, tall cedar trees. I climbed to the driving seat and S took the other front seat. My other fiend sat in the back. I started driving the jeep dead-slowly in the football ground. After 5 minutes or so, I was growing confident and suggested that we take it to the road. S okayed it and we began slowly driving on the road around the buildings. My confidence was soaring by now, and I was growing comfortable with the idea that I could control this behemoth of a machine. I went around the buildings four times. We were on the fag end of the road, where a right hand turn would take us to the road that ran parallel to the football field. I took the right turn, and was bringing the steering wheel back to its normal position. The old Mahindra, like its million cousins was a pain to steer. I had passed the curve and I had not yet managed to steer the jeep back to the straight position. There was a huge cedar tree on the right side about 6 meters away. I was going at 20kmph and thought I still had a lot of time to steer it back. My friend sitting in the back did not think so and shouted out that we were headed for the tree. And then, all hell broke loose. I rammed the accelerator down, thinking it was the brake, and the jeep sped in to the cedar tree. I dont remember how fast it was, but it was pretty fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We survived. I had to shell out around 6k to repair the right side of the jeep. I had managed to spectacularly break the bumper, the suspension and the brake on the right side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This incident left me with an absolute terror of vehicles and the road. When we finally managed to get the jeep repaired, my friends advised me to continue learning. I remember sitting there behind the wheels of the jeep in the football field - hands trembling, head shaking and heart racing. The fear of ending up killing somebody on the road and was real and strong. At that moment, I gave up. I decided that I would never attempt to drive in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fascination&#34;&gt;The fascination&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving to Bangalore almost three years ago changed my life in more ways than one. Playing football, the thing around which my days revolved around during college ended up being something I did once in a while. Reaching places where people played football proved to be very difficult. I remember having to hop on two buses to get to IISc. to play a game of football on Sundays and I equally remember a game of football in a ground in JP Nagar being interrupted by one of those ultra-Kannadiga politicians turning up and decreeing that only Kannadigas could play. I did discover this awesome gang that played football everyday at the Koramangala Post Office grounds. I was a regular there for a long time. Walking for 30 minutes at 6:00 AM was proving to be difficult. I really wanted to be able to transport myself to different quarters fast. Bicycle, anyone?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-retry&#34;&gt;The retry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started trying to learn to ride. My brother, who is 11 years younger than me tried to help me. But then, it never took off. The pain and embarrassment of showing off my noob-ishness on a street where the onlookers were people who slightly admired me was too much. The learning sessions lasted about ten minutes each and ended with me being left totally frustrated with myself. This was not going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;and-then-it-happened&#34;&gt;And then, it happened&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to IISc on a Saturday two weeks ago. The desire to learn had returned to me. IISc has a big football field, an my friend suggested that I ride around the field. I rode the bike and after the initial struggling to gain balance, it just came to me. I could do this thing. I was doing it. It was far from perfect, but I was comfortable, and I had balance. As I completed my first round around the football field, I felt the kind of happiness that I have seldom felt in my life. I really could do this. Three hours of riding around the ground and 15 minutes on the road that increasingly looked like the road where I had the jeep accident later, I knew that I had cracked it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-road&#34;&gt;The road&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following Friday I borrowed a friend&amp;rsquo;s bicycle. I was vary excited. I kept on telling people that I had to leave early, lest I end up under one of those sad-looking blue &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bmtcinfo.com/site/index.jsp&#34; title=&#34;BMTC&#34;&gt;BMTC&lt;/a&gt; buses. The memory of riding the bicycle on to the road from the parking lot would live with me forever. It was around 5:00pm and that is not the kind of time when a cycling noob would want to ride on Bangalore&amp;rsquo;s roads. I was afraid, and I was not making up the fear about the buses. But I knew that this time no fear of life or failure would hold me back. In that crazy rush-hour traffic, I rode home. And no, I did not end up under a bus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the following day, I practiced for close to four hours. I was getting very comfortable. And on Sunday, I rode close to 20 kilometers, more than half of it on the Bannerghatta road. There was crazy amount of traffic, I was still afraid of the buses. In fact a blue BMTC bus almost knocked me out of the road. But that had more to do with the driver of the bus being a total moron than me making any mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-crash&#34;&gt;The crash&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was returning from this ride full of pride and a more than healthy dose of confidence. I had rode 20 kilometers on some of Bangalore&amp;rsquo;s craziest roads and had done well. As I approached the place I live, I was riding pretty fast. On the penultimate turn, I sped before I had come out of the curve, and I the bicycle and me crashed hard on the tarmac. From the pain and the amount of skidding my body did on the tarmac and the flight of my spectacles, I guessed it would have been spectacular. I had a bunch of keys in my jeans pockets and one of those decided to embed it&amp;rsquo;s end to my thigh. There was a lot of blood. The pair of jeans survived, and so did my knees and elbows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-aftermath&#34;&gt;The aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I regularly ride the bicycle to the office these days. I still have not mastered it. I am still afraid of the blue BMTC buses. I still get confused when that motherly lady with the small kid decides it is a great idea to step in front of a bicycle. But, what the heck? I will ride the bicycle like I should have 20 years ago - full of pride and joy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poorly executed xkcd spoof</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2011/03/30/poorly-executed-xkcd-spoof/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2011/03/30/poorly-executed-xkcd-spoof/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is not anything to add, except it is a poorly executed attempt to spoof xkcd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-IRlTq69suHw/TZMTwnh2pFI/AAAAAAAACCc/PuUsHXZWOb0/s400/fake_xkcd.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Does this look like XKCD?&amp;quot;&#34; title=&#34;Does this look like XKCD?&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saying Good Bye is tough</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2010/05/10/saying-good-bye-is-tough/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2010/05/10/saying-good-bye-is-tough/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Njaan Varaam, Assalamu Alaikum&lt;/em&gt; (I will be back, Peace Be Upon You). I felt myself choking as those words escaped my mouth. And as I reached the gate and took my first step out, I heard my mother say &lt;em&gt;Wa Alaikum Assalaam&lt;/em&gt; (Peace Be Upon You, too). And then I felt the straps of the laptop bag sink into my shoulders, and it felt so heavy. It should not be. It still had the same stuff as it did when I set on my journey home on the Friday evening. In fact, it should feel lighter, as I had moved some stuff into another bag, which I was holding in my right hand. Sigh! I knew why I choked and the bag felt heavier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been performing this almost teary-eyed, choking Good Bye scene endless number of times, ever since I was 12. The first, if I remember correctly, was when I set on my journey to be part of the residential school which would end up as my world for the subsequent seven years. I remember being sad, and being happy and excited with anticipation at living at the school. My good bye was not drenched in tears, nor were I choking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choking and the tears happened when I was about to return to the school after my first trip back home. I had seen the school, experienced it and quickly had realized that it was not what I wanted. But, I went back, and ever since saying Good Bye to my mother at the gate is an experience that makes me deeply emotional. Even these days, when I know that going back home is as easy as jumping onto a bus. But still, somewhere deep inside me, I can still hear that boy telling me &amp;lsquo;Dude, you wont be back till the next vacation, and you know what? The next vacation is in next May. That is five months!&amp;rsquo;. Those of you who know about my school would understand the significance of those words. For others, &lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/blog/2008/11/12/school-story-the-adult-magazines-and-the-great-raid/&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; would give some idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post school, I went to college at Trivandrum. During the first year, I used to find silly excuses to come home almost every other weekend. I didn&amp;rsquo;t mind bunking classes, just to go home. And after all these trips, I still lived those moments of choking, all over again. I knew, I could be back here the next day, if I wanted to. I knew I was no longer in a &amp;lsquo;jail&amp;rsquo;. Still, it hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days, when I know that nothing would prevent me from getting back home the next weekend, I still feel that choking. I am too old to cry, but it would be a lie if I said that there were no tears lingering in the depths of my eyes. You see, however silly it might seem,for me, saying Good Bye is a big deal and it hurts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Missing the game</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2010/02/05/missing-the-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2010/02/05/missing-the-game/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have continued to watch and follow the beautiful game, save for my first few months in Bangalore. This is supposed to be a metro. Well, apparently a metro where people don&amp;rsquo;t give a damn about football. After taking a cable connection, I soon realized that I will have to beg with the cable guy to put on ESPNStar so that I could watch EPL. Pretty soon, Hathway had some issues with ESPNStar, which meant there was no way I could watch ESPNStar. On the weekends, I tried to pursue the cable operator to put on NEO Sports, at least I could watch Bundes Liga and Serie A. He would not budge, and I had to endure the interesting argument that &amp;ldquo;NEO Cricket and NEO Sports are the same&amp;rdquo;. It was tough to accept - in the small village of Vadakkethala, where I hail from, I could watch as much football as I wanted. In Malappuram, if you are a cable TV operator and don&amp;rsquo;t put on channels with football on, God save you. So Bangalore&amp;rsquo;s apparent indifference to football was frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have enjoyed playing the game since I was a small kid, and that habit too has taken a hit since I came to Bangalore. The first time I went to play on a weekend, a guy with a Red and Gold shawl draped around his neck came to the ground and ordered everyone who couldn&amp;rsquo;t speak Kannada out of the ground. Since then, I have come to realize and acknowledge the power of the Red and Gold colors in Bangalore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do manage to play the game once in a while, mainly at a ground in JP Nagar. I am planning to soon join fellow Malayalees playing in a ground in Koramangala.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for watching Football, I have bought a Videocon d2h which gives me all the sports channels I want, and all the Malayalam channels the diamond pack offers is an added advantage. No more arguments with the cable TV guy about NEO Sports and NEO Cricket being two channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to watch and play a lot of football.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TWU Graduation</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2009/09/22/twu-graduation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2009/09/22/twu-graduation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I had predicted, the last week of training was hectic, chaotic and crazy. Although we ended up leaving the whole project simulation in jeopardy, we learned a lot of things, especially how things that work smoothly at one second can go wrong very very wrong the next second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had decided beforehand that I would volunteer for roles that I want to do in my career, and that at the same time would leave me out of my comfort zone. I played the BA role for two days, and although I made lots of mistakes, I did certain things well. I was appreciated for the e-mails I sent out that day. And I got some nice feedback from the head of training, and I am sure his words will help me in my way forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once BA-ing was out of the way, I was ready for some coding. But it was a learning experience in itself. On the first day of coding, I and pair spent the whole day staring at our monitor wondering why something ridiculously simple did not work the way it was supposed to do. Later in the day, we discovered that it was because somebody had written code that was simply swallowing an exception instead of throwing it up or doing something about it then and there. One feedback that I had got from my Dev trainers had warned me of exactly this sort of a thing happening, and I could see why he was very serious about this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day was luckier for me, as the pair I was part of actually managed to contribute towards completing one functionality. And we were given the t-shirts that we would wear for our graduation from TWU. During the night, I had to spend some time (read the whole night) trying to re-factor the code I had written for my assignment. In the morning, I was too tired, too sleepy and too giddy to wake up and could not attend the project simulation. I turned up in the afternoon, and found all my colleagues having lots of fun, playing dodge-ball. I learned that the project simulation had failed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a graduation ceremony at the office. Receiving the certificate from the MD, wearing our special edition t-shirts and graduation hats was a great experience. I wonder why Kerala University cannot have a graduation ceremony for B.Tech students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_bZ_kjFIgY0w/Srh7h88cjtI/AAAAAAAABQA/uq5OEtmKWkc/s320/DSC06527.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;TWU-14 graduates&#34; title=&#34;TWU-14 graduates&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TWU-14 graduates. I am somewhere in there, even I dont know where I am!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the evening, we had a graduation party at a nice place called &amp;lsquo;Take5&amp;rsquo;. The food was great, and all souls who enjoy alcohol had an even better time. I sat there with my glass of orange juice. While there was party around us in full flow, I had a nice conversation with a co-worker about philosophy and how life is sometimes very unfair. Intellectually stimulating conversation in a not-so-simulating environment! But I had to leave early, as I had to head home and appear at the Regional Passport Office, Malappuram to prove that I was indeed Sadique Ali K M. More about the passport story later!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The university experience was great, and I learned a lot from trainers and co-workers, met lots of interesting people and made friends with some of them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A lot to learn</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2009/08/21/a-lot-to-learn/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2009/08/21/a-lot-to-learn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The past few days have just flown by. I had to learn so much things and did not have much time to do it. Most days, I sleep around 2:00 in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was in college, I had friends who were already working. I used to wonder why sometimes they did not reply to a mail I sent, or did not ping me back when I pinged them on IM. Well, now I know! If any of you are reading this, guys, please pardon me for not understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had an assignment to submit and I got the feedback that the work I had done was &amp;lsquo;Poor&amp;rsquo;. Had a tough time, when I got the response. But having thought about the feedback given to me about the assignment, I now understand that there are a lot of thins I need to learn, there are changes to be made in the way I approach coding, and there are some stuff to be un-learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope I will be able to cope with the pressure and move forward.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yet another week in Bangalore</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2009/08/16/yet-another-week-in-bangalore/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2009/08/16/yet-another-week-in-bangalore/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yet another week of my Bangalore life has unfolded. It was tougher, and better than the first two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned lots of new stuff, stuff that would greatly help me in my profession. I made friends with new people. But most important of all, I got some feedback on some of the things I do in life. It was kind of very scary, to be honest. But then I realized that the feedback will let me improve. I am trying hard to use the feedback in the most positive way possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally was able to enjoy some football. It was the friendly between Netherlands and England. Since England was playing away, Sony Pix did not care to telecast it. I had to listen to BBC Radio 5 Live on the web. It was kind of nostalgic. It reminded of the Saturday and Sunday evenings, when I would sit and listen to the commentary of English Premier League on BBC World Service. The only place where people watched live football was in the local sports club, and I was not allowed to go there after the evenings. So I would sit and listen to the commentary, broken every five minutes by the latest breaking news, alerts on goals in football matches elsewhere, and tennis and golf updates. I think football commentary on Radio is more descriptive and the commentators (at least the better ones) really manage to give you a mental picture of the distribution of players on the field, and the movement of players. The commentary on Radio 5 Live was good too. May be I am biased; the commentary I used to hear on World Service seems to be better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I watched the first day of English Premier Leagues. Chelsea seems to have transformed under Ancellotti; they passed the ball brilliantly. The only flipside for Chelsea fans would have been the sight of Stephen Hunt celebrating the opening goal. A collision with the former Reading winger two seasons ago left Chelsea goalkeeper Petr Cech with an injured head and the Czech still wears protective head-gear while playing. The Stamford Bridge faithful let Hunt know they did not like him by booing every instant he touched the ball. But Hunt did manage to score the new season&amp;rsquo;s first goal. Didier Drogba scored two amazing goals –the first was a breathtaking free kick. The second one looked more like an attempted cross and Drogba admitted it in the post match interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal ran riot against Everton, and they won 6-1. It was sad to see some of the Goodison Park faithful booing David Moyes&amp;rsquo;s team. Wigan beat Aston Villa to earn the first surprise result of the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friends had a get together back at Manjeri. Talked to them while the party was on. Really miss those guys! Wanted to be there.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bangalore Journal</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2009/08/08/bangalore-journal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2009/08/08/bangalore-journal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my 13th day in Bangalore. And the first week of my training at ToughtWorks has gone by. I learned lots of stuff, talked to some great people and made friends with some of them. I still have not overcome the difficulties of adapting to life in the City. May be I will soon, or I never will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had planned to post everyday about my experiences in TWU. But I did not have much time. The sessions last till 5:00 pm, and then I will be very tired to do much. I am really missing football. I had hoped to play with my friend Aneesh on last Sunday, but we were not allowed to play as one old guy who turned up decided that only regulars could play there. Sigh !!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the positive things have been that my flatmate is an amazing person. He is a leftist, and it seems we share the same view on all kind of issues. We have heated and passionate discussions/debates/arguments about all kind of things under the sun -politics, the economy, religion and technology. The fact that we have the same views on almost all issues allows us to go deep in to the subject and have very intellectually simulating discussions. The discussions continue till late in the night. He is a software engineer of tremendous experience, and I hope I will learn some things from him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the personal front, I have a big decision to make, but I am confused like anything. For the time being, I am going to play the &amp;lsquo;wait-and-watch&amp;rsquo; game. Hope things turn out well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The football season is kicking off tomorrow with the FA Community Shield. Looking forward to watching ManUtd in the new kit, with Rooney playing as the striker. The transfer market has almost died down, with Xabi Alonso&amp;rsquo;s move to Madrid being the last significant transfer. Sunderland is splashing lots of money, Darren Bent being the latest player to be on the payroll at the Stadium of Light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happened to read the incredible story of Wimbledon AFC&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/sport/football/news/5989930/AFC-Wimbledon-face-Luton-Town-in-Blue-Square-Premier-after-four-promotions.html&#34;&gt;remarkable rise&lt;/a&gt; through the Football pyramid. The fact that thy are playing Luton Town in the season opener is kind of an irony. Wimbledon AFC&amp;rsquo;s rise and Luton Town&amp;rsquo;s fall epitomizes everything the game of football represents - ecstasy and agony; pain and joy; dizzying heights and demoralizing lows. Good luck to AFC Wimledon! They did a tremendous job of rebuilding after their proud club was &amp;lsquo;moved&amp;rsquo; to Milton Keynes and re-branded as MK Dons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During one of heated debates with my friend, he made the point that the issue of Palestine had become one of &amp;lsquo;my ego&amp;rsquo;. I know I am emotional about Palestine, but is it a matter of ego for me? I am not sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next week will see me and my fellow trainees at ThoughtWorks get some hands-on coding training. I am really looking forward to it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>