<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sadique Ali</title>
    <link>https://sdqali.in/categories/life/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sadique Ali</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <atom:link href="https://sdqali.in/categories/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>First week in San Francisco</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/01/21/first-week-in-san-francisco/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2013/01/21/first-week-in-san-francisco/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I moved to San Francisco last week and is just getting acquainted with
the city. This blog
post is a summary of my first impressions of SF to share with a lot of friends whom I have not been able to keep in touch and who have been wondering what I am up to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;it-is-cold-here&#34;&gt;It is cold here&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I landed in SF without enough winter wear. I had a windbreaker that I
used in Bangalore and provided more than adequate warmth back in
Bangalore. Soon, I realised that it won&amp;rsquo;t be enough. Temperatures were
under 10 C. I had to get a proper jacket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-views-are-stunning&#34;&gt;The views are stunning&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty much wherever you are in the city, you have nice views - the bay,
the Golden Gate bridge or the downtown. As a bonus, the place where
ThoughtWorks put me up has nice views of the bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;vehicles-actually-stop-for-pedestrians&#34;&gt;Vehicles actually stop for pedestrians&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking to work on Bangalore&amp;rsquo;s roads was a tough experience because
nobody waited for the pedestrians to cross and the red signals were
eaten away by bikers eager to squeeze in. Walking on SF&amp;rsquo;s streets is a
pleasant experience. Sidewalks are wide and clean and when you have to
cross the road, vehicles actually stop and let you pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;diversity&#34;&gt;Diversity&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SF is a place with huge racial, religious and cultural diversity. There
is something for everyone here. From the busy people in the Financial
District to the guy selling weed at the Fisherman&amp;rsquo;s wharf to the people
roaming the market street, SF has a lot of variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-golden-gate-bridge-is-magnificent&#34;&gt;The Golden Gate bridge is magnificent&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks stunning in the pictures. It looks even better when you see it
up close.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saying Good Bye is tough</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2010/05/10/saying-good-bye-is-tough/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2010/05/10/saying-good-bye-is-tough/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Njaan Varaam, Assalamu Alaikum&lt;/em&gt; (I will be back, Peace Be Upon You). I felt myself choking as those words escaped my mouth. And as I reached the gate and took my first step out, I heard my mother say &lt;em&gt;Wa Alaikum Assalaam&lt;/em&gt; (Peace Be Upon You, too). And then I felt the straps of the laptop bag sink into my shoulders, and it felt so heavy. It should not be. It still had the same stuff as it did when I set on my journey home on the Friday evening. In fact, it should feel lighter, as I had moved some stuff into another bag, which I was holding in my right hand. Sigh! I knew why I choked and the bag felt heavier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been performing this almost teary-eyed, choking Good Bye scene endless number of times, ever since I was 12. The first, if I remember correctly, was when I set on my journey to be part of the residential school which would end up as my world for the subsequent seven years. I remember being sad, and being happy and excited with anticipation at living at the school. My good bye was not drenched in tears, nor were I choking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choking and the tears happened when I was about to return to the school after my first trip back home. I had seen the school, experienced it and quickly had realized that it was not what I wanted. But, I went back, and ever since saying Good Bye to my mother at the gate is an experience that makes me deeply emotional. Even these days, when I know that going back home is as easy as jumping onto a bus. But still, somewhere deep inside me, I can still hear that boy telling me &amp;lsquo;Dude, you wont be back till the next vacation, and you know what? The next vacation is in next May. That is five months!&amp;rsquo;. Those of you who know about my school would understand the significance of those words. For others, &lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/blog/2008/11/12/school-story-the-adult-magazines-and-the-great-raid/&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; would give some idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post school, I went to college at Trivandrum. During the first year, I used to find silly excuses to come home almost every other weekend. I didn&amp;rsquo;t mind bunking classes, just to go home. And after all these trips, I still lived those moments of choking, all over again. I knew, I could be back here the next day, if I wanted to. I knew I was no longer in a &amp;lsquo;jail&amp;rsquo;. Still, it hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days, when I know that nothing would prevent me from getting back home the next weekend, I still feel that choking. I am too old to cry, but it would be a lie if I said that there were no tears lingering in the depths of my eyes. You see, however silly it might seem,for me, saying Good Bye is a big deal and it hurts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>