<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>{code that works}</title>
    <link>https://sdqali.in/tags/social-network/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on {code that works}</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <atom:link href="https://sdqali.in/tags/social-network/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Dear Content Creator, Your URL Shortener Is Pointless</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/23/dear-content-creator-your-url-shortener-is-pointless/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/23/dear-content-creator-your-url-shortener-is-pointless/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;People love URL shorteners. They are everywhere. You can use one of
&lt;a href=&#34;http://goo.gl&#34;&gt;the giants&lt;/a&gt;, or use one of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly&#34;&gt;URL Shortening As A Service&lt;/a&gt; options available
or you can run one on your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But none of that matters. Apart from adding to the redirect hell
prevalent on the web today and giving you a minor branding push, custom
URL shorteners does not add anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People started using these shortening services because of two
reasons. The first reason was the necessity to share
ugly URLs like
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://example.com/reports.php?start=2001&amp;amp;end=2010&amp;amp;item=Foo%20bar&#34;&gt;http://example.com/reports.php?start=2001&amp;amp;end=2010&amp;amp;item=Foo%20bar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and
they wanted to make it easier on the eyes of people. The second reason
was the limit on the number of characters allowed in a post by micro blogging services
like Twitter and Identi.ca.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once they became popular, people started using it everywhere, even in places like Facebook posts where there were
no limit on the number of characters in a post or comment. People also
started shortening URLs that were not particularly ugly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, the social networks
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/07/17/social-networks-and-url-shorteners/&#34;&gt;got on the game&lt;/a&gt;
and from that point, every single URL shared on those social networks had to go
through one more extra redirect. Some &lt;a href=&#34;http://royal.pingdom.com/2010/09/22/is-the-web-heading-toward-redirect-hell/&#34;&gt;had predicted&lt;/a&gt; this redirect
hell long ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the social networks were setting up their own
&lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.twitter.com/blog/introducing-twitter-web-analytics&#34;&gt;analytics service&lt;/a&gt;
around the URLs their users shared on them, content creators started
using their own custom URL shorteners. The BBC uses &lt;em&gt;bbc.in&lt;/em&gt;, the
Guardian uses &lt;em&gt;gu.com&lt;/em&gt; and Business Insider uses &lt;em&gt;read.bi&lt;/em&gt;. And it is
not just big players in the content space that uses URL
shorteners, this is prevalent among blogs too. For example,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.arabist.net/&#34;&gt;The Arabist&lt;/a&gt; uses &lt;em&gt;arb.st&lt;/em&gt;, which is in turn
hosted by &lt;em&gt;bit.ly&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But once Twitter, Facebook and Google+ came to the table and decided to
take their pound of meat from the redirect hell, all this custom URL
shortening became pointless. These social networks do not expose any data about the
shared URL. In Twitter&amp;rsquo;s case for example, all you as a website know is
that some traffic came to a particular page from a URL that looks like
&lt;em&gt;t.co/Foobar&lt;/em&gt;. If you want to make more sense of the who, when and how
aspects of your content being shared on Twitter, you have to ask
Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the fact that those shortened URLs are &lt;em&gt;short&lt;/em&gt; are does not serve
much purpose because Twitter automatically
wrap a &lt;em&gt;t.co&lt;/em&gt; URL around anything you post to it and show the a link
with the original URL as the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So content creators, please stop running your own URL shortening
services and contributing to the redirect hell. The web will be a better
place for it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I am not on Facebook</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/11/why-i-am-not-on-facebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/08/11/why-i-am-not-on-facebook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday a colleague of mine asked me if I was on Facebook. He
was genuinely surprised by my reply that I was not and he wanted to know
 why. For the next 20 minutes or so, I explained to him why I quit
 Facebook and does not want anything to do with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not the first time I have had to explain my absence from Facebook. In this post I will explain my attitude towards Facebook in a more structured manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broadly, these are the points I will touch upon:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Narcissism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Symmetric nature of sharing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The social pressure to &amp;lsquo;friend&amp;rsquo; someone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low signal to noise ratio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;narcissism&#34;&gt;Narcissism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have observed that Facebook makes people a lot more narcissistic than
they are in their real life. Facebook does this by providing a
convenient avenue to channel people&amp;rsquo;s self-love and then use the social
pressure of the system to create incentive for people to use this
avenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an example that explains this well. I have seen people go to beautiful hill-sides and instead of enjoying
the nature around them, they start shooting photos of themselves with
the scenery in the background. This is a carefully executed ritual and
involves careful posing and choosing spots that maximises potential
&lt;strong&gt;Likes&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Comments&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have done this and observed a lot of people do it. Looking back, I
wish  had spent that time observing and appreciating the beauty of the
scenery around me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, one might point out that generating content as a fodder
for social networks is endemic to all social networks and no just
Facebook. This is where the lure of the &lt;strong&gt;Likes&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Comments&lt;/strong&gt; and the
social pressure to gather them comes in to play. Being able to generate
&lt;strong&gt;Likes&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Comments&lt;/strong&gt; becomes closely tied to your identity on
Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;symmetric-nature-of-sharing&#34;&gt;Symmetric nature of sharing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook relationships are fundamentally symmetric i.e. if &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; is your
&lt;strong&gt;Friend&lt;/strong&gt;, then you are &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;Friend&lt;/strong&gt; as well. This is drastically
different from the way relationship manifest in Twitter. The issue with
this symmetric relationship is that if &lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt; would like to consume the
content that you post to Facebook, he will have to be your &lt;strong&gt;Friend&lt;/strong&gt;
which immediately results in you having to consume content posted by
&lt;strong&gt;X&lt;/strong&gt;. This becomes increasingly annoying if you do not particularly like
cat pictures but Bob who likes cat pictures would likes to view the
photos you share. All of a sudden, you find yourself staring at cat
pictures from Bob.
Facebook later introduced asymmetric sharing with the concept of
&lt;strong&gt;Subscribe&lt;/strong&gt;, but unless you were a celebrity, you still got friendship
requests from people who would like to view your posts.
There is an obvious solution to this problem - just don&amp;rsquo;t accept that
friendship request from Bob. But unfortunately, this is easier said than
done, for the reason I talk about next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-social-pressure-to-friend-someone&#34;&gt;The social pressure to &amp;lsquo;friend&amp;rsquo; someone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You get a friendship request from Alice who is a colleague. You do not
necessarily consider Alice a friend and you do not share common
interests. At that point you find yourself having to accept Alice as a &lt;strong&gt;Friend&lt;/strong&gt; on Facebook because of the social
pressures associated with it.
You could be clever and ask Facebook to hide the updates from Alice, but
then you have to be an expert who knows where exactly Facebook decides
to hide the settings that allow you to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;low-signal-to-noise-ratio&#34;&gt;Low signal to noise ratio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could be a manifestation of the large number of people on Facebook
and the relative esoteric and geeky nature of other social networks I
use, like Twitter. I have observed that my Facebook home page contained
a lot of noise compared to my Twitter stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find useful content on Twitter whereas my Facebook home page showed me
a lot of obscure photo-shopped images, animated GIFs and useless FUD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;quitting-facebook&#34;&gt;Quitting Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After suspending, deleting and re-creating my Facebook profile once I
deleted it for good in July, 2011. I let people whom I consider as
friends know that I would be available on my phone and through email. I
started calling up my friends instead of &lt;strong&gt;Liking&lt;/strong&gt; their updates and
photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blocking-facebook&#34;&gt;Blocking Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a well known fact that Facebook tracks people on the web using the
myriad of widgets, plugins and buttons they have managed to spread to
most of the web. My response has been to block anything to do with
Facebook. I use the cheap and simple way of using my &lt;strong&gt;/etc/hosts&lt;/strong&gt; to
accomplish this. After many changes, this is how the Facebook related
part of it looks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34; style=&#34;background: #f0f3f3&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;line-height: 125%&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;127.0.0.1 facebook.com
127.0.0.1 fbcdn.com
127.0.0.1 fbcdn.net
127.0.0.1 login.facebook.com
127.0.0.1 static.ak.connect.facebook.com
127.0.0.1 static.ak.fbcdn.com
127.0.0.1 static.ak.fbcdn.net
127.0.0.1 www.facebook.com
127.0.0.1 www.fbcdn.com
127.0.0.1 www.fbcdn.net
127.0.0.1 www.login.facebook.com
127.0.0.1 www.static.ak.connect.facebook.com
127.0.0.1 www.static.ak.fbcdn.com
127.0.0.1 www.static.ak.fbcdn.net
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current incarnation is adapted from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://nonzen.in/2012/06/17/etchosts.html&#34;&gt;Sajith Sasidharan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There. That is my Facebook story.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Networks and their URL Shorteners</title>
      <link>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/07/17/social-networks-and-their-url-shorteners/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sdqali.in/blog/2012/07/17/social-networks-and-their-url-shorteners/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been noticing lately that much of the traffic that my blog
receives comes from Twitter&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;t.co&lt;/strong&gt; domain or Google+&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;strong&gt;plus.url.google.com&lt;/strong&gt; domain. I don&amp;rsquo;t receive much traffic and I don&amp;rsquo;t
particularly care about the amount of traffic. However, when I
see traffic from Google+ or Twitter, I know that somebody is discussing
or sharing my posts and I am curious to know who is doing that. But if I
look at where the traffic comes from, with the hope that I will be able
to find Tweets or Google+ updates where people are talking about my
content, all I would be able to see is a &lt;strong&gt;t.co&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;plus.url.google.com&lt;/strong&gt;
URL that redirects to my page. While it is mildly frustrating, I have
been thinking why both Twitter and Google+ replace every URL users share
on their network and replace it with their own URLs that does a redirect
to the original content being shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I finally understand why. Data about user&amp;rsquo;s sharing content is
of huge interest to a lot of people, most importantly marketers. URL
shortening services like &lt;a href=&#34;http://bitly.com&#34;&gt;bit.ly&lt;/a&gt; have been able to
come up with some interesting analysis about content sharing trends. The
difference now is that the social networks themselves have taken over
URL shortening and by way of that capturing and hiding user&amp;rsquo;s sharing
habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this scenario. You find something interesting on the web that
you would like your followers and friends to see. It could be a new interesting
startup, a programmer&amp;rsquo;s rant, a tutorial, a new framework or the
Internet&amp;rsquo;s most favourite thing - cat pictures. You have a browser
plugin that nicely shortens the rather long URL and gives you a new
&lt;strong&gt;bit.ly&lt;/strong&gt; URL. You share it on Twitter. Twitter does not post the nice
&lt;strong&gt;bit.ly&lt;/strong&gt; URL. Instead, it converts it into a &lt;strong&gt;t.co&lt;/strong&gt; URL that redirects
to the &lt;strong&gt;bit.ly&lt;/strong&gt; URL. From that point onwards, all &lt;strong&gt;bit.ly&lt;/strong&gt; knows is that
a lot of people are sharing a particular &lt;strong&gt;t.co&lt;/strong&gt; URL. Unless they figure
out where the &lt;strong&gt;t.co&lt;/strong&gt; URL redirects to or does a Twitter search for the
URL, they don&amp;rsquo;t have a clear idea of who shared the URL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the impact of this, lets look at another
scenario. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/HonestFrank&#34;&gt;Francis Keogh&lt;/a&gt;, a journalist
with the BBC shares a piece of Football transfer news on Twitter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/e2tqA.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Screenshot of tweet saying &#39;West Ham close on deal to sign Mali striker Modibo Maiga&#39;&amp;quot;&#34; title=&#34;Screenshot of tweet saying &#39;West Ham close on deal to sign Mali striker Modibo Maiga&#39;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He obviously uses a shortened URL generated with BBC&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;bbc.in&lt;/strong&gt;
shortener. BBC, being the media company they are have huge interest in
knowing who shares their content, when and where. But all that their
analytics system setup around &lt;strong&gt;bbc.in&lt;/strong&gt; will be able to tell is that a
lot of traffic is coming from the URL &lt;a href=&#34;http://t.co/a0Sh34av&#34;&gt;http://t.co/a0Sh34av&lt;/a&gt; which is not of much use to
them because it strips the &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt; aspects of the act of
sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now here comes the money part of it. There is somebody who has full
knowledge of this sharing - Twitter. They know who, when and where the
content was shared by. If media companies and others want to figure out
who shares their content, you have to ask Twitter. And it looks like to
me that Twitter won&amp;rsquo;t give that information away easily. Twitter could
charge these companies and I would think that there will be a lot of
companies interested in buying this data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I showed an example of how Twitter does this, Google+ does
something very similar. And I would assume Facebook does the same with
its &lt;strong&gt;fb.me&lt;/strong&gt; URL shortener. I am not sure, and I can not verify because I
don&amp;rsquo;t have a Facebook account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, social networks that are about sharing hides knowledge
about the content people share behind a system that only they have
access to and can potentially make a lot of money from that data. Pretty
clever of them, if you ask me.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>